<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of independency the fourth and last part : continued from the death of His late Majesty, King Charls the First of happy memory, till the deaths of the chief of that juncto / by T.M. Esquire, lover of his king and country.</title>
            <author>T. M., Esquire, lover of his king and country.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W331A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18043</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12349003</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12349003</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59927</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66882)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59927)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 903:40)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of independency the fourth and last part : continued from the death of His late Majesty, King Charls the First of happy memory, till the deaths of the chief of that juncto / by T.M. Esquire, lover of his king and country.</title>
                  <author>T. M., Esquire, lover of his king and country.</author>
                  <author>Walker, Clement, 1595-1651. History of independency.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 124 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Brome ... and H. Marsh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Fourth part of Walker's The history of independency, added by T.M.; published with preceding three parts in one volume in 1661.  Cf. DNB, v. 20, p. 505.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Variant edition of Wing W331.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Roundheads --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59927:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF Independency.</p>
            <p>The Fourth and laſt Part.</p>
            <p>Continued from the Death of his late MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IESTY, King CHARLS the Firſt of happy Memory, till the deaths of the chief of that <hi>Juncto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By T.M. Eſquire, a Lover of his King and Country.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cicero Epiſt. Lib. 2. Ep. 3.</hi>
               </bibl> Civem mehercule non puto eſſe, quitemporibus his ridere poſſit.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Id. Lib. 5. Ep. 12.</hi>
               </bibl> Habet autem praeteriti doloris ſecura recorda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio delectationem.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Brome</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> in <hi>Ivie-Lane;</hi> and <hi>H. Marſh</hi> at the Princes Arms in <hi>Chancery-Lane.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59927:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59927:2"/>
            <head>Moſt Dread Soveraign.</head>
            <p>IT is neither arrogance nor ambition that makes me thus boldly to intrude into your preſence, for I know ſo great a Sun will quickly dazle my weak eyes, but becauſe the former parts were honoured with your royal Fathers name, this therefore hopes to be ſheltered under your Princely wing, this but concluding what they begun, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king you the happy repayrer of thoſe Breaches, which that powerfull and reſtleſs faction of Independency made on the <hi>Regalia</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> that poſterity may as well ſee, in this, their felicity, by you, in the ruine of that faction, as formerly they read their own miſery, in the Treaſonable actings thereof, againſt his late Majeſty of ever glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious memory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> have no more but only to pray, that you may in this World be bleſſed with the
<pb facs="tcp:59927:3"/>wiſdom, and happyneſſe of <hi>Solomon,</hi> a peaceable, long and all glorious Reign: the age of <hi>Methuſelah,</hi> wherein you may enjoy the full contents of a moſt happy life, and at laſt full of honour and dayes arrive to the perfect fruition of a more glorious Kingdom, in Gods preſence, before whom is fullneſs of joy, and at his right hand plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for evermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>This from his ſoul is the daily prayer of Your Majeſties moſt faithfull ſubject and Servant.</hi> T. M.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>29</hi> Oct. <hi>1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59927:3"/>
            <p>TO THE <hi>SACRED MAJESTY</hi> OF Great BRITTAINS MONARCH. (<hi>The Triumphant Son of a most Glorious Father, who was in all things</hi> More than Conquerour.) The Illuſtrious ofspring of a Royal Traine of ANTIENT PRINCES CHARLES The Second of that Name, Entituled PIOUS By the ſole Providence of an Almighty hand, of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> King, Defender of the Faith.</p>
            <p>Reſtorer <hi>of the</hi> Engliſh Church <hi>unto its</hi> Priſtine State <hi>and</hi> Glory.</p>
            <p>Patron <hi>of</hi> Law <hi>and</hi> Liberty, Not to be Seconded by any but himſelf, Who <hi>is the beſt of Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of all Vertue to the World THE GRAND EXEMPLAR</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59927:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the</hi> Nobility, Gentry, Clergy <hi>and</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>IT is I think more out of cuſtome than neceſſity, that I do at this time premiſe any thing, the Subject whereof we treat, having been fatally felt by moſt of the Nation in ſome way or other, yet is it neceſſary that the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſuch turgencies in the State ſhould be communicated, that poſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity may hereafter ſee, in their riſe and fall, the certain puniſhment of Treaſon, though for a time guarded and upheld by armed violence, and the higheſt policies of a ſubtle malice.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid of the <hi>Epicureans,</hi> that, though they acknowledged no providence, nor any immortality of the ſoul, and propoſed pleaſure as the only end of their lives, yet they maintained (most of them) that they that were lovers of pleaſure, muſt of neceſſity be lovers of Justice, and that without virtue it was not poſſible for men to live intrue pleaſure, So as it was ſaid of the <hi>Stoicks</hi> (who were for the most part notable hypocrites) that they ſpoke good things, and did foul actions, but that the <hi>Epicureans</hi> ſpoke and taught things that ſeemed foul and ſhamefull, but did that which was fair and honest.</p>
            <p>Certenly theſe two ſects of Phyloſophers might be the very pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of our date times, wherein our Stoicall Grandees could ſpeak nothing but holineſs, where the practice of their lives was a continued ſeries of horrid Treaſons, while a litle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent mirth and freeneſs of ſpeech was the greateſt that lay, or indeed could be caſt, upon integrity of their deſpiſed Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſts: ſo that we might ſee <hi>Cucullus non fecit Monarchum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It had been well for <hi>England</hi> if the ſad occaſions of writing
<pb facs="tcp:59927:4"/>this hiſtory of the times had never happened: but they have been: And, as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Offences muſt come, but wo be to them by whom they come,</hi> ſo then to declare the actings, and their method and manner, is but ſo to lay them open, that they may for the future be the better avoided and prevented.</p>
            <p>The knowledg of all perſons, the meaning of all matters,
<note place="margin">Voſſ. de ſeri Agt. &amp; de art. hiſtor.</note> and the depth of all ſecrets, is lockt up in hiſtory according to that of <hi>Voſsius,</hi> alluding to that of the Roman Poet,
<q>
                  <l>Qui quid ſit turpe, aut pulchrum, quid utile, quid non</l>
                  <l>Plenius &amp; melius Chryſyppo &amp; Crantore dixit.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And this I dare promiſe you in the enſuing Manual; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out too violent reflections to widen differences: all the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations ariſing as naturally from the relations, as ſuteable words do fitly ſupply the ready tongue of a Learned Oratour.</p>
            <p>It is the general happineſſe at this preſent, that we can, read the downfall of faction, and rejoyce in the glory of reſtored Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty with ſafety and content; and I pray God, that all the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs of the remaining <hi>Achitophel's, Shimei's</hi> and <hi>Rabſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keh's,</hi> may ſall upon their own heads: but peace, happineſs and proſperity, may waite on our <hi>Solomon,</hi> that he may be bleſſed, and his throne be establiſhed, before the Lord forever.</p>
            <p>To Conclude; As your Loyalty in the worſt, oftentimes hath been ſignal (if in nothing elſe yet in ſufferings) ſo diſpiſe not to read this tractate, wherein, I dare preſume, you will find ſomething which before you knew not: the work, 'its true is ſhort, but will not, I hope; want ſubſtance, <hi>ineſt enim ſua gratia parvis;</hi> and to remember theſe things certainly cannot be irkſome—
<q>—Saepe recordari medicamine melius omni.</q> to ſee and eſcape danger cauſeth, not only admiration but plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: which that you may receive with content by the peruſall hereof is deſired.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59927:5"/>
            <p>I ſhall only add one word in particular, firſt to the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; You are Right Honourable Princes in the Congregation of our Iſrael, Men of renown, exemplarily both in your names and honours. Be as eminent in ſervice for your Prince, as obliged to him for favours, that it may be recorded of you as it is of Davids Worthies. Theſe are the mighty men which <hi>David</hi> had, who ſtrengthened themſelves with him in his Kingdom, according to the word of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> To the Gentry, You are they whom <hi>Jethro</hi> counſelled <hi>Moſes</hi> to provide out of all the people to aſſiſt him, and be mediatours between Prince and People; approve your ſelves according to that counſel to be able men, ſuch as fear God, men of truth and hating covetouſneſs, ſo ſhall the Lord give a bleſſing as he hath promiſed.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> To the Clergy, God hath made you as a Beacon upon an hill, that you might forewarn <hi>Iſrael</hi> of her ſins, ye are the ſalt of the Earth, while you preach to others be not your ſelves caſt away, but in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon labour, labour to declare Chriſt not of contention and ſtrife, but ſowe the word to effect that fruit may grow thereby.</p>
            <p>And Laſtly to the Commons, who are <hi>tumidum &amp; inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile vulgus:</hi> I ſhall only wiſh that they will labour for peace, and, according to their Royal Princes dictate in his late Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration concerning Eccleſiaſticall affairs, acquieſce in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcentions concerning the differences which have ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted the Sate: by which endeavour all good Subjects will by Gods bleſſing enjoy as great a meaſure of felicity as this Nation hath ever done; which is the earneſt prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your, &amp;c. <hi>T. M.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>No. <hi>2. 1660.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59927:5"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF Independency.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Fourth and Laſt part.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE former parts of this Book having traced the prevalent and ſtrong Factions of <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian</hi> and <hi>Independent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eme.</note> through the ſeveral devious pathes wherein they marched, and with what devilliſh cunning they did, each, endeavour to be greateſt, by ſurpriſing, or at leaſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the other, until at laſt they unriveted the very foundations of Government, by the execrable murther of their undoubtedly lawful Soveraign, a crime ſo abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that it is even inexpiable, not to be purged with ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59927:6"/>for ever: I ſay, theſe things having received ſo live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a delineation in the former parts, ſhall need no new recitalls. I ſhall then begin at the end thereof, which was; when the ſacred Reliques of betrayed Majeſty, <hi>ſpecie juſtitiae,</hi> received a fatal ſtroke from blood-thirſty hands, neither able to protect it ſelf, or be a ſhadow and <hi>Aſylum</hi> for rejected Truth, and unſpotted Loyalty. Thus in an unſetled and confuſed poſture ſtood poor <hi>England,</hi> when the Sceptre departed from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Royal Lyon was not only robbed of, his prey, but his Life: which Barbariſm once committed, what did the Independent Faction, now grown chief, ever after ſtick at? Having taſted Royal Blood, the Blood of Nobles ſeemed but a ſmall thing: to which end, and to heighten and perfect their begun villanies, they erect another High Court of Juſtice, for the Tryal of <hi>James</hi> Earl of <hi>Cambridge, Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Holland,
<note place="margin">Lords <hi>H H. C.</hi> try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> George</hi> Lord <hi>Goring, Arthur</hi> Lord <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,</hi> and <hi>Sir John Owen</hi> Knight: whereof that Horſlecch of Hell, <hi>John Bradſhaw,</hi> was alſo Preſident, who with ſixty two more (as honeſt men as himſelf) by a Warrant under the hands of <hi>Luke Robinſon, Nicholas Love,</hi> and <hi>J. Sarland,</hi> ſummoned for that purpoſe, did accordingly appear upon <hi>Munday</hi> the fifth day of <hi>February,</hi> 1648. for the putting in Execution an Act of Parliament (as they called it) for the erecting of an High Court of Juſtice, for the trying and adjudging the Earls and Lords aforeſaid; with whom (according to their fore-ſettled reſolution) making ſhort work (for they would admit of no plea) of the five they preſently condemned three to loſe their heads on a ſcaffold in the Pallace-yard at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lords condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> on <hi>Friday</hi> the ninth day of <hi>March:</hi> which day being come, about ten of the clock that Morning, Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Beecher</hi> came with his Order to the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59927:6"/>ſeveral Priſoners at S. <hi>James</hi>'s, requiring them to come away; from whence they were immediately hurried in Sedans, with a ſtrong guard, to Sir <hi>Thomas Cottons</hi> houſe at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where they continued about two hours, ſpending the whole time in holy devotion and religious exerciſes. After which the Earl of <hi>Cambridge</hi> preparing firſt for the Scaffold, after mutual embraces, and ſome ſhort parting expreſſions to, and for, his fellow-ſufferers, he took his leave, and went along with the Officers, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended on by Dr. <hi>Sibbalds,</hi> whom he had choſen for his Comforter in his ſad condition. Being arrived at the Scaffold, and ſeeing ſeveral Regiments both of horſe and foot drawn up in the place: after he had waited a little while with a fruitleſs hope and expectation of receiving ſome comfortable news from the Earl of <hi>Denbigh</hi> who was his Brother; having ſent for his Servant, who being returned, and having delivered his Meſſage to the Earl of <hi>Cambridge</hi> privately, he ſaid, <hi>So, It is done now:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> ſpeech at his death.</note> and turning to the front of the Scaffold he ſpake to this effect. <hi>That he deſired not to ſpeak much, but being by providence brought to that place, he declared to the Sheriff, that the matter he ſuffered for, as being a Traytor to the kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>he was not guilty of, having done what he did by the command of the Parliament of his own Countrey, whom he durſt not diſobey, they being ſatisfyed with the juſtneſſe of their procedure, and himſelf by the commands by them laid upon him; and acknowledging that he had many wayes deſerved a worldly puniſhment, yet he hoped through Chriſt to obtain remiſſion of his ſins. That he had from his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy profeſſed the ſame Religion eſtabliſhed by Law in the land. That, whereas he had been aſperſed for evil intents to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the King, all his actions being hypocritically diſguiſed to advance his own ſelf-intereſt: hereto he proteſted his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59927:7"/>profeſſing he had reaſon to love the King, as he was his King, and had been his Master, with other words to the ſame effect. That, as to the matter of invitation into the kingdom, he referred himſelf to the Declaration then in Print; and ſetting forth how ready and willing he was ever to ſerve the Engliſh, wiſhing happineſſe and peace to them, and praying that his blood might be the laſt that ſhould be drawn, heartily forgiving all, ſaying, I carry no rancour along with me to the grave. That his Religion was ſuch as he ſpoke of before, whoſe Tenets he needed not to expreſſe, as being known to all, and himſelf not of a rigid opinion, being not troubled with other mens differing judgments; with which words, and forgiving all that he might have even the greatest animoſity againſt,</hi> he kneeled down with Dr. <hi>Sibbald,</hi> and prayed with much earneſtneſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion: which pious exerciſe performed, and ſome ſhort ejaculations paſſing between himſelf and the Doctor, the Earl turning to the Executioner, ſaid, <hi>Shall I put on another cap, and turn up my hair? Which way is it that you would have me lye, Sir?</hi> The Executioner pointing to the front of the Scaffold, the Earl replyed, <hi>What, my head this way?</hi> Then the Underſheriffs ſon ſaid, My Lord, the Order is, that you lay your head toward the High Court of Juſtice. Then the Earl, after ſome private diſcourſe with his ſervants, kneeled down on the ſide of the Scaffold, and prayed a while to himſelf; afterwards with a ſmiling and cheerful countenance he embraced the Doctor in his Arms, and then his ſervants, ſaying to them, <hi>Ye have been very faithful to me,</hi> and <hi>the Lord bleſſe you:</hi> then turning to the Executioner, ſaid: <hi>I ſhall ſay a very ſhort prayer while I lie down there, and when I ſtretch out my hand, (my right hand) then, Sir, do your duty, and I do freely forgive you, and ſo I do all the World.</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59927:7"/>So lying down, and having fitted himſelf,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hamilton</hi> execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> devoutly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to himſelf a ſhort ſpace, he ſtretched out his right hand, whereupon the Executioner, at one blow, ſevered his head from his body, which was received by two of his Servants, then kneeling by him, into a Crimſon Taffeta ſcarfe; and that with the body immediately put into the Coffin brought thither for that purpoſe, and ſo carried to Sr. <hi>John Hambletons</hi> houſe at the <hi>Mewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Execution done, the Sheriffs guard went imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to fetch the Earl of <hi>Holland,</hi> whom they met in the midway, where the under Sheriffs ſon having received him into his charge, conducted him to the Scaffold, Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> paſſing all the way hand in hand, with him. Being come upon the ſame, and obſerving he could not ſpake aloud enough to be heard by the People, by reaſon of the numerouſneſs of the Souldiery that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed him, he ſaid.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hollands</hi> ſpeech on the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</note> 
               <q>I think it is to no purpoſe to ſay any thing; then proceeded. That his breeding had been in a good family, that had ever been faithfull to the true Proteſtant Religion, in which he had ever lived, and now reſolved by Gods grace to dye. That he hoped God would forgive him his ſins, though he acknowledged his Juſtice in bringing him thither for puniſhment of them in this World. He obſerved, that he was looked on as one that had ill deſigns againſt the State. Truly <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> I look upon it as a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not having offended the Parliament in any thing, ſave an extreme vanity in ſerving them very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily. That his affections had been ever known to be faithfull, and without wavering: where the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament wrought changes beyond and againſt reaſon and Religion, there He left them. That he ever ſought the peace of the Kingdom, and that made him do
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59927:8"/>what he did. That he knew not how to judge of (the th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n) preſent affairs; but ſhould pray, that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome might be again governed by the King, by the Lords, by the Commons: and that the People may look upon the Poſterity of the King with that affection they owe: that they may be called again without blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and admitted into that power and glory that God in their birth intended to them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>That he wiſheth happineſs even to the cauſers of his death, praying heartily to God to forgive them. And as Chancellor of <hi>Cambridge</hi> really praying, that that Univerſity might flouriſh, and be a continuall Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery both to Learning and Religion. Then mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning again his Religion and family, relating ſomething to his own behaviour, and his being a great ſinner, yet that he hoped God would hear his prayers, and give him faith to truſt in him,</q> with his prayers for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he ended. Then turning to the ſide, he prayed for a good ſpace of time: after which by the inſtigation of Mr. <hi>Bolton,</hi> he ſaid. <q>That he was the leſs troubled with his violent death, when he remembred how his Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſuffered for him; and again, when he conſidered the King his Maſter not long before paſſed the ſame way; with others at this time with himſelf, with a ſerious and pithy juſtification of his ſaid Maſter the late Kings Majeſty, a ſhort recapitulation of his firſt ſpeech con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Actions, Religion, breeding and ſufferings. After all, wholly caſting himſelf, on the merits and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Jeſus chriſt forgiving his Enemies, praying for peace, and that their blood might be the laſt, which was ſhed ſtrangely, the tryall being as extraordinary as any thing in the Kingdom:</q> but be owned it as Gods hand: then having, ſome divine conference with Mr.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59927:8"/>
               <hi>Bolton</hi> for neer a quarter of an hour, and ſpoken to a Souldier that took him priſoner and others, he embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Lievtenant Collonel <hi>Beecher,</hi> and took his leave of him. After which he came to Mr. <hi>Bolton,</hi> and having embraced him, and returned him many thanks for his great pains and affection to his ſoul, he prepared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the block: whereupon turning to the Executioner, he ſaid; <hi>here my friend, let my Cloaths and my body alone, there is ten pounds for thee, that is better than my cloaths,
<note place="margin">His beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</note> I am ſure of it. And when you take up my head, do not take off my cap:</hi> then taking his farewell of his Servants, he kneeled down and prayed, for a pretty ſpace, with much earneſtneſs.</p>
            <p>Then going to the front of the Scaffold, he ſaid to the People, <hi>God bleſs you all, God give all happineſs, to this Kingdom, to this People, to this Nation.</hi> Then laying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf down, he ſeemed to pray with much affection for a ſhort ſpace, and then lifting up his head (ſeeing the Executioner by him) he ſaid, <hi>ſtay while I give the ſigne</hi> and preſently after ſtretching out his hand, and ſaying, now, now; juſt as the words were coming out of his mouth,
<note place="margin">E. of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> death.</note> the Executioner at one blow ſevered his head from his body.</p>
            <p>The Execution of the Earl of <hi>Holland</hi> being thus performed, the Lord <hi>Capell</hi> was brought to the Scaffold as the former: and as he paſſed along, he put off his hat to the People on both ſides, looking about him with a very ſtern countenance; when mounting on the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold having before taken his leave of his Chaplain, and bidding his Servants that were with him to refrain from weeping, coming to the front of the Scaffold,
<note place="margin">Lo. <hi>Capell</hi> his ſpeech before hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> death.</note> he ſpoke to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <q>That he would pray for thoſe that ſent him thither,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59927:9"/>and were the cauſe of his violent Death; it being an effect of the Religion he profeſſed, being a Proteſtant, with the profeſſion whereof he was very much in love, after the manner as it was eſtabliſhed in <hi>England</hi> by the 39. Articles. That he abhorred Papiſtry, relying on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on Chriſts merits. That he was condemned to dye contrary to the Law that governs all the World, that is, by the Law of the Sword, the Protection whereof he had for his Life: yet among Engliſhmen, he an Engliſhman acknowledged Peer, condemned to dye contrary to all the laws of <hi>England.</hi> That he dyed (as to the cauſe he fought in) for maintaining the fifth Commandement, injoyned by God himſelf, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Country, the King, as well as the natural Parent being to be obeyed thereby. That he was guilty of Voting againſt the Earl of <hi>Strafford;</hi> but he hoped God had waſhed off the guilt of his blood with the more precious blood of his Son. That his late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty was the moſt vertuous, and ſufficient known Prince in the World. God preſerve the King that now is, his Son. God ſend him more fortunate and longer dayes. God reſtore him to this Kingdom, that that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily may reign till thy Kingdom come; that is, while all Temporal power is conſummated. God give much happineſs to this your King; and to you that in it ſhall be his ſubjects. That he did again forgive thoſe that were the cauſers of his coming thither from his very ſoul: ſo praying again for the King and his reſtoration, and for the peace of the Kingdom, he finiſhed his ſpeech.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then turning about to the Executioner,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L. C.</hi> his carriage.</note> he pulled off his doublet; when the Heads-man kneeling down, Lord <hi>Capell</hi> ſaid, <hi>I forgive thee from my ſoul, and ſhall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59927:9"/>pray for thee; There is five pounds for thee, and if any thing be due for my cloaths, you ſhall be fully recompenced. And when I ly down, give me a ſhort time for a prayer:</hi> then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain bleſſing the People very earneſtly, and deſiring their prayers at the moment of death, he ſaid to the Executioner, <hi>you are ready when I am ready, are you not,</hi> then as he ſtood putting up his hair, with hands and eyes lift up he ſaid. <hi>O God, I do with a perfect and a willing heart ſubmit to thy will.</hi> O <hi>God, I do most willingly hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my ſelf,</hi> ſo kneeling down, and fitting his neck to the block, as he lay with both his hands ſtretched out, he ſaid, <hi>When I lift up my Right hand, then ſtrike.</hi> When af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had ſaid a ſhort prayer,
<note place="margin">L. <hi>Capell</hi> behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> he lifted up his right hand, and the Executioner at one blow ſevered his head from his body, which was taken up by his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and put into a Coffin.</p>
            <p>Having thus brought to paſs their bloody purpoſe, ſhortly after they acquitted the Lord <hi>Goring,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Owen</hi> as to their lives, but ſeized upon all they had: according as they did upon moſt of the Eſtates of the Nobility and Gentry throughout <hi>England;</hi> for ſuch now was their unſatiable malice,
<note place="margin">The bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> that they thought it not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ruine and deſtroy the heads of Families; but, with divelliſh rancor, endeavour to blot out the name and memoriall of Poſterity, by ſuch unheard of cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and barbarous actions, as would make a Savage <hi>Scithian</hi> or <hi>Barbarian</hi> bluſh to think on, ſo that we may ſay with <hi>Cicero</hi> in the like caſe; <hi>Rem vides, quomodo ſe habeat: orbem terrarum Imperiis distributis ardere bello: urbem fine legibus, ſine judiciis, ſine jure, ſine fide relictam direptioni, &amp; incendiis.</hi> Which indeed is the very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent caſe.</p>
            <p>Thus did they grow from bad to worſe, acting rather
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59927:10"/>like butchers then Men, each one of them proving to all about him, a devouring wolfe, whoſe inſatiate gorge was never filled with his pray, ſo that having in effect the maſtery of them (whom they called their Enemies) like true thieves they fall out about parting the ſtakes:
<note place="margin">The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent cloſe</note> the Presbyterian faction will brook no ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, the Independent no equall, upon theſe terms ſtands the Kingdom divided, when the later grown now more powerfull by the additon of the Army, whoſe guilt in the murther of the King had ſuggeſted to them, that the only way to ſave and raiſe themſelves, was to confound and reduce all things elſe to an Anarchy. In purſuance of which Principle they at laſt proceed againſt the very root of Monarchy: and after many uncouth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates reſolved, that the Nation ſhould be ſetled in the way of a free State,
<note place="margin">Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</note> and Kingly government be utterly aboliſhed. Now was the ſtile in all proceedings at the law altered, the ſeals changed, and the Kings armes and ſtatues in all places taken down, that ſo their ſeared con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences might not at the ſight thereof be terrified, with the ſad remembrance of their committed crimes. And that no ſparke or attendant of antient Majeſty might be left remaining, ſoon after, they vote the houſe of Lords to be burdenſome and uſeleſs:
<note place="margin">Lords houſe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</note> and that the People might underſtand their meaning alſo, on the 21th. of <hi>February</hi> they proclaim at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and ſend it to the City the next Day to the like purpoſe, but the then Lord Mayor refuſing to do it, as being contrary to his honour, conſcience and Oath, rather choſe to ſuffer an unjuſt impriſonment, which he did in the <hi>Tower:</hi> Any honeſt Man would have thought this example would have put a ſtop to the attempt of any villain for the making that proclamation, but ſo farr were they from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59927:10"/>being deterred, that they rather grow more implacable, and having found ſome hair brained, and half decayed, Cittizens, out of them, one is ſet up as a mock-Mayor, who being a fellow fit for their turns, after a ſhort com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement or two with the Juncto:
<note place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation againſt Kingſhip.</note> he enters the Stage and Proclaims, the aboliſhing of Kingſhip, and the Houſe of Lords. Having thus brought their deſign to ſome kind of maturity, they find another invention to be as a Shibboleth, a mark of diſtinction, between them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and other men,
<note place="margin">The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement a mark of diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and that was the engagement forſooth, whereby every man ſhould promiſe to be true and faithfull to the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a King or houſe of Lords, and he that would not ſubſcribe to this, was forced either to fly, or which was as bad, to ſtay at home, and have neither the benefit, nor the protection, of the law of the land, nor any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage either of his liberty or Eſtate; Now might you have ſeen <hi>Vice regnand,</hi> and nothing but Schiſme and faction Countenanced, now might you have beheld <hi>England,</hi> ſometime the Glory of the World, now become its by words, the name of Engliſh being among forreign Nations eſteemed as a crime ſufficient, ſo did the Land mourn for oaths that ſhe was ready to vomit out her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, while the Juncto ſtill endeavour to palliate their villany, and to get allies among neighbour Princes and States, to many of whom they ſend Embaſſadours (as they ſtiled them) and were again reciprocally cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and owned, and particularly by the Spanyard and the French; but the Dutch did ſeem to be Men of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mould and temper,
<note place="margin">The dutch quarrel.</note> and therefore having no better ground they quarrell for ſuperiority; denying to vaill to the Engliſh, becauſe they were the younger State, yet ſtill owning that reſpect to the Monarchy: hereat the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59927:11"/>Engliſh (though yet but an) Embrio begin to ſtartle, and weighing the unſetledneſs of their baſis, and that all they had hitherto done was only dawbed together with untempered morter,
<note place="margin">St. <hi>Johns</hi> ſent to treat, but returnes without doing any thing.</note> they reſolve to try all wayes rather then fall out, and will ſeek to gain that by Courtſhip, which they are unwilling to hazard by force; as a fit Man for this work they pick out a pure Saint, Mr. <hi>Oliver,</hi> St. <hi>Johns,</hi> and diſpatch him into <hi>Holland</hi> with, as large a train, as great State, and as full inſtructions as they could poſſibly afford or invent, whether when he is come, he makes his addreſſe to the Lords States, but with ſo little approbation and ſucceſs, that in a little time he began to grow weary of his buſineſſe, eſpecially, when the multitude began to grow clamourous againſt him, inſomuch that he durſt hardly ſtir abroad, ſo that being both outworded, and outwitted, after many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, brotherly expoſtulations, Declarations, and hearty deſires to ſmall (or rather indeed to no) purpoſe, he gravely makes his Congee, takes his leave and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth; The Juncto at his teturn, ſomewhat diſcontented at his fruitleſs Embaſſie, yet finding no other remedy, and willing to make the beſt of a bad market, prepare for war, (for by this time the Dutch had begun both to affront them and ſeize on what they could catch as lawfull prize) which ſo vexed the Engliſh Puny State, that they preſently fall to an open war, the various ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of which, and the loſſes that accrewed thereby toeach party by means of the ſame, I ſhall not make the work of my pen, having only deſigned to delineate thoſe black deeds of impiety acted within the narrow limits of our <hi>England,</hi> by the horrideſt crew of bloody miſcreants that were ever ſpared by Divine vengeance from ſudden deſtruction.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59927:11"/>
            <p>The Engliſh affairs and Government being thus wreſted into the hands of a few deſperate perſons,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ireland</hi> looked at.</note> the next thing aimed at is, the reducing of <hi>Ireland:</hi> for ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting whereof they give a Commiſſion to,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſent to <hi>Ireland</hi> and prove Victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> and raiſe an Army under the Command of, <hi>Cromwell,</hi> which he as ſuddenly tranſports thither, <hi>Ormond</hi> and <hi>Inchequeen</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at that time all the Country in obedience to his Majeſty, (ſave only <hi>Dublin kept</hi> by Col. <hi>Michael Jones,</hi> and <hi>London-derry</hi> by Sir <hi>Charles Coot</hi>) when lo, as it were to wellcome <hi>Cromwell, Jones,</hi> immediately before his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival, had made way for him by the overthrow of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> forces about <hi>Dublin:</hi> And now, as if fortune had already deſigned him the laurell, St. <hi>Charles Coot,</hi> in an other place at <hi>Londonderry,</hi> worſteth a Second party, and the Earl of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Inchequeen,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving joyned their broken froces into a conſiderable ſtrength, are again together overthrown at <hi>Connaught.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The concatenation of theſe ſucceſſes, together with the cruelty exerciſed by <hi>Cromwell</hi> at the taking of <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagh</hi> by ſtorm, where his rage ſpared neither age nor ſex, a barbariſm ſcarcely uſed by the very Turkes, caſt ſuch a Panick fear over the whole Nation, that the ſtrong holds fell into his power, like over-ripe fruit into the prepared hands of its ready gatherer.</p>
            <p>So hidden and miſticall is the ſeries of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that for a time, the moſt enormous crimes are counted vertues, &amp; the poor looſing honeſtfoul conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſtoop and bow under the heavy yoke of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing tyrant; yea Majeſty it ſelf enforced, (like the clouded Sun) compulſively to hide his beams, and retire with his light for a while, as though it had been but borrowed, but as the Sun, ſo Majeſty can never be kept in perpetuall darkneſs: for by this time the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59927:12"/>who had for a ſpace been chief, find a Competitor of the Leveller,
<note place="margin">The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to ſtir.</note> who reſolves either to ſhare in the whole, and ſo reduce and keep all in an equality, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by himſelf may be one of the greateſt, or elſe to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to bring back all into its originall channel, and to ſhew they meant as they ſaid, with better hearts then ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs or ſtrength they riſe in three or four places, for they are aſſoon quaſht as ſeen, and themſelves and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign end both together: A garment of linnen and wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len was forbidden to be worn by the Leviticall law, and I ſuppoſe becauſe the mixture would be improper either for wearing, or handfomneſs of ſight, in the ſame manner may I ſay of the Levelling faction, that though they in intent were reall for reſtoring the King, yet God would not ſuffer it to be brought to paſs by ſuch hands, that had been ſo deeply dyed before in royall blood. The royal party though under hatches, and now ſuffering for their loyalty, having paſſed and been refined in the fire of affliction muſt be the Men, whoſe unſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fingers ſhall not only pull down the Idolized Babel of the Peoples imagination, but repair the decayed ruines of our broken Government, and reinſtate exiled Majeſty upon its throne adorned with ſafety, and with beauty both, and guarded with the ſafeſt ſtrength of faithfull hearts and hands, better then walls of braſs or formed troops of mercenary Souldiers.</p>
            <p>But that time was not yet come,
<note place="margin">Scots ſend to the King.</note> although the Scots ſent a peculiar meſſenger, the Lord <hi>Libberton</hi> to the King, deſiring him among other things, that he would pleaſe to appoint a place for a Treaty to be between his Majeſty and his Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which offer of theirs, was graciouſly accepted, and a Treaty appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Breda,</hi> on the 15th. of <hi>March,</hi> whither the Scots
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59927:12"/>Commiſſioners came the 16th. and on the 19th. fell to their buſineſs, neither would by any means relinquiſh their Presbytery though but in part, and as to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon of the King himſelf, whom they ſtrongly bound up to the Covenant, Directory and Catechiſmes,
<note place="margin">Treaty at <hi>Bredah</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> where to his Majeſty; after many long and ſeriuos debates, having unwillingly conſented. The Scots on their part did promiſe. 1. That his Majeſty ſhould be admitted to the throne of <hi>Scotland.</hi> 2. That his Rights then ſhould be by Parliament, recovered from the hands of Uſurpers, and 3. That they would aſſiſt to bring the murtherers of his Father of bleſſed memory, to condigne puniſhment, and to reſtore him to his Native Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A happy, Omen, ſurely was this promiſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking hoped to be, and ſo indeed it might have proved, if it had been gained from any but the worſt of Scotch-men, the Presbyterians, for, at the very ſame time as it were, when they had concluded the Treaty, and thus highly promiſed the King as is before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I ſay at the ſame time, having gotten the famous Marqueſs of <hi>Montroſs</hi> into their hand, whoſe only fault was Loyalty to his Prince, having brought him with as much ignominy as they could deviſe to <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> they there charge him for keeping away the King (obſerve the King was now upon the point of coming to them) from his ſubjects. 2. For the invading that Kingdom. 3. For all the murders in the war, and for waſt upon <hi>Argiles</hi> Eſtate, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Mark, here I pray,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Montroſs</hi> murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thereof.</note> 
               <hi>Montroſs</hi> muſt be murthered (the beſt ſubject the King had in <hi>Scotland</hi>) and juſt when the King is ready to come thither, (as if it were done in deſpight to him) but why? for keeping away the King?
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59927:13"/>No, he had promiſed to be with them with all ſpeed, which <hi>Montroſs</hi> in priſon could not have hindred. Was it for invaſion? alas neither, for he had none but his own Countrymen, and of them but a very few and they quickly, and eaſily defeated; what, was it for then, for muder? alas neither, what then? O! here's the Divel that murthered the famous <hi>Montroſs,</hi> for waſte upon <hi>Argiles</hi> Eſtate; <hi>Argile,</hi> I ſay that underminer of his Soveraign, who in a ſhort time after, upon his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival, was by the means and inſtigation of him, upon pretence of non-performance by the King, left deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute either of friends (whom they baniſhed from his Court,)
<note place="margin">The K. in <hi>Scotland.</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld to hard meat.</note>) means, (which they curtailed him of) and ſtrength (allowing him neither a Souldier nor a gariſon, nay not a town where he might with ſafety repoſe his head); things being at this paſs, and his Majeſty with much adoe gotten into <hi>Scotland</hi> as afore ſaid, which the Juncto at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> having perfect intelligence of, and weighing with themſelves that promiſe of the Scots, to bring the murtherers of the Kings Father, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dign puniſhment, they begin to think it high time, to provide for their own ſafety, in conſulting whereof, after much time ſpent, it is reſolved the ſafeſt, wiſeſt, and to them leaſt chargeable courſe to wait, on the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in his own Country, whereby they carried the war from home, and not to ſtay for him to bring it to their own doors.</p>
            <p>As a ſtrong motive to this, juſt at the inſtant, they diſcover that many of the Presbyterians of <hi>England,</hi> had by their agents agreed with the Scots at <hi>Bredah,</hi> to re-eſtabliſh his Majeſty in all his Dominions: Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many eminent perſons are ſeized on, and among them, Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jenkins,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jackſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59927:13"/>Which Mr. <hi>Love</hi> together with one Mr. <hi>Gibbons</hi> ſuffered death together on <hi>Towerhill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed.</note> at the earneſt ſute of <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> proteſting he would not march into <hi>Scotland,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they were cut off: Being moved hereby as well as by their own fear and guilt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cromwell</hi> invades <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </note> his Majeſty is ſcarce in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but <hi>Cromwell</hi> is at the borders with 16000. Horſe and Foot, on their behaſt; to whom <hi>Leſlly, L.G.</hi> of the horſe, which were now raiſed, after ſome expoſtula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by Letters and Declarations, ſends word that he is in armes upon the account of the good old cauſe, and not upon the account of the King,
<note place="margin">Scots di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> whom he cleerly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned; <hi>Straughan</hi> and <hi>Ker,</hi> not only diſown the King, but ſay poſitively they will fight againſt him, ſo that now it was not <hi>Bellum Regale,</hi> a war to maintain the Kings honour, and the points of the treaty, but <hi>bellum Presbyteriale,</hi> a war for the Kirke of <hi>Scotland,</hi> againſt the Independent faction of <hi>England</hi> (thoſe two great parties being come now to a ſecond conteſt for ſuperiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) for <hi>Leven</hi> commanded the Foot, and <hi>Leſlly</hi> as I ſaid before the horſe, and theſe two unaminouſly drew out againſt <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and fought him within ſix miles of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> though to little purpoſe,
<note place="margin">1. Fight at <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</hi>
               </note> for he immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after became Maſter of the field, and took Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, as faſt as he came to them, defeating them at <hi>Muſſelbourgh,</hi> and purſuing them to <hi>Pentlan-hills,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Fight at <hi>Muſ. ſelbourgh.</hi>
               </note> where the Scots had him in a ſtraight, and might have deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, but the cerrainty as they thought of the victory, cauſed them to delay, by which, and the fatal neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſickneſs, hunger and cold preſſing upon <hi>Cromwells</hi> Army, made them chooſe rather at one fight deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to hazard all, then timourouſly to become the ſcorn of an inſulting foe, which they knew they ſhould find: following this reſolve with diligence, they whiſper about
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59927:14"/>the word to each other, in the midſt of a dark and rainy night, they crept up the hill and fell on the Scots ſo ſuddenly and beyond expectation, that they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered by the firſt attempt,
<note place="margin">3. <hi>Dunbar</hi> fight and totall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat.</note> yet by reaſon of, their mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, and a little courage, they held up a while, till ſurrounded on the back by <hi>Cromwells</hi> horſe, the Scots horſe affrighted, begin to retreat, and ſoon after to flie in good earneſt, leaving their foot to mercy, who were taken in greater numbers then the Engliſh Army con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of; the Independent power by this victory being abſolute conqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rors,
<note place="margin">King in the North of <hi>Scotl.</hi> private.</note> and the Presbyterian pride laid groveling in the duſt.</p>
            <p>During this quarrell between the ſaid two factions, the King (as diſowned ſo) not intereſted therein, retires firſt to St. <hi>Johnstons,</hi> and after that, privately into the North of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where he conti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ued, expecting what God would do for him; aſſuring himſelf that this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat at <hi>Dunbar</hi> (as things then ſtood) could not be for his prejudice which indeed,
<note place="margin">King ſent to and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes.</note> quickly fell out accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his expectation; for the Scots upon that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw were ſomwhat humbled in Spirit, and now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan again to think of their late abuſed King, wiſhing in their hearts he were among them, (fearing to ſpeake the truth) leaſt he would have joyned with Northern and loyal Highlanders, to prevent which they ſend <hi>M. G. Montgomery</hi> with forces to intreat his Majeſties return, who finds him out, and affectionately delivers his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: which the King received even with joyfull tears, as minding the juſtice of God upon thoſe perfidious Scots, whoſe pride in ſucceſs carried them beyond all bounds of allegiance (and like a ſtubborn child muſt be ſoundly whiptere they will kneell and the good manners they obtain muſt be beaten into them): Yet he accepts
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59927:14"/>of their requeſt, and accordingly goes towards them. Who but ſo good a King would have expoſed himſelf to ſuch mens truſt, in ſo dangerous a time? <hi>Innocentia est ſibt munimentum,</hi> for he reſolves to return.
<note place="margin">King crowned.</note> Upon notice hereof and his arrivall, the Parliament addreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to him, and appoint the time for his Coronation: which was accordingly with much State, pompe and Ceremony, performed on the firſt of <hi>January</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Schone;</hi> the particulars whereof I ſhall not enter upon, ſeverall relations thereof being already extant.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty thus inveſted in his throne, undauntedly proceeds to ſecure both his perſon and Kingdom:
<note place="margin">K. raiſeth an army.</note> to which end he begins to raiſe and levy an Army, both of horſe and foot, which in ſhort time, by the conflux of loyal hearts from all parts, became even formidable to its Enemies, eſpecially having their Prince engaged in perſon, (whoſe every hair was valued at ten thouſand lives) and an equall ſharer with them in all things. As they did encourage the hearts, and ſtrengthen the hands of all that were faithfull, ſo they were a torment of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to the inſulting Enemy, who for the preſent, ſeeing that force alone would not ſerve the turn, politickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves, to undermine and weaken them by diviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, knowing that rule to be true, <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de &amp; impera,</hi> and indeed ſo it proved:
<note place="margin">Scors di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided.</note> for with ſo much divelliſh cunning did the Engliſh work, that they procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Straughan</hi> with ſome ſorces together with <hi>Ker</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt the King, Laſtly with others, ſtand for Kirk and King. But <hi>Brown, Middleton,</hi> &amp;c. with the beſt and honeſt part of the Army, vow to ſacrifice their Lives and Eſtates in defence of the Kings perſon. In this tottering and unſtable condition ſtood affairs, when <hi>Cromwell</hi> alwayes mindfull to lay hold on the firſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59927:15"/>and being certainly informed of the height and heat of theſe diviſions, he takes time by the forelock, and ſtriking while the Iron was hot, he ſends to <hi>Straughan</hi> and wins him over to him, to fight againſt his lawfull Soveraign, rejoycing to have debauched ſuch a Souldier, whoſe infidelity muſt now make him ſure to <hi>Cromwell,</hi> not daring to rely on the good of thoſe whom he had ſo trayterouſly deceived; the remaining two parties, continuing yet in their feuds, are at length, to prevent the deſtruction of both,
<note place="margin">The roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts and Kirk re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couciled.</note> by the care of the Parliament then ſitting taken into conſideration, and reconciled by the equal diſtribution of commands, upon the moſt eminent perſons of both factions; under one only head and Generall commander, which was the King himſelf. By this union being again become conſiderable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea and indeed in a poſture of defence, the King deliberately ſets forward toward the Enemy, who hearing of it, with more, both fury and expedition marcheth to meet him. And here you might have obſerved the different means uſed by two potent armies to deſtroy each other, <hi>Cromwell</hi> would ruine the King by fighting, the King endeavours to conquer <hi>Cromwell</hi> by delaying: never were <hi>Hanniball</hi> and <hi>Fabius</hi> ſo truly patterned as at this time, for the King knowing it to be an invading Army, took the beſt means to break it by delayes, getting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all proviſion, that the Enemy might have no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and as occaſion ſerved, giving ground, till ſome notable advantage might be found, as might give an hopes if not an aſſurance of a victory; and according to expectation ſo had it proved, for being deſirous to fight,
<note place="margin">Fight in life.</note> and hearing the King intended to paſs at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain narrow Iſland, thither he commandeth two Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt whom <hi>Brown</hi> did march with five or ſix,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59927:15"/>fell on them, and in probability had deſtroyed them ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, had not relief come with ſpeed, and in the nick of time, whereby after a hot and eager fight for ſome hours, both parties retreated with no ſmall loſs to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet ſuch was the fortune of that ambitious wretch <hi>Cromwell,</hi> that notwithſtanding this, and that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty had ſtill a good Army in the field, he over-ran the whole Country and conquered with leſs difficulty than he marched; which his Majeſty perceiving, he reſolves on new deſignes, and accordingly within a ſhort time, with his choyſeſt friends and the remains of his Army amounting to 16000. he privately,
<note place="margin">K. march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es into <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> gives <hi>Cromwell</hi> the go-by, and marches by <hi>Carliſle</hi> into <hi>England:</hi> ſo have I ſeen a bird decoy the greedy fowler from her loved neſt, by a ſeeming neglect thereof in the retiring from it.</p>
            <p>It was generally believed that the Kings arrivall in <hi>England</hi> would have been a motive to all that loved him to ſtir and ſhew themſelves in armes for his defence, but ſuch was their hard fate and ſad miſery at that time, that they durſt not ſtir, the yoke lay ſo heavy, that it was impriſonment if not death, but to look towards the King, yet maugre all devices againſt him,
<note place="margin">K. wins <hi>Warring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> bridg.</note> he came through all the North into <hi>Warrington</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> where at a bridge the paſſage was diſputed with the Enemy, who did endeavour to break it down, but with ſuch advantage, that the Rebells were forced to fly and leave the King maſter of the place,
<note place="margin">Comes to <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
               </note> from whence with his whole Army he marched towards <hi>Worceſter,</hi> where contrary to the rules, both of reaſon and war, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his own mind and reſolution, overſwayed by the treacherous Counſel and perſwaſions of ſome too neer, and in too great command about him, he ſtayed. what might be the motives to delude the King into ſuch
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59927:16"/>a trap the <hi>L. G.</hi> is better able to give account off than my pen; but where treaſon lies in the heart, there muſt all things of force be bad, no relations, ties, or duty can hold or convince him who hath ſold his conſcience. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this time, the whole Kingdom, having taken the Alarum, run in troups and multitudes, ſome one way, ſome another, ſeverall of the Gentry, particularly the Earls of <hi>Derby</hi> and <hi>Cleveland,</hi> the Lord <hi>Howards</hi> El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Son, Collonel <hi>Howard,</hi> with many others bring what ſtrengths, in ſuch a confuſion of affairs and ſtreight of time, they could gather together, but to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpoſe: for they are as it were beſieged within the City of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> all the Counties of <hi>England</hi> having powered out their auxiliary forces againſt that place, to heighten and increaſe whoſe malice <hi>Cromwell</hi> is ſent to head them. Now might you have ſeen <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate</hi> reconciled, and both againſt Chriſt: Thoſe two reſtleſs and adverſe factions, the Presbyterian and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent faction, could joyn together, both in their armes, and prayers againſt his ſacred Majeſty, belching forth the ſcandalous language of their ulcerous tongues to incenſe the People, and bring them into frenzy againſt thoſe few poor deſpiſed loyall ones, &amp; ſo indeed they did; thoſe very pretended Miniſters not only preaching, but largely contributing to the raiſing of more forces from day to day, yea ſome of them going in perſon to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſinate the poor incloſed Royaliſts, who yet reſolved, that though they foreſaw their ruine, as not being able without a miracle to cope with ſuch an innumerable multitude, they would ſell their lives at a dear rate, and make ſome of the purchaſers at leaſt ſhare in an equall fate with them, and ſo in truth they did. For <hi>Cromwell</hi> now being very neer, commands <hi>Lambert</hi> to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59927:16"/>take and ſecure <hi>Hopton</hi> bridge,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Worceſter.</hi> fight.</note> in the defence of which paſſage <hi>Maſſey</hi> ſhewed both much courage and experience, though forced to retreat thence and leave the ſame unguarded, being over-powered with <hi>Lamberts</hi> multitudes: after which, for a Day or two, there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened diverſe Skirmiſhes with as various fortune as is uſuall at ſuch times; but <hi>Cromwell</hi> not brooking ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes (as fearing they might prove dangerous, if any part of his forces ſhould bethink themſelves) reſolves upon one generall attempt: and to find work for all hands, himſelf falls on upon one ſide, and <hi>Fleetwood</hi> on the other, ſo that now ther's nothing but rage, ſlaughter, and blood, the loyall Highlanders even ſtanding to fight when they had loſt their legs, not at all daunted at the ſeverall horrid ſhapes-Death preſented himſelf to them in, but covering the ground with their ſlaughte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red bodies, in death made good that place, which in life they undertook to defend: while the increaſing En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emy by his numbers, rather killing then conquering, their fear and guilt guiding them to exorbitances, which the other valiant, though dying ſouls were not capable of, proving that maxime true, that fear is farr more painfull to cowardiſe, than death to a true courage. But <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tum est,</hi> their end is concluded, the decree is gone forth: ſo after ſeverall routs and rallies, a generall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat ſucceeds with the death of between 4000. and 5000. and about 7000. or 8000. taken priſoners, the purſuite being both hotly and eagerly purſued, each villain hoping to enrich himſelf by ſeizing on the Royal pray. But Heaven had ſent a Guardian Angell to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect him, that at length he may once more come and be the reſtorer, both of our peace, Religion, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. I ſhall not mention the means were uſed, or the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59927:17"/>Spirits which God raiſed up to be inſtrumentall, in that miraculous deliverance, let it ſuffice they have their honour and reward, and bleſs we God; who hath made us worthy to be partakers of the ineſtimable good that hath accrewed thereby, invoking Heaven to crown his life with length of dayes and health, and to ſettle his throne by a decree as unalterable as that of the Earth which cannot be moved.</p>
            <p>Thus once more we ſee Rebellion flouriſh and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded; for after this, the ſeeds of ambition begin to grow higher in <hi>Cromwell,</hi> it is not enough that his facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the ſtrongeſt, and he the head of it, unleſs he may as well govern as command: The military ſword will not ſatisfie him, he muſt and will alſo have the civill, but as he ſees it muſt not be done raſhly or ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, leaſt he ſhould miſcarry, ſo knowing that fair and ſoftly goes farr, and <hi>festinare lente</hi> is the beſt haſt, he concludes in his heart either to have all at his own beck, or dye in the attempt; and the better to moddell his deſign according to his reſolution, he comes to the Juncto, gives them account of all his tranſactions, and ſo inſinuates into them that he gets his Son <hi>Ireton</hi> to be made Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cromwels</hi> policy and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> and intruſts <hi>Scotland</hi> into the hand of <hi>L. G. Moncke,</hi> a revolted Cavalier, by which two perſons in a ſhort time he ſo roughly handled both thoſe ſaid Nations, that they were redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to as perfect a ſlavery as could be imagined.</p>
            <p>Upon conſideration of theſe ſucceſſes on all hands, he begins now more publickly to unmask himſelf; As General he places and diſplaces Officers in the Army at his pleaſure, untill he have ſo fitted them to his own humour, that he dares begin to take them into his Councill, where the firſt thing reſolved is, ſtill to hold
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59927:17"/>up the mask of religion, there is no bait ſo catching to the vulgar: religion therefore muſt be cried up, methinks I ſee <hi>Cromwell,</hi> like <hi>Catiline</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> with all his crew of bankrupt and much worn Officers about him, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them thus. Surely I need not tell you the great things the Lord hath done for us, your ſelves are wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes thereunto: I confeſs, our actions ſeem not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to our profeſſions, but tis no matter, let People ſay what they will, ſo we be ſtill gainers, let Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments totter and fall, the whole World be made but one Enthuſiaſme, or reduced into its primitive <hi>Chaos,</hi> rather than we ſhall now looſe or hold, yet ſtill the mask of zeal muſt be kept on that we may not appear in our naturall colours, villains <hi>ab origine;</hi> By theſe and the like words is that vicious brood ſoon inſtigated to act what his ambition dares command.</p>
            <p>Now was he grown ſo lofty and imperious that he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven growes weary of the Juncto, and eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were at the preſent the main barr that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred his greatneſs: To remove therefore that obſtacle, on the twentieth of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1653.
<note place="margin">Long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment turned out.</note> early in the morning he ſeazes the keys of the Parliament houſe, ſhuts up the doors, and tells the Members that they muſt come no more there, having already ſate too long, meriting rather puniſhment than applauſe, being no other than an aſſembly of Whoremaſters, Drunkards, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, Knaves and Oppreſſours; thus was the pretence of the Parliament taken away, and no face of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment viſibly appearing: Never was the faults of Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers with more bitterneſs laid open than now by him, whom we ſhall ſhortly, as tranſcendently, to out-do them in all acts of Tyrauny and Uſurpation, as the brighteſt beams of a midday ſun excell the glimmering
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59927:18"/>light of a midnight candle. Tis true as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la tam modeſta est faelicitas ut malignitatis dentes vitare poſſit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sen.</hi> ep. 3.</note> there ever was and ever will be ſome murmurers at preſent Governours, but ſo far were either they, or he from being belyed, that unleſs a Man do ſpeak all that may be imagined evill, he muſt needs fall ſhort of their wickedneſs,</p>
            <p>The Government being thus altered, firſt by laying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide and murthering their lawfull Soveraign, then by ſifting and purging the Parliament, till looſing its origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, it either became as nothing, or at the beſt but a Juncto, and when it would no longer ſute with <hi>Cromwells</hi> ambitious ends and ſoaring thoughts, by turning it ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely out of doors; At laſt after much pretended ſeeking of God by dayes of humiliation, <hi>Cromwell</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth is counſelled to call together an aſſembly of men, picked out and called as fit for his deſign. Theſe he ſummons together by a Letter under his hand and ſeal directed to each ſingle Man;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Barchones</hi> Parlia ment.</note> who (in their way of can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) admiring at the great goodneſs of God, that had put it into the Generalls heart to ſelect them to ſo great a work as the ſettlement of the Kingdom, and to ſhew their skill, and as an Eſſay of their zeal, they firſt vote down all Tythes, diſcourage the Miniſtry, abuſe the Univerſities, and endeavour to aboliſh the law, and conſequently to take away all propriety. By which Acts the Nation beginning to be ſenſible of the Divel, where with they were poſſeſſed, did frown upon them, which ſo diſanimated our Fanatick Enthuſiaſts, that at the very firſt blaſt they left the helm, and like good boyes and well-taught, having drawn up formally an inſtrument under their hands and Seals, they repair to <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and (according as the deſign was laid) together with the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59927:18"/>ſaid inſtrument deliver and reſign the Government to him and his Councill,
<note place="margin">They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to <hi>Cromwell</hi>
               </note> who (though at firſt he ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denyed) yet immediately after, with much ſolemnity he accepts thereof, before the Mayor, ſome Aldermen, ſome Judges, and the Officers of the Army. Having thus far perfected his devilliſh deſign, and made all his own, by modelling the Army under the command, of his own Creatures; ſetling the Government of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> upon his Son <hi>Harry,</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> reduced to obey and ſubmit to him:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cromwels</hi> firſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</note> It is now thought fit he ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himſelf, which to pleaſe and gull the people the better, he does by abaſing himſelf, and calling (as he termed it) a Parliament, to meet on the Third of <hi>September</hi> 1654. Which it did, but the poor animalls not having well conned their leſſon before-hand, were, ſuſpected dull, and turned a grazing to get more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, the very firſt inſtant he might lay hold on to do it; By which means once more all pretence of Government being utterly aboliſhed, he himſelf playes Rex, and by an arbitrary power beyond, without,
<note place="margin">Major Gen. ſet up.</note> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, law, doeth what he liſt, by Mayor-Generals (a name in <hi>England</hi> unknown) oppreſſing the Country, robbing the Gentry, ſpoiling all, and murdering many, ſo that none durſt ſay what doeſt thou? A queſtion was converted into a plot, and to deny a tax merited de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimation. It was not enough, to have ſuffered all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer rapines, impriſonment and plunderings, fines and taxes, but at laſt we muſt all be decimated. We were <hi>tanquam Oves</hi> deſtined for ſlaughter, and ſuch was our miſery there was none to redeem: ſad teſtimonies whereof were <hi>Gera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, Grove</hi> and others about this time, whoſe blood only could expiate a crime they never thought or were guilty off.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:59927:19"/>
            <p>In this unlimited poſture of arbitrary power did the the Kingdom ſtand, when that Arch-Machiavilian <hi>Cromwell</hi> adding ſtrength to the wings of his ambitious mind ſoared an Eagle-height, and made all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of his actions to center at the royall State, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a graſp of the Scepter to ennoble his name and family, not minding either the danger of the paſſage or the ſlipperrineſs of the ſtation, when arrived at the top: And indeed ſuch was his fortune that he did aſcend the throne, in which it was for the future, his reſtleſs endeavour to ſettle himſelf and his poſterity, and the better to caſt a ſeeming gloſs of legality upon his uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cromwels</hi> ſecond Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment confirm him as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector.</note> he ſummons another Parliament, in the Year 1656. hoping thereby to work his ends unſeen, and ſo he did (as to the vulgar eye) for ſoon after their meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and firſt triall of their temper, he ſo moulds them to his own humour by a recognition, that they are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſtily delivered of a ſtrange abortion, by them called the petition and advice, &amp;c. in which with much ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, though damnable hypocrifie, they deſire him to be King, but in more general terms to take upon him the government, and be chief Magiſtate, which he very gravely conſidering of diverſe dayes, returnes his denyall, in part, but withall inſinuates in part, his willingneſs to be ſetled Lord Protector, at which newes his faction rejoycing, (with many Eulogies for his humility in refuſing the Kingſhip) he is by the ſaid Parliament, who adjourned for the ſame end, ſolemnly inſtalled Protector at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> by <hi>Widdrington,</hi> who was the Speaker to that convention, by <hi>Whitlock, Liſle, Warwick,</hi> &amp;c. And upon their reſiſting, he is petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to accept of almoſt two millions, by the year for his ſupport, to maintain a crew of idle wenches his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59927:19"/>daughters, whoſe pampered luſts were grown almoſt inſatiable) 2. To erect a new houſe of Lords of his own Creatures, who being indebted to him for their raiſing, durſt do no other than by a ſlaviſh ſubmiſſion, perform his tyrannous will, 3. To name his ſucceſſor, that ſo he might entail his yoke of tyrannical Uſurpation and ſlaviſh oppreſſion on the Kigdom, and ſeverall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things: which with much adoe, after many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive intreaties and much unwillingneſs, God knowes) he accepts of.</p>
            <p>No ſooner is this done,
<note place="margin">The ſaid Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</note> but the fox laughs in his ſleeve to ſee how he has cheated the Parliament. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to make them know their rider, after a few words of exhortation to them of the want of them in the Country, and the neceſſity of their retiring thither for the peace of the Nation, with a friendly nod he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſeth them and ſends them home.</p>
            <p>Thus with much cunning and diſſimulation having attained the perfection of his deſires,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſeeks to ſtrongth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> knowing that ſuch greatneſs muſt be upheld with allies, and every no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble coat of armes muſt have his ſupporters, he ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens himſelf at home, by intermixing with noble blood marrying own of his Daughters to the Lord <hi>Faulcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> and an other to the heir apparent of the Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Warwick,</hi> the later of which though in the prime of his your<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, finding the diſagreement between Noble and Rebell blood, was ſoon over-heated and by the ſuddenneſs of his death left his wife the widow of a loathed bed. In the next place he ſeeks friendſhips and leagues abroad, and intending to cloſe with <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> he directly quarrels with the <hi>Spanyard,</hi> and affronts him in ſeverall places near about one time, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſends one part of the Fleet under the command
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59927:20"/>of <hi>Pen</hi> to <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> but with ſo little diſadvantage that he was enforced to retreat thence, with no ſmall loſs, falling ſoon after on <hi>Jamaica</hi> with better ſucceſs, win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a part thereof, though moſt inconſiderable, the whole Iſland being not worth the tenth part of the blood and treaſure it hath coſt this Kingdom, being no way at all ſerviceable, either for the advance or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of trade in thoſe parts; <hi>Mazarine</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> finding the benefit of theſe helps, upon the very firſt motion ſtrikes with him a league offenſive and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, <hi>Cromwell</hi> promiſing to aſſiſt the French with 7000. Men to maintain the war againſt the <hi>Flanders:</hi> which at this time he ſent, they proving ſo helpfull by their valour, that in a ſhort time they gain <hi>Mardike,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dunkirke</hi> gained.</note> Gravelin,</hi> and <hi>Dunkirke,</hi> the laſt of them according to articles, being delivered up to the Engliſh, in whoſe hand it yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains. In the <hi>interim</hi> while theſe things were tranſact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſuſpicious of every blaſt of wind, and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of every motion, contrives in himſelf to take off two or three of the moſt eminent of the Kings party in <hi>England</hi> to daunt the reſt, among whom he ſeparates one layman, Sir <hi>Henry Slingsby,</hi> and one Churchman, Dr.
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its</hi> death.</note> 
               <hi>Hewit,</hi> for the ſlaughter: and conſcious to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that they had done nothing contrary to the law of the land, he durſt not try them by a Jury, but re-erects his monſtrous high Court of Juſtice; before which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought, they denyed the authority thereof as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable, which ſo wrought upon the patience of Mr. <hi>Liſle</hi> their bloodily learned Preſident and the reſt of the gange, that they (according as they were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſtructed by their Maſter Divell <hi>Oliver</hi>) without any great matter of circumſtance condemne them both to be beheaded, which ſentence was accordingly executed,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59927:20"/>on them the 8th. Day of <hi>June</hi> at <hi>Towerhill,</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the means their friends could uſe of engagements, perſwaſions and money, and the deep, earneſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued intreaties, ſollicitations and ſupplications of Mrs. <hi>Claypoole</hi> his beſt beloved daughter,
<note place="margin">Mrs. <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pooles</hi> death.</note> for ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exorable he continued, that like the deaf adder he ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his ears to the charmer, charme he never ſo wiſely: at which unheard of cruelty, and for that Dr. <hi>Hewits</hi> Lady (as is ſaid) was then with child, Mrs. <hi>Claypoole</hi> took ſuch exceſſive grief, that ſhe ſuddenly fell ſick, the increaſe of her ſickneſs making her rave in a moſt lamentable manner, calling out againſt her Father for <hi>Hewits</hi> blood and the like, the violence of which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant paſſions working upon the great weakneſs of her body, carried her into another World, even at the heigheſt thereof.</p>
            <p>No ſooner did <hi>Cromwell</hi> receive the deplorable newes of this ſad death of his Daughter, but himſelf falls into a deſperate melancholly,
<note place="margin">Obſerve.</note> which never left him till his Death, which was not long after. Give me leave here to relate a paſſage which I received from a Perſon of Quality, <hi>Viz.</hi> It was believed, and that not without ſome good cauſe, that <hi>Cromwell</hi> the ſame morning that he defeated the Kings Army at <hi>Worcester</hi> Fight, had conference perſonally with the Divell, with whom he made a contract, that to have his will then, and in all things elſe for ſeven years after from that time (being the Third of <hi>September</hi> 1651.) he ſhould at the expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſaid years have him at his command, to do at his pleaſure, both with his ſoul and body. Now if any one will pleaſe to reckon from the third of <hi>September,</hi> 1651. till the Third of <hi>September,</hi> 1558.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cromwels</hi> death.</note> he ſhall find it to a Day juſt ſeven years and no more,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59927:21"/>at the end whereof he dyed but with ſuch extremity of tempeſtuous weather, that was, by all men judged to be prodigious, neither indeed was his end more miſerable, (for he dyed mad and deſpairing) than he hath left his name infamous; this was the end of our Engliſh <hi>Nero,</hi> and thus having laid the beſt foundations, his ſhort and troubleſome Reign would give leave to have continued his poſterity in the ſame unlimited Dominion, at his death, <hi>(ſi ullafides viris, qui castra ſequuntur)</hi> declaring his eldeſt Son <hi>Richard</hi> his ſucceſſour in his Uſurpation. Leaving his Son <hi>Henry</hi> Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and his Daughter <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> married to the Commander in chief of the Army un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himſelf, and the only Man ſuſpected for a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titour in the Protectorſhip, for <hi>Lambert</hi> had been laid aſide long before as a perſon of too dangerous and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring principles to be truſted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Cromwell</hi> preſently aſcends the Throne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Richard Cromwell</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector.</note> being but a private Gentleman of <hi>Hampſhire,</hi> invited there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto and incouraged by <hi>Flee wood, Deſhorow, Sydenham,</hi> the two <hi>Jones, Thurloe,</hi> and others, the relations and confidents of his Father: His firſt work is to take care for his Fathers Funerall, his corps being ſhortly after interred among the Kings and Queens at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> at a farr
<note n="*" place="margin">29000 <hi>l.</hi>
               </note> greater charge than had been uſed upon like occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the richeſt times, death giving him that honour which he aſpired to, but durſt not embrace in his life time, which ſolemity aſt, by the contrivance of the now Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, congratulations are ſent (prepared at <hi>Whitehall</hi>) from moſt of the Counties, Cities &amp; c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ief Townes of <hi>England.</hi> And from the Armies of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland,</hi> with engagements to live and dye with him. Addreſſes from the Independent Churches, by Mr. <hi>Goodwine</hi> and <hi>Nye,</hi> their Metropo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itans, and was indeed worſhipped by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59927:21"/>many as the riſing Sun in our Horizon.</p>
            <p>This Introduction being made for transferring the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of theſe Nations, from the Royal family of the <hi>Stewarts</hi> to that upſtart of the <hi>Cromwells:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ks</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment now mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delled.</note> it was thought fit, that a generall Convention, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a Parliament wiſely choſen by influences from <hi>Whitehall</hi> ſhould be called, to meet the twenty ſeventh of <hi>January,</hi> and (upon pretence of reſtoring the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to their antient way of Elections, but reall) that the Court might command the more votes, the <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> alſo had writs ſent to them, and the Elections were all made in the antient way, only thirty members were called by writs from <hi>Scotland,</hi> and as many from <hi>Ireland,</hi> according to the late combination of the three Nations into one Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>This new kind of Parliament being met at the time and place appointed, God who had ſo well ordered the Elections, notwithſtanding the practices of Men, that their Engliſh Spirit quickly appeared againſt Impoſitions, both from Court and Army,
<note place="margin">Act of Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> which being diſcerned by the Protector and his Grandees, a Recognition is ſent to them to be drawn into a bill, the debate whereof taking up a whole fourtnights time, and they ſtill remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a great ſtreight, till, by the expedient of an honeſt Gentleman, they were extricated thence by paſſing theſe votes on <hi>Munday</hi> the 14th. of <hi>February,</hi> 1658. without any diviſion or negative.</p>
            <p>Reſolved, <hi>that it be part of this Bill to Recognize and declare his Highneſſe</hi> Richard <hi>Lord Protector, and chiefe Magistrate of the Common-wealth of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:59927:22"/>Ireland, <hi>and the Dominions and Territories thereunto belonging,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reſolved, <hi>that before this Bill be committed, the Houſe do declare ſuch additionall clauſes to be part of this Bill, as may, bound the power of the chief Magistrate, and fully ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Rights and Priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Liberties and Rights of the People, and that neither this nor any other previous vote, that is, or ſhall be, paſſed in order to this Bill, ſhall be of force, or binding to the People, till the whole Bill be paſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This done,
<note place="margin">Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection.</note> a Committee of In ſpections is appointed to take a view of the accounts and revenue of the Common-wealth, &amp; twelve Members verſed in matters of account, were ſelected and fully impowered for that work, in order to the leſſening the charge of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Saturday</hi> the 19th. of <hi>February,</hi> they re-aſſumed the debate upon the Act of Recognition and reſolved. That it be part of the bill to declare the Parliament to conſiſt of two houſes:
<note place="margin">Parl. to conſiſt of two houſes.</note> after which they fell upon the point of bounding the chiefe Magiſtrates power and the bounds and powers of the other houſe, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors party ſtanding for the powers, given by the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and advice, and the reſt of the houſe withſtood it as of no value being obteined by force, by which force alſo thirteen hundred thouſand pounds a year was ſetled
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59927:22"/>for ever upon the ſingle perſon: and the ruling members of the other houſe, being a hotch potch or medley of Officers of the Army, and Protectorian Courtiers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the law of the land,
<note place="margin">The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther houſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated.</note> and to the enſlaving of the people. By this means nothing being done herein as to the powers, the <hi>Cromwelians,</hi> that they might enforce ſomething, propoſe the queſtion of tranſacting with the perſons ſitting in the other houſe as an houſe of Parliament, urging both law and neceſſity for the ſame, yea threatning force from the Army upon refuſall; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all which a whole fornight the honeſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Houſe thought of nothing leſs, aſſerting the undoubted Right of the antient Peers, and denying all the reſt, but ſeeing nothing could be done till this was over, in a very full houſe they came at laſt to this well qualified reſolve.</p>
            <p>Reſolved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That this Houſe will tranſact with the Perſons now ſitting in the other houſe, as an houſe of Parliament, during this preſent Parliament. And that it is not hereby intended to exclude ſuch Peers as have been faithfull to the Parliament, from their priviledge of being duly ſummoned to be Members of that houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein may be ſeen ſomething of the old Engliſh gallantry,
<note place="margin">Not own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Lords.</note> for in this vote thoſe in the other Houſe are not owned as Lords, (but called the Perſons now ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the other Houſe as an houſe of Parliament) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59927:23"/>would the Commons treat and confer with them in the uſuall way, as with the houſe of Peers, but found ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a new word (to tranſact) and that neither but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on tryall, <hi>Viz.</hi> during this preſent Parliament. And the better and more legally to curbe them if they ſhould begin to grow imperious, they inſerted the priviledge of the antient Peers as a good reſerve, concluding alſo to receive no meſſage from them, but by ſome of their own number.</p>
            <p>During this time,
<note place="margin">The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ment.</note> they had under conſideration ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall good Acts about the Militia, againſt Exciſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Cuſtomes, &amp;c. and queſtioned diverſe illegall impriſonments, calling ſome Jaylors to the Bar, and preparing a ſtrict bill to prevent the unlawfull ſending Freeborn Engliſhmen againſt their wills to be ſlaves in forreign Plantations; They alſo examined ſeverall grievances, by the Farmers of the Exciſe, Major Generalls, and tyrannicall, and exorbitant Courts of Juſtice. The Committee of Inſpections having by this time brought in their report by which it did appear, that the yearly incomes of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpections report.</note> came to Eighteen hundred ſixty eight thouſand ſeven hundred and ſeventeen pounds, and the yearly Iſſues to, Two Millions, two hundred and one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, five hundred and forty pounds. So that, Three hundred, thirty two thouſand eight hundred twenty three pounds of debt incurred yearly by the ill manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of double the revenew that ever any King of <hi>England</hi> enjoyed: And to maintain the unjuſt conqueſt of <hi>Scotland</hi> coſt us yearly, One hundred ſixty three thouſand ſix hundred and nineteen pounds more than the revenew of it yields.</p>
            <p>At theſe proceedings the Protector and the Army,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59927:23"/>who were already jealous of one another,
<note place="margin">Diviſions between the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector Pralia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Army.</note> grew both ſuſpicious of the Parliament, becauſe the people begin to ſpeake as if they expected great good from the iſſue of their Counſells, therefore the Army, (leaſt they ſhould come too late) put in for to get the power into their hands, and according to the method uſed by them in like caſes, erect a Generall Councill of Officers who daily meet at <hi>Wallinford-houſe,</hi> which the Protector hearing, endeavours to countermine at <hi>Whitehall;</hi> but they, better skilled in their work than he was, conclude a repreſentation, which is with ſpeed both drawn and preſented to him about the ſeventh of <hi>Aprill,</hi> a copy whereof the next day after is ſent encloſed by him in a Letter to the Speaker of the Houſe: who hereupon takes the Alarum, and while the Protector thinks to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure himſelf by ſtanding on his guard, they not fearing the menaces of the Souldiers, but reſolving to behave themſelves like true Engliſhmen, on <hi>Munday</hi> the 18th. of <hi>Aprill</hi> paſſed theſe votes following.</p>
            <p>Reſolved,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That during the ſitting of the Parliament, there ſhould be no generall Concill or meeting of the Officers of the Army without directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leave and Authority of his Higneſs the Lord Protector, and both houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reſolved,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That no perſon ſhall have and continue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny command, or truſt in any of the Armies,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59927:24"/>or Navies of</hi> England, Scotland, or Ireland, <hi>or any the Dominions and Territories there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to belonging, who ſhall refuſe to ſubſcribe. That he will not disturbe or interrupt the free meeting in Parliament, of any the members of either houſe of Parliament, or their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in their debates and Counſells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that this bitter pill might be the eaſier ſwallowed, knowing, or at leaſt believing that want of money was the thing that pinched in chief as to the private Souldier, (without whom the Officer was worthleſs) they paſſed a vote to take into conſideration how to ſatisfie the Arrears of the Army, and provide preſent pay for them, and alſo to prepare an Act of Indempnity for them. But all this tended nothing to ſatisfaction, for the Souldier being through Levened with the wicked deſignes of their Officers, did nothing but murmur, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſince the Protector in purſuance of the votes of the houſe had forbidden the meetings of the Officers; ſo that now the animoſities grew ſo high, that guards were kept night and day by one againſt the other, in which divided poſture the management of affairs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued till <hi>Friday</hi> the 22. of <hi>April,</hi> on which day early in the Morning, <hi>Fleetwood, Desborough,</hi> and the reſt of the Mutinous Officers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dicks</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</note> with the greateſt part of the Army at their beck, the <hi>Cromwelian</hi> party not daring to ſtir, got the ſupereminency, and forced young <hi>Richard</hi> to conſent to a commiſſion and Proclamation ready pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared, thereby giving power to certain therein na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to diſſolve the Parliament, although he had with
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59927:24"/>much ſerious earneſtneſs proteſted and promiſed, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to dye than be guilty of ſo puſillaminous an act, which he was well aſſured would work for his confuſion. But <hi>actum est,</hi> for the ſame day the black rod was ſent twice to the houſe of Commons to go to the other houſe, which they refuſed and ſcorned, but underſtanding there were guards of horſe and foot in the Pallace yard, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome ebullient motions, without reſolving any queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they adjourned till <hi>Munday</hi> morning, the five and twenty of <hi>April,</hi> and with much courage and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion attended the Speaker in order through <hi>Westminſter-Hall</hi> to his Coach, even in the face of the Souldiery.</p>
            <p>The Army having thus for the preſent miſſed their deſign, reſolve no longer to dally; whereupon they, lay aſide their new Mr. <hi>Richard,</hi> and all the Officers, great and ſmall with one conſent, take the Government into their own hands, having ſhut up the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons door, whither when the Members came on <hi>Munday,</hi> entrance was denyed them by the Souldiers, who had poſſeſſed themſelves of the Court of requeſts and all avenues in all places, giving no other account to the Members than this, <hi>Viz.</hi> They muſt ſit no more.
<note place="margin">The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my rew model<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The next meeting of Officers new modelleth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſome they caſheire as <hi>Whaly, Ingoldsby, Goſſe,</hi> &amp;c. others they re-admit, as <hi>Lambert, Haſelrig, Okey,</hi> and others, in which time not knowing how to behave themſelves in ſuch a condition, and weary of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall toyle they foreſaw, they muſt ſtill with ceaſing undergo; they mean to caſt the burthen off from their own ſhoulders, and to that purpoſe they ſend to ſome of their old hackney drudges of the long Parliament,
<note place="margin">The Rump comes in.</note> (as they then did call it) at that time about <hi>London,</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:59927:25"/>whoſe conſciences they knew would digeſt any thing, and did not care how, <hi>per fas aut nefas,</hi> ſo they might again be ſuffered to ſit, with ſeverall of theſe, I ſay, upon the fifth and ſixth dayes of <hi>May</hi> they had confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, the laſt of which was at their never failing Speakers, the Maſter of the Rowles houſe in <hi>Chancery-Lane,</hi> where both Officers of the Army, and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Members, to the number of twenty ſollicited <hi>William Lenthall</hi> Eſquire to ſit Speaker again, but he objected diverſe ſcruples in judgment and conſcience: (But O how ſoon had the ſweet ambition of domineering ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literated all ſuch idle fancies?) yet nevertheleſs inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fifteen Articles being agreed upon among themſelves, they conclude to meet in the houſe on <hi>Saturday</hi> the 7th. day of <hi>May,</hi> and the better to compaſs their ends by a baſe and clandeſtine ſurpriſe, they gave out that they would not ſit till <hi>Tueſday</hi> the tenth of <hi>May,</hi> yet ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptitiouſly, as I ſay, they met early on <hi>Saturday</hi> in the painted Chamber at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and wanting of their number to make up a houſe, they ſent for thoſe two debauched luſtfull Devills, the Lord <hi>Munſon,</hi> and <hi>Harry Martin</hi> out of priſon, where they were in Execution for debt, with <hi>Whitelock,</hi> and <hi>Liſle</hi> of the Chancery Court, making in all forty two, the Chancery Mace alſo for haſt being carried before them, <hi>William Lenthall</hi> Eſq. their tender conſcienc'd Speaker, together with the ſaid
<list>
                  <item>L.
<note place="margin">Names of the Rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</note> 
                     <hi>Munſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry Martin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Whitlock.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Liſle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Thomas Chaloner.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Alderman <hi>Atkins</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Alderman <hi>Penington.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Scot.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cornelius Holland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Henry Vane.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> Att. Ge</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>James Harrington.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:59927:25"/>
                  <item>L. G. <hi>Ludlow.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Michael Oldſworth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Jones.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Purefoy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>White.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Harry Nevill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Say.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Blagrave.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Bennet</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M. <hi>Brewſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sergeant <hi>Wilde.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Goodwin.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Nich. Lechmore.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Auguſtine Skinner.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Downes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Dove.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>John Lenthall.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Saloway.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>John Corbet.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Walton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gilbert Willington.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Gold.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Sydenham.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Bingham.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Ayre.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Smith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Ingoldsby.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And Lieutenant Generall</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fleetwood.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Stole on a ſudden into the houſe, the invitation of the Army for ſitting of the long Parliament being firſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in <hi>weſtminster-Hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon notice of this ſurpriſe of the houſe by ſo few, there being more than double the like number of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame Parliament there, and about town, ſome of them at the ſame inſtant in the Hall, they to prevent future miſchief, (whereof this packing of Parliament men was an ill Omen) to the number of fourteen, went immediately into the Lobby, and the perſons that did ſo were theſe, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Anſlewy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sr. <hi>George Booth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>James Harbet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Prinne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>George Montague.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>John Evelin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>John Harbert.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Gowen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Evelin.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Secluded. mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</note>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Knightly.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Clive.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hungerford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Harbey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Pecke.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:59927:26"/>
            <p>But aſſoon as they came near the door, they were not ſuffered by the Officers of the Army to go into the houſe, though they diſputed their priviledge of ſitting, (if the Parliament were not diſſolved) but reaſon not prevailing, after they had thus fairly made their claim they retired, reſolving to acquaint the Speaker by letter of their uſage. And accordingly on <hi>Munday</hi> the 9th. of <hi>May</hi> they went to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where the guards being not yet come, Mr. <hi>Anſley,</hi> Mr. <hi>Prinne,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerford,</hi> went freely into the houſe, receiving the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the 7th. of <hi>May</hi> at the door, But <hi>Mr. Anſley</hi> walking down into the Hall, (the houſe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to ſit) at his return was by one Capt. <hi>Lewſon</hi> of <hi>Goffes</hi> Regiment and other officers denyed entrance, Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> continued within and reſolved ſo to do,
<note place="margin">Vote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſecluded mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</note> ſince he ſaw there a new force upon the houſe, whoſe only ſtaying (ſo guilty were the reſt of their evill actions) made them looſe that morning, and adjourn without the Speakers taking the chair. And to prevent his or any other honeſt mans coming in among them, after that they barred the door by the following Vote.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Ordered.</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That ſuch perſons heretofore, Members of this Parliament, as have not ſate in this Parliament, ſince the year</hi> 1648. <hi>And have not ſubſcribed the engagement in the Roll of engagement of this Houſe, ſhall not ſit in this houſe till further order of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:59927:26"/>
            <p>Thus (to the griefe of all honeſt and true hearted Chriſtians) the ſame pretended Parliament that was fitting in 1653. (till <hi>Oliver</hi> diſſeized them) ſitting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in 1659. upon a Declaration of the Army, with the ſame reſolutions they had before, minding nothing but prefering one another,
<note place="margin">The good old cauſe what.</note> and their friends into good Offices and commands, and Counſellors places, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by their Vote of the 29th. of <hi>May, Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Parliament doth declare, that all ſuch as ſhall be employed in any place of trust or power in the Common-wealth, be able for the diſcharge of ſuch truſt, and that they be perſons fearing God, and that have given teſtimony to all the people of God, and of their faithfulneſs to this Common-wealth, according to the Declaration of Parliament of the</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
               <hi>of</hi> May.</p>
            <p>Now who they mean by perſons fearing God in their canting language, by their very next work you ſhall ſee, which is the nominating a Councill of State,
<note place="margin">Councill of State nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> into whoſe hands is given the diſpoſe of all places of truſt and profit, yea and the command of the wealth of the Kingdom; thoſe of the houſe are as follow.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Henry Vane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ludlow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jo. Jones.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sydenham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scot.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Saloway.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fleetwood.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:59927:27"/>
               <item>Sir <hi>James Harrington.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Walton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nevill.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chaloner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Downes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whitlock.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Harb. Morley.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sydney.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Thomſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Dixwell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Reignolds.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oliver</hi> St. <hi>Johns.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Wallop.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Of Perſons without the houſe Ten. <hi>Viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John. Bradſhaw.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Lambert.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Desborow.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fairfax.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Berry.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Anthony Aſhley-Cooper.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Horatio Townſend.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Robert H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ywood.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Archibald Johnſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And <hi>Joſia Berners.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Who under the mask of the good old cauſe began now to act as high villains as ever before; having forgotten how juſtly they formerly had been laid aſide, but they are like the dog that returnes to his vomit, and with the ſow that is waſhed, to her wallowing in the mire.</p>
            <p>And the better to caſt a ſeeming gloſs over the foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their actions,
<note place="margin">The good old cauſe what it is.</note> and their clandeſtine intruſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Government, they ſend forth a Declaration in print, the particulars whereof might very well have been here obſervable, if they had not already been ſo cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrated, by the laborious pen of learned Mr. <hi>William Prinne,</hi> in his book entituled, The Republicans good old cauſe ſtated; having therein ſo fully detected them,
<note place="margin">Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Crown <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ands to be fold.</note> that there remains nothing more to be ſaid in the ſame matter.</p>
            <p>And now, as if already they had not waſted enough, by expoſing to ſale the Kings, Queens, Princes, Nobles
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59927:27"/>and Gentries, Lands and Goods, being very quick ſighted, and of a long and large memory, whereby they knew all was not ſold: therefore about the beginning of <hi>June,</hi> to ſhew us further what they meant by the good old cauſe, they ordered the bill for publick ſales to be brought in; A ſweet act, to enrich the ſaints, as they in their canting language called themſelves; but their neceſſities (by the long deteining of the publick purſe from them) being grown very preſſing, and though they thought the money ariſing from thoſe ſales would be ſure, yet for their preſent urgencies (not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to ſtay till that could be raiſed) they appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame afternoon to conſider of a more ſpeedy way for raiſing money, for that was all they ever aimed at, or hoped for, and to this purpoſe a bill of Aſſeſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is concluded the moſt fitting:
<note place="margin">Quaerenda pecunia primum eſt.</note> And becauſe they would leave no ſtone unturned, from which they might hope gain, ſee how ingeniouſly they can project, making an order to the Committee of inſpection (a precious crew) to take ſpeciall care that ſuch perſons who have aſſumed the titles of Honour, Dignities and precedencies heretofore conferred on them by the late King, ſince the ſame were taken away by act of this preſent Parliament,
<note place="margin">Honours given by the late King or his Son to be null.</note> do pay the ſeverall ſummes of money by them forfeited, and that the ſaid Committee do alſo examine whether they have brought in their Patents, and to report how the ſaid monies may be employed to the beſt advantage of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and to offer an act to take away all honours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred by the late Kings Son. Was there ever ſuch a piece of unſeemly inconſiſtency, that the Fountain of honour ſhould be debarred of its ſpring by a company of peaſants, whoſe Acts were no better than of an aſſembly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59927:28"/>of rogues at beggars buſh; but would you know why they were ſo much troubled; 'twas precedency that ſtuck in their ſtomachs, thoſe noble ſouls went before them both in honour and honeſty therefore ſeeing they could not hinder them from being called Lords by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yea the generality, they lay it as a crime of pride upon them, that they did aſſume ſuch titles, for which imaginary fault they muſt pay the ſummes forfeited for ſuch inſolence againſt their Rumpſhips. O this <hi>Auri ſacra fames, quid non mortalia pectora cogit,</hi> what will it not make them do? They firſt muſt pay, then bring in their Patents, otherwiſe pay again: thus the Divel rangeth, fierceſt, when his time is moſt ſhort; for ſo generally was theirs hoped to be, in regard they and their Maſters of the Army could not cotton together,
<note place="margin">The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my fright the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees.</note> being already alarumed from them by a petition and addreſs, yet they grew a little more confident upon the newes of <hi>Harry Cromwells</hi> ſubmiſſion, and falling down to worſhip the image which they had ſet up, <hi>Moncke</hi> alſo having about the ſame time, ſent them the reſolutions of himſelf and his Army to adhere to them, as a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony whereof he informed them of a deſign of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent from the King of Scots (as they called him) which his diligence and care in the Highlands had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</p>
            <p>Theſe newes ſo animated our Juncto, that thinking all cockſure,
<note place="margin">Money matters only ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of.</note> they fall to their old Trade of raiſing money. Firſt by aſſeſſements, then by continuing the Exciſe and Cuſtomes untill the firſt of <hi>October,</hi> and laſtly by ordering the Truſtees for ſale of Crown Lands, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to proceed to the ſale of all computed within the Act for ſale thereof, and that they take care of the profits ariſing from the ſame, for the uſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth till ſale thereof be made.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:59927:28"/>
            <p>Money being thus taken care for to be raiſed by all means, ſuddenly after by a Vote they revive the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for plundered Miniſters (or rather for plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Miniſters) that ſo they may alſo provide them of hacknies who ſhall infuſe into the people ſtrange En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſtick wayes of Government.
<note place="margin">Plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Tythes.</note> It was not enough with <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to cauſe a generall rebellion, but with him alſo to uphold it, they make of the loweſt and baſeſt of the people, Prieſts of their high places, for whom the old way of tythes is not thought good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, it was conſulted how a more equall and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table maintenance might be ſetled on the miniſtry for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the people, whom thus intending to lull aſleep: they reſolve to advance their own ſafety by colloguing with the land forces with promiſes of ſudden pay,
<note place="margin">Seamen to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</note> and ſtrengthening the Navy by impreſſing Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which about this time, in <hi>June</hi> they were about, And leſt they ſhould be wanting to themſelves in any thing, mercenary drudges of the Juncto begin to take upon them as may appear by this order.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <head>22. <hi>June.</hi> 1659 By the Contractors for ſale of Crown Lands.
<note place="margin">Crown lands ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</note>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Theſe are to give you notice, that</hi> Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet-houſe <hi>with the Appertenances, and</hi> Hampton-Court <hi>with the parkes, &amp;c. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto belonging, are ſpeedily to be expoſed to ſale, and that the Contractors intend to ſit on</hi> Wedneſday <hi>next the</hi> 29. <hi>inſtant, to take in deſires of ſuch as intend the purchaſe of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59927:29"/>any part of</hi> Somerſet-Houſe, <hi>and on</hi> VVedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day <hi>the</hi> 6th. <hi>of</hi> July, <hi>the deſires of any that intend the purchaſe of any part of</hi> Hampton-Court, <hi>the premiſes are to be ſold for ready money.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Will. Tayler <hi>Clark attending the ſaid Contractors.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Indeed the laſt clauſe for ready money was very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſary, as affairs then ſtood, for the Grandees at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> having only waſted and imbezelled the reſt by diviſions and ſharings among themſelves and friends, with no advantage to the publick Exchequer, they would now ſeem to begin to amend, but it is according to the Proverbe like ſowre ale in Summer, for they intended nothing leſs than increaſing the publick ſtock, but rather by augmenting and converting it to their own uſe, make a hoped proviſion againſt an enſuing ſtorm, which they foreſaw would ere long fall upon them without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny means of prevention: yet reſolving to ſhare the ſpoil as long as they could, at <hi>Midſummer,</hi> they re-made their everlaſting Speaker,
<note place="margin">Offices beſtowed and on whom.</note> 
               <hi>Cuſtos rotulorum,</hi> of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Berkſhires.</hi> And that worſhipfull Judas, Sir <hi>H. Mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may, Cuſtos rotulorum</hi> for <hi>Eſſex,</hi> with ſeverall other the like places to diverſe of their leading members, as the Government of <hi>Jerſey</hi> to Col. <hi>Maſon,</hi> and ſeverall Regiments in <hi>Ireland</hi> to Col. <hi>Cooper,</hi> Col. <hi>Zankey,</hi> Col. <hi>Sadler,</hi>
               <note place="margin">H. <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> leaves <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </note> and Col. <hi>Laurence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having proceeded on thus far ſuccesfully, they now begin to clap their wings as invincible, <hi>Ireland</hi> being
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59927:29"/>delivered up wholly and quietly into their power by that pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ull cowardly Impe <hi>H. Cromwell</hi> who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready attended their pleaſure at the Commons bar, for which good ſervice they ſtroaked him on the head, told him he was a good boy, for which kindneſs he buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his hand, made a leg and <hi>Exit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leave we him to ſtupid folly, and let us ſee what rates Crown land bears, the Contractors late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were very buſie, and behold the product.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="notice">
                        <head>
                           <hi>June.</hi> 29. 1669.</head>
                        <p>By the Truſtees and Contractors appointed by Act of Parliament, for ſale of the Caſtles, parkes, &amp;c. exempted from ſale by a former Act.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Theſe are to give notice, that there are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors for the purchaſe of</hi> Somerſet-Houſe,
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Sommer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet-houſe</hi> ſet to ſale etc.</note> 
                           <hi>with the Appurtenances in the</hi> Strand, Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex, <hi>which therefore is to be expoſed to ſale for ready money, by the box to be opened on</hi> Friday, <hi>the eight of</hi> July <hi>next. The annuall value being</hi> 233. l. <hi>the groſs value of mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialls, &amp;c.</hi> 5545. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>ſ.</hi> 3. <hi>d. At which time ſuch as deſire to purchaſe the ſame may put in their papers with their name ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed into the box aforeſaid at</hi> VVorſeſter-Houſe,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59927:30"/>
                           <hi>conteining how many years purchaſe,</hi> (<hi>not under</hi> 13.) <hi>they will give for the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall value, &amp;c. and he that offers most is to have the purchaſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>VVill. Tayler <hi>Clarke, &amp;c.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>At the ſame time they appointed to ſell ten brace of Buckes, or more out of <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> Parkes, and ſo from time to time.</p>
            <p>Thus did they ſtrive to make havock of whatever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the King, which indeed, and no other, was the good (or rather curſed) old cauſe that theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants ſo luſtily fought for, and ſo loudly cryed up.</p>
            <p>And now, leſt they ſhould ſeem ingratefull to <hi>Richard Cromwell,</hi> who had ſo tamely left the chair of State to theſe Mountebanks to ſit in: they vote him an exemption from all arreſts, for any debt whaſoever, for ſix moneths, and appoint a Committee to examine what was due, for mourning for the late Lord Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected.</note> and to conſider how it may be paid for, without charge to the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Kind Gentlemen ſurely they are, they take all he hath from him, and then allow him a penſion; they rob him of a pound and give him a farthing, not a feather of his own bird, and well ſo too: for his ambitious ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping into the royall feat, deſerved a greater puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which 'twas a wonder how he eſcaped, ſince U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation and Tyranny in different hands are generally vehement ſcourges to each other, and alwayes tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to themſelves; as will appear by the ſequel.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59927:30"/>
            <p>For theſe godly great ones, being now newly warm in their ſeats,
<note place="margin">New plots and jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies.</note> begin (as of old) to dream of Jealouſies and fears: Plots, Plots, nothing but Cavaleer plots rings either in their ears or mouths: if two Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men do but meet accidentally in the Street, and talk together, ſtraight there is a confederacy, and they muſt be committed to priſon for doing nothing, ſo that we might ſay with that Noble Romane <hi>Cicero, Circumſpice omnia membra Reipublicae, quae nobiliſſima ſunt: nullum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritur profecto quod non fractum, debilitatumve ſit. O rem miſeram! dominum ferre non potuimus, conſervis vero jam ſervimus.</hi> A ſad cauſe of complaint, to live in ſuch a ſlavery; but our Taskmaſters would fain ſeem mercifull, witneſs their Act of Indemnity,
<note place="margin">Act of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity pardons all but Cavaliers.</note> which came out in print about <hi>July,</hi> wherein they except none from pardon but only ſuch whoſe conſciences are not large enough to approve of open Rebellion, as the laſt clauſe of their ſaid mock-Act will ſhew, wherein all are debarred the benefit of the ſame, even from ſixteen years of age, unleſs they ſubſcribe againſt a ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Kingſhip or houſe of Peers; all ſins can be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted by theſe fellowes, except lawfull obedience to magiſtracy, which they ſo abominate that all perſons that are tainted therewith muſt not only depart out of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> but out of <hi>England,</hi> in either whereof if they be taken, they ſhall be proceeded againſt as Traytors: and all perſons are impouered to take and apprehend them, for encouragement of which roguery every one that diſcovers, or takes ſuch a perſon was to have ten pounds from the Councill of State; Surely they are in a great fear, elſe what ſhould they make all this noiſe, and buſtle ſo furiouſly on a ſudden, to ſettle and raiſe a new militia, but <hi>latet anguis in herba,</hi> for now (it being
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59927:31"/>the Dog-dayes) the houſe grew ſo hot, that diverſe members withdrew, whereby the reſt in regard of their fewneſs, being become incapable to act, becauſe not enough to make up a houſe, according to their own phantaſticall modell on <hi>Friday</hi> 22. of <hi>July</hi> did Reſolve.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Members of Parliament,
<note place="margin">Members to attend.</note> who have had Letters to attend the ſervice of the Parliament, or have actually attended ſince the 7th. of</hi> May, 1659. <hi>be hereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to give their attendance in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment every Morning at eight of the clock, for fourteen dayes, and if employed by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, within a fourtnight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas, poor men, the harveſt truly was great, but the labourers few; therefore it was time to call for more help, for which now they are ſo put to it, that they hardly know which way to turn themſelves: they complain of deſignes, &amp; of buying up of Armes to diſturbe the peace, which made a great one among them ſay, this reſtleſs Spirit of the common Enemy ſhould excite the friends of the Common-wealth to diligence and to ſtudy unity, that advantage may not be given by diviſions, but that we may be all of one Spirit to uphold and promote the common cauſe that hath been contended for. And the better to colour their villanies (according to their uſuall cuſtome in like caſes when they had miſchief to do) they ſet apart a day of faſting and humiliation;
<note place="margin">A faſting day ſet a part for miſchief.</note> and to ſhew that they were the ſame men and of the ſame (if not worſe) mind than formerly for rapine and blood, they
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59927:31"/>proclaim <hi>J. Mordant</hi> Eſquire, with ſeverall others tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; and order the Lady <hi>Howard,</hi> Sr. E. <hi>Byron,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sumner,</hi> to be brought to a ſpeedy triall, for dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and trayterous deſignes, of bringing this Nation into blood and confuſion again: that is for endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to reſtore his Sacred Majeſty to his lawfull birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and dominions, for which the whole current of the law is conſtant encourager, although theſe mens effrontery is ſuch, that they dare ſay any thing by an infallible Spirit as they imagine, and the World is bound to believe them. But their vizor being now ready to fall off,
<note place="margin">Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> and the people not willing to be any longer blinded, begin to move in moſt parts of <hi>England,</hi> which ſo mads the Phanatick faction, that they ſeaze upon perſons, horſes, and armes all about <hi>London,</hi> increaſe and double their guards, ſtop paſſengers, even on the Road, the Councill of State (ſo called) ſits night and day without intermiſſion, whereby the City militia and all the forces throughout <hi>England</hi> were drawn into a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dy to prevent the danger. Yea ſo generall was the fear that they begin to court the people in their canting way.</p>
            <p>And becauſe you ſhall ſee their deſperate fear of, and divelliſh malice to, the King and his Friends, take the words of one of themſelves as they paſs,
<note place="margin">A canting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lye.</note> 
               <hi>Viz. The Lord ſtir up the hearts of his people to prayer and ſincere humiliation, and fill them with unanimity and courage in this evill time, and make the People to ſee, that whatever fair pretences may be made uſe of by the common Enemy, to get power into their hands, yet ſhould they prevail, no man that hath been of a party againſt them heretofore, yea no man that hath been a meer Neuter, but muſt expect that his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Eſtate, as well as the publick Liberty, ſhall become a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59927:32"/>prey to a deſperate crew of ravenous and unreaſonable men: for (ſaith he) like an irreverent Villain) let but</hi> CHALES STUART <hi>get in, and then to ſatisfie the rable of follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the payment of forreyners to enſlave you, you ſhall ſoon ſee them entailed upon your ſelves and your Posterity, to maintain the pompe and pride of a luxurious Court, and an abſolute Tyranny.</hi> Thus far he, which how much truth, yea or but probability thereof is therein; I dare ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the greateſt Enthuſiaſt among their whole gange: for if there were nothing in it elſe but the rayling (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all the falſity and Scandall) it were ſufficient to convince the Speaker to be a Son of <hi>Beliall,</hi> as having ſo far forgotten grace, and laid a ſide all honeſty, that he durſt rail againſt the Lords anointed, concerning whom the Scripture forbiddeth to have an evill thought, but tis the cuſtom of rebells to go on from bad to worſe, and when they have once drawn the ſword againſt their Prince, to throw away the ſcabbard, and never enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a thought of return or repentance, like the bold Uſurper in the Poet.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The more we are oppoſed the more wee'le ſpread,</l>
               <l>And make our foes our fuell: To be head</l>
               <l>Wee'l, cut off any member, and condemn</l>
               <l>Vertue of folly for a Diadem.</l>
               <l>Baniſh Religion, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And ſuch was their practice,
<note place="margin">The uſe of the Juncto's faſting.</note> though ſometimes (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when encompaſſed with dangers) they hang their head like a bull ruſh, and even but mock God with a faſt, while they only pray to be proſperous in their villany</p>
            <p>About this time, the whole Nation of <hi>England</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59927:32"/>to grow ſick of the abhorred fag end of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, endeavouring to make head againſt them in <hi>Kent, Suſſex, Surrey, Hartford, Hereford, Gloceſter, Briſtoll,</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> eſpecially,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>England</hi> ſick of the Rump.</note> where many of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try were actually engaged, correſpondence maintained, a rendevous appointed, and the antient City of <hi>Cheſier</hi> ſurpriſed: this indeed was the moſt formidable appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in all <hi>England,</hi> for the only appeaſing whereof moſt of the County forces in thoſe parts, and ſeveral Regiments of the Army from <hi>London,</hi> did ſpeedily march under the command of a hot-ſpur zealot, Mr. G. <hi>Lambert,</hi> whoſe ambition made old Nol lay him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide as dangerous, and that diſhonourable diſcarding, created him a deſperate Enemy to the <hi>Cromwelian</hi> name and family, which made the Juncto think him the fitter man for their ſervice,
<note place="margin">A riſing in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> by Sir <hi>G. B.</hi>
               </note> Sir <hi>G. B.</hi> appeared commander in chief in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> though many other Noble Gentlemen, were preſent, ſo that this ſeemed to be the moſt likely place for Action. <hi>Lambert</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Order being upon his march thither, with three Regiments of horſe, and three Regiments of Foot, and one Regiment of Dragoones, beſides a train of Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery: and the Juncto for his encouragement ſhot a paper gun (by them called a Proclamation) after him againſt Sir <hi>George Booth,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Middleton, Randolph Eger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> proclaiming them and their adherents to be Rebells and Traytors, and all elſe that ſhould any way aſſiſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet or conceal the carrying on of their deſign; backed thus he marcheth furiouſly, and in a fourtnight or three weekes time draweth neer to <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> in the mean and during his abſence, the congregated Churches of Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks and Sectaries in and about <hi>London,</hi> raiſe three Regiments for the ſecurity of thoſe parts, in the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valls
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59927:33"/>of which time, Sir <hi>George Booths</hi> Declaration came out in print, the contents whereof was ſetting forth how the <hi>Weſtminster</hi> Stateſmen had violated all lawes of God and Men; that the defence of the lawes and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties was the chief things he and his aimed at, which would never by theſe ſelf ſeekers be ſetled, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſired a new free Parliament. This, as it carried nothing in it but what was reall true, ſo it gave very great ſatisfaction to all underſtanding people, though by the Phanatick rout it was deſcanted upon otherwiſe: but Gods time was not yet come, for <hi>Lambert</hi> no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er arrived with his Army neer Sir <hi>George Booth,</hi> and his forces,
<note place="margin">Sir <hi>G. B.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed.</note> but he fell on them with valour and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, which produced a very ſharp engagement, but the Country not being acquainted, nor uſed to ſuch hot &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious work quickly yielded ground: Sr. <hi>Georges</hi> whole body being afterwards drawn forth neer <hi>Northwich,</hi> and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the bridge, they drew up their foot in the meadowes, yet <hi>Lamberts</hi> Men being commanded to attempt the paſs, did it with ſuch reſolution that they ſoon beat the Enemy from them, and made way for the whole Army, who having paſſed the river imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately gave them a totall rout.</p>
            <p>The newes of this victory ſo fleſhed our bloodhounds, that they began to boaſt above meaſure, vaunting the Lords mercy to them (his own people forſooth) but Juſtice to their adverſaries in ſo apparently blaſting their Trayterous undertakings in every corner of the land; like the turkes, reckoning the goodneſs of their cauſe by the keenneſs of their ſword,
<note place="margin">Their maxime to make good their cauſe.</note> and denying that any thing may properly be called <hi>Nefas,</hi> if it can but win the Epithete of <hi>Proſperum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Juncto upon this, ſet forth a Declaration to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59927:33"/>all the people to thankſgiving, for this great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance to the Parliament, and Common-wealth,
<note place="margin">Lamberts policy.</note> (as they ſtiled themſelves): but <hi>Lambert</hi> intends to make uſe of his ſucceſs againſt the loyall party for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to that end in a ſeeming, ſlighting and neglect of himſelf, writes to the Parliament his Souldiers merits, with whom (the ſooner to endear them) he is more than uſually familiar: and the Parliament have no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er voted him 1000 l. to buy him a Jewell, as a mark of their favour, but he preſently diſtributes it among his Souldiers, endeavouring by that and all other means to engage them wholly to himſelf, ſo as to venture in one bottom with him; he yet carried himſelf ſo, that his ambitious deſign was not diſcovered, and that he might the better conceal: at this time Sir <hi>George Booth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> G. B. <hi>taken.</hi>
               </note> who had fled from the battle, at <hi>Northwich</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> was taken at <hi>Newport-Pannel</hi> in diſguiſe; upon notice whereof, he is committed cloſe priſoner to the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London.</hi> for high Treaſon, in levying warr againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Common-wealth, and that a Committee be appointed on purpoſe to examine him, all which was done accordingly, and Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig,</hi> (two Saints of the Divells laſt edition) went to him to take his examination.</p>
            <p>While things are thus in handling here, <hi>Lambert</hi> ſeeks cunningly to get all the ſtrength of thoſe Counties into his own hands, which the Parliament at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt grant him, by giving him power to ſeize all armes for their uſe (as he pretended) in the ſame: of which piece of ſervice they ſeemed to be very glad as alſo of letters that came out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> aſſuring Generall <hi>Monkes</hi> fidelity to them againſt the intereſt of the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> or any other whatſoever, ſo that now they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59927:34"/>to deſcant on the late deſign,
<note place="margin">A triall of the royall family.</note> laying all the blame on the loyall party, whoſe game they ſaid it was, though he leaſt appeared in it, taking occaſion alſo from thence to blaſt the royall family with helliſh ſcandalls: the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of which the divine providence hath alwayes had a particular and peculiar care of, but as it were in deſpight of Heaven, they are not content with all their former wickedneſſes of baniſhing, exiling, and railing againſt their lawfull Soveraign, but now they will enforce all to renounce him, which in <hi>September</hi> they Reſolved in theſe words.</p>
            <p>J. A. B. <hi>Do hereby declare,
<note place="margin">Oath of abjurati. on.</note> that I renounce the pretended title of</hi> CHARLS STUART, <hi>and the whole line of the late King</hi> James, <hi>and of every other perſon, as a ſingle perſon, pretending to the Government of theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and the Dominions and Territories thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing. And that I will by the grace and aſſiſtance of Almighty God be true, faithfull, and conſtant to this Common-wealth againſt any King, ſingle perſon, and houſe of Peers, and every of them, and hereunto I ſubſcribe my name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus may every one ſee, that it was not to amend or reform any errours in the State, but only their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular malice to the Royall line and covetouſneſs after
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59927:34"/>their Eſtate, that made them run into ſuch deſperate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, wherein having ſo deeply engaged themſelves, that there was no going back, they mean to make all ſure to their intereſt: and to that end take into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate in the beginning of <hi>September,</hi> the matter of the Government, and referred it to a Committee upon the votes in 1648.
<note place="margin">The blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Juncto.</note> To prepare ſomething in order to the ſettlement of the Government, on or before the tenth of <hi>October.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See here the indiſcretion of theſe men, after a ten years unſettlement and bringing all into confuſion, in all which time they have minded nothing but their own private wealth, and till this laſt minute of time have not ſo much as thought of reſettling; and that they now have, is ſo weakly, that it tends no further than to an offer: thus running willingly into one crime, they daily perpetrate new ones without any ſenſe of evill, or will of amending, attributing the guilt of their faults to all that endeavour either to reform or puniſh them.</p>
            <p>The buſineſs of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> thus blown over, and the great hopes that were grounded thereon blaſted; the Juncto fall to their old humour of raiſing money, no leſs will ſerve their turn than 100000. l. a moneth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Exciſe and Cuſtomes,
<note place="margin">Taxes and exciſe confirmed, new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents made and mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itia arreas collected.</note> together with the hoped benefit that would ariſe from the ſequeſtred Eſtates of new Delinquents; and leaſt any thing ſhould eſcape them, the 16th. of <hi>September</hi> they vote.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That ſuch perſons as have been aſſeſſed to find horſes and Armes, by vertue of the Act of Parliament, for ſetling the Militia, and have not brought in their horſes and Armes,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59927:35"/>nor paid in lieu thereof the ſumm of money, appointed by the ſaid Act. That every ſuch perſon and perſons do under the penalty in the ſaid Act mentioned pay, after the rate of ten pounds for an horſe and Armes for ſuch number of horſes and Armes reſpectively as they have been charged to find.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reſolved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That ſuch perſon and perſons as have been aſſeſſed to find Armes for a foot Souldier, and have not ſent in the ſame, or money in lieu thereof, do under the penalties in the ſaid Act mentioned pay, reſpectively for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſuch foot Armes, ſuch ſumm of money as the Commiſſioners ſhall appoint, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding twenty five Shillings for every ſuch foot Armes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis no matter, you ſee, by this, whether any Horſe or Armes be brought in at all, ſo that the money be paid, Oh! 'Tis the money that adds Life and Legs to a decrepit and dying old cauſe: The Grandees would never take ſo much pains, unleſs an extraordinary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit alſo waited thereon; which they reſolve to compaſs, though with the extreameſt hazards, whereof there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be ſome kind of an appearance, by the growing of heart-burnings, and multiplying fears and jealouſies
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59927:35"/>between their late great Champion <hi>Lambert</hi> and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Juncto grow ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious o</hi> Lambert</note> the ſparks of which animoſities growing into a flame, quickly increaſed to that height, that not daring to truſt him any longer with the Army, they ſend a ſeeming courteous Letter to invite him home; which he, taking no notice of any thing further than the pretended outſide fair ſhew, acceps of; and on the 20th. of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> returnes accordingly to <hi>London,</hi> but immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his arrivall there, the Juncto,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>He comes to</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note> to ſhew the great charity, wherewith they abounded, took into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion how to cozen the poor Knights of <hi>Windſor,</hi> and to ingroſs into their hands all Hoſpitals and their reveneues, by theſe two following votes. <hi>Viz. Tueſday September</hi> 20th. 1659.</p>
            <p>Reſolved,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it be referred to a Committee,
<note place="margin">The Juncto in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſeize on all Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls and convert their rents.</note> to look into the revenue for maintenance of the poor Knights of</hi> Windſor, <hi>to examine what the ſame at preſent is, and will be for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, after Leaſes expired, and to ſee that the charitable uſes, to which the ſaid reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue was granted, be performed, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue to be anſwered, to the uſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, (by all means pray take a care of that) and to examine the Leaſes that have been made, and the fines that have been paid thereupon, and how diſpoſed, and by what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; with power to give reliefe and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59927:36"/>to the ſaid poor Knights, and other poor people not exceeding their former allowance (Oh, take heed of too much charity!) and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to take a Catalogue of all Hoſpitalls with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Common-wealth, and the revenewes of them (they are ſure to mind that.) And that the Maſters and Governours do return to this Committee, the conſtitution of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective hoſpitalls, and how the profits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of have been, and are diſpoſed of, and by what authority, before the firſt of</hi> December, 1659. <hi>And to report the whole matter to the houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Ordered,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That all Maſters and Governours of hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalls, be, and are hereby prohibited to grant or renew any Leaſes of any Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and hereditaments belonging unto any of the ſaid reſpective hoſpitalls, untill this houſe take further Order. Notice of which is to be given to the reſpective concerned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, by the Councill of State.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>See here how greedy is the zeal of theſe devouring Statiſts, which yet is clothed in the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>be of a ſeeming Sanctimonious care, but this hypocriſie muſt not go long
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59927:36"/>unpuniſhed, neither does it, for now begins to appear the reſult of <hi>Lamberts</hi> deſignments abroad, in a remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative addreſs from the Army: at the very firſt newes, whereof the Parliament is ſo ſtartled, that, fearing to be whipped with their own rod, they ordered, Col.
<note place="margin">Armies remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the Juncto ſend for ſome Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</note> 
               <hi>Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> Col. <hi>Cobbet,</hi> and Lieutenant Col. <hi>Duckenfield,</hi> (three of the chief promoters of it) to bring to them the original paper, intended to be preſented; upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of which order given, immediately, a letter was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered into the houſe ſigned by many perſons of the Army, ſuperſcribed to the ſaid three ſummoned perſons, by whoſe hands they deſired the incloſed paper might be preſented to the Lord <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> and after to the generall Councill, which incloſed paper was intituled, to the ſupream authority of theſe Nations, the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> The humble Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition and propoſalls of the Officers under the Command of the Right Honourable the Lord <hi>Lambert</hi> in the late Northern expedition, the manner and method of which paper the Juncto ſo highly reſented (as ſuppoſing it to ſtrike at their very root) that they preſentely voted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That this houſe doth declare,
<note place="margin">Obſerve this crack.</note> that to have any more Generall Officers in the Army, than are already ſetled by Parliament, is needleſs chargeable and dangerous to the Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here was the firſt ſtep to that diviſion, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards grew into a flame but the Army Officers finding their deſign, was not yet ripe enough, by a diſſembled
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59927:37"/>acquieſcency, ſeemed to lay aſide their propoſalls, by ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying to the Parliament, that they would adhere to their authority in oppoſition to the common Enemy, and that they would ſtand by them in the ſettlement of the Common-wealth, againſt all diſturbances whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which lulled the Juncto into a kind of ſecurity, the City alſo at this time ſeeming to claw them by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation to a Thankſgiving dinner, whereat the field Officers of the Army were alſo to be preſent;
<note place="margin">Thanks-giving dinner in the City.</note> ſo that now being in a manner rid of their fear, they fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſequeſtring the Gentry, about Sir <hi>George Booths</hi> bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, ſettle the Exciſe, and revive the Aſſeſſements for the Militia, uſing all their skill and power for amaſſing together the wealth of the Nation into their private purſes, concluding with the <hi>Epicureans, ede, lude, bibe, poſt mortem nulla voluptas,</hi> ſo ſottiſhly ſtupid were they grown in their high flown ambition.</p>
            <p>But now, leaſt they ſhould forget their duty, the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Army preſent a new addreſs requiring an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thereto,
<note place="margin">Armies new ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs.</note> which made them take it into the ſeveral pieces wherein it was propoſed, wherein among other things (to ſhew you the harmony that was then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them) they give to their third propoſall this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.
<note place="margin">Juncto angry there with.</note> 
               <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Parliament declares, that every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Army, as free Men of</hi> England, <hi>have a right of petitioning the Parliament, but withall thinks fit to let them know, that the Petitioners ought to be very carefull, both in the manner, and in the matter of what
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59927:37"/>they deſire, that the way of promoting and preſenting the ſame may be peaceable, and the things petitioned for, not tending, to the disturbance of the Common-wealth, nor to the diſhonour of the Parliament. And that it is the duty of petitioners to ſubmit their deſires to the Parliament, and acquieſce in the judgment thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this Declaration they intended to curb the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingford</hi> party, by teaching them manners, and to know their diſtance; but they being Men of another ſpirit, and knowing they had the power of the ſword in their own hands, would not be ſo put off: which the Juncto, perceiving, and beginning to grow jealous of their own ſafety, and ſatisfyed that the Army could not ſubſiſt without money (which is the Nerve of War) to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the People to themſelves, and to diſ-inable the Officers from raiſing any money (in caſe they ſhould (which they now much doubted) interrupt them in their ſitting) they paſſed an Act againſt raiſing of monies upon the people, without their conſent in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. Part whereof take as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be it enacted, &amp;c. That all Orders,
<note place="margin">Act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt raiſing money without conſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment makes the Souldiery mad.</note> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and Acts, made by any ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and his Councill, or both, or either of them, or otherwiſe, or by any aſſembly or convention pretending to have Authority of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59927:38"/>Parliament, from and after the</hi> 19th. <hi>Day of</hi> April, 1653. <hi>and before the</hi> 7th. <hi>of</hi> May, 1659. <hi>And which have not been, or ſhall not be enacted, allowed, or confirmed by this preſent Parliament be, and are hereby decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, deemed, taken and adjudged to be of no force and effect from and after the ſaid ſeventh day of</hi> May 1659.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And be it further enacted, that no perſon or perſons, ſhall after the eleventh of</hi> Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, 1659. <hi>Aſſeſs, Levy, Collect, gather or receive any Cuſtom, Impost, Exciſe, Aſſeſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, contribution, Tax, Tallage, or any ſumme or ſumms of money or other impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whatſoever upon the people of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, without their conſent in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or as by law might have been done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the third of</hi> November, 1640. <hi>And that every perſon offending contrary to this Act ſhall be, and is hereby adjudged to be guilty of high Treaſon, and ſhall forfeit and ſuffer as in caſe of high Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Juncto had thrown abroad this killing thunderbolt, to ſhew that they durſt own the power which they yet conceived themſelves Maſters off, they
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59927:38"/>took into conſideration a Letter, dated <hi>October</hi> the 5th. and ſigned by diverſe Officers of the Army, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to Col. <hi>Okey,</hi> and alſo a printed paper, called the humble repreſentation and Petition of the Officers of the Army to the Parliament, &amp;c. Upon the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which two papers, the houſe was ſo highly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed and flew into ſuch a ſudden heat of paſſion, that without any more adoe they reſolved.</p>
            <p>That the ſeverall Commiſſions of, Col.
<note place="margin">9. <hi>great Officers diſplaced and voted out of commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>John Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> Col. <hi>John Desborow,</hi> Col. <hi>James Berry,</hi> Col. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Kelſey,</hi> Col. <hi>Richard Aſhfield,</hi> Col. <hi>Ralfe Cobbet,</hi> Major <hi>Richard Creed,</hi> Col. <hi>William Packer,</hi> and Col. <hi>Rob. Barrow,</hi> were null and void, and every of them diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from military imployment. And that the Army ſhould be governed by ſeven Commiſſioners, <hi>Viz. L.
<note place="margin">Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners to govern the Army.</note> G. Charles Fleetwood, L. G. Edm. Ludlow,</hi> Generall <hi>George Monck,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlelrig</hi> Barronet, Col <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentine Walton,</hi> Col. <hi>Harb. Morley,</hi> and Col. <hi>Robert Overton,</hi> or any three or more of them, which ſaid Commiſſioners, were to give notice to the ſaid nine Officers of the diſcharge of their Commiſſions, which being accordingly communicated, now might you have ſeen the ſmoaking embers of diſſembled friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, break out into an open flame of violent enmity, this great and ſo long domineering faction, being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in it ſelf, and each ſide prepairing for its own,
<note place="margin">The feud betwixt the rump and he Souldiery breaks out.</note> both defence, and elevation, for now <hi>a Quorum</hi> of the Commiſſioners which were appointed to govern the army, being gotten together, and ſitting all night in the Speakers chamber, which was within the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment houſe, to iſſue forth orders; part of the army with moſt of the diſcharged Principall Officers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently drew down to <hi>Westminſter</hi> in a warlike order,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59927:39"/>where they poſſeſſed themſelves of the great Hall, the Palace yard, and all avenues, and paſſages lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto, having before given out, that they found it abſolutely neceſſary for the good of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to break up this Parliament, for the maintaining whereof another part of the army were as active in drawing together, the ſame night alſo marching down to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and planting themſelves in <hi>Kingſtreet,</hi> and in and about the <hi>Abbey</hi> Church and Yard: This unuſuall aſſembly at ſuch an unaccuſtomed hour cauſed a generall terrour in the hearts and minds of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, who dreaded ſome greater miſchief than they were ſenſible of, but the night being paſt, in the morning the Speaker Mr. <hi>W. Lenthall,</hi> at his uſuall time came along <hi>Kingſtreet,</hi> and had paſſage through the ranks of Souldiers,
<note place="margin">The Rump turned out of doors.</note> till he came to the new Palace gate, where his Coach was ſtopped, and himſelf compelled to return home, as wiſe as he went, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the houſe was interrupted from ſitting; which was the chief thing that <hi>Lambert</hi> aimed at; yet though he had thus wrought his purpoſe, he durſt not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, but make good his ſtation againſt the other facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the greateſt part of the day, each of the Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick leaders (for ſo indeed they were both) expecting who ſhould give the firſt blow, of which meekneſs the then council of State taking notice, required both to draw off to their quarters, which motion was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly accepted on all hands, and ſo both ſides march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away.</p>
            <p>Thus have we ſeen that rump of pretended autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<note place="margin">Obſerve.</note> which in <hi>May</hi> was, with much ſolliciting, many intreaties, and not a few ſpecious pretences, courted to come into play, now again in <hi>October,</hi> with as great
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59927:39"/>ſcorn and malice laid a ſide and trampled on: <hi>Nec lex est juſtior ulla, quam necis artifices arte perire ſua,</hi> It hath been a generall Obſervation, that Treaſon is alwayes the greateſt puniſhment to it ſelf, like the Viper, it breeds young with her own deſtruction, and as the Poet ſpeaketh of envy, <hi>ſit licet injuſtus livor,</hi> ſo may I ſay of it, though it be unjuſt to others, yet is it very juſt, to deſtroy them firſt that would deſtroy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>The Councill of Officers having thus ſeized the Government into their hands,
<note place="margin">Officers meet.</note> played with it for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain dayes, till (with the old Philoſopher, in the queſtion about God) finding, the more they ſtudyed, the leſs they underſtood, and that they were led by an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> which only trained them to the ſight, but would never bring them to the certenty, of a ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and pondering their own many weakneſſes, and infirmities, with the exigency of affairs, they fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſideration of what was fit to be done: In the debate whereof, after many frivolous eſſayes, they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed at length among themſelves to nominate ſome perſons to be a Councill of State, which device being applauded, and a new name deviſed for them (for they will be called forſooth the Committee of ſafety) theſe following perſons were pitch'd upon,
<note place="margin">They erect a Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, their names and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters.</note> 
               <hi>Viz. Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> whoſe folly would have exempted, but they were affraid he would have cryed. Knowing alſo that the beft play ever hath a fool in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lambert</hi> a ſeeming Saint, but chief Engenier of the modell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Desborow</hi> a drunken Clown, skill'd in Harraſſing the land ſteel, once a ſneaking petty fogger, now Lord Chancellour of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and a Traytor.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:59927:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Whitlock</hi> a lump of ingratitude and deceit.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> chief ſecretary to the ſeven dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſins.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ludlow,</hi> once a Gentleman, but ſince by himſelf Levelled into the plebeyan rank.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sydenham,</hi> nothing good in him but his name.</p>
            <p>Upſtart <hi>Saloway Strickland,</hi> once a rumper, after a Lord of <hi>Nolls</hi> edition, then a convert to the good old cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Berry, ped<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m nequiſſimus,</hi> the wickedſt villain among 10000.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lawrence,</hi> once an upſtart privy Counceller, now ſcarce a Gentleman.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>James Harrington, Per riſum multum poſſis cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſcere.</hi>—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wareſton,</hi> a mickle knave geud faw Sir.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ireton,</hi> and <hi>Tichborn,</hi> two of the City Puckfoiſts, who lye leger in the Common Council, to diſcover plots for the getting of money.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Brandrith,</hi> fit for miſchief, elſe he had not been here.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thompſon,</hi> a dull fellow, but a ſoaking Committee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hewſon,</hi> the Common-wealths upright ſetter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sniveling</hi> Col. <hi>Clarke</hi> Factious, Col. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Col. <hi>Bennet,</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Holland,</hi> a moſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Apoſtate, both to God and his King.</p>
            <p>To theſe fellowes thus firly accoutred,
<note place="margin">Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty their power.</note> is the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment committed, and not only ſo, but they have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to call Delinquents to account, to oppoſe, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs all inſurrections; to treat with forreign States, and Princes, to raiſe the militia's in the ſeverall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. To diſpoſe of all places of truſt, with many other
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59927:40"/>things: by which may be ſeen, what an unlimited ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power they aſſumed to themſelves over the lives and eſtates of all Engliſhmen. And that all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> might take notice hereof,
<note place="margin">Armies decla ati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> they ſend out a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in print, entitled a Declaration of the General Council of the Officers of the Army, wherein they ſay they have lodged the civil and executive part of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, in the Committee of ſafety, whom they have obliged to prepare ſuch a form of Government, as may beſt ſute with a Free-State, without a ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Kingſhip or houſe of Peers: with many equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating, though Saint-like, expreſſions to the like effect, with which they hoped to delude the World, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinnue their uſurpation, but <hi>Sera venit ſed certa venit.</hi> All their hypocriticall ſhewes cannot cheat God, who raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up the Spirit of one among themſelves to chaſtiſe the errours of their pride, and vain glorious attempts: for no ſooner is that Infernall crew of Atheiſts met in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their Committee, but they are alarumed with a letter from General <hi>Monck</hi> out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> wherein he gives them notice that both himſelf and ſome Officers of the Army in <hi>Scotland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Monck <hi>diſſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</hi>
               </note> were much diſſatisfied in reference to the tranſactions of affairs in <hi>England,</hi> at the ſame time receiving intelligence that he had, ſeized ſeverall ſtrong holds, ſecured diverſe of his diſſenting Officers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seizeth</hi> Barwick.</note> and poſſeſſed himſelf of <hi>Barwick,</hi> which drove them for a time into a kind of Phanatick ſtupidity, that they knew not which way to move in the management of their affairs, but at laſt willing to preſerve themſelves, they order the forces in the North into a poſture, and command <hi>lambert</hi> with more Regiments out of the Southerly parts to joyn with them, that ſo they might appear formidable at leaſt at a diſtance, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59927:41"/>put a ſtay to the violence which they foreſaw was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching to them;
<note place="margin">Lambert <hi>marcheth againſt him.</hi>
               </note> for the prevention of which ſtorm Col. <hi>Cobbet</hi> is ſent to General <hi>Monck</hi> with inſinuating relations, whom the Generall immediately upon his arrivall commits to cuſtody, thereby, preſerving his Army from the dangerous contrivances that Perſon brought along with him, and depriving of the intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence he might have carried to <hi>England</hi> back with him: which being done by the power of his Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as one of the ſeven) he ſtraight new models his Army, according to his own mind, and then declares his reſolution to aſſert the authority of Parliament, againſt all violence whatſoever. Upon newes of this, our ſafe Committeemen, knowing the pulſe of the late Juncto to beat after the mode of a free-ſtate, think they ſhall merit highly at the hands of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, if they promote that, though they diſown the Parliament he pretended to declare for, and to that purpoſe having nominated ſeverall Gallant fellowes of their own number, <hi>Viz. Fleetwood, Vane, Ludlow, Saloway, Tichburn, Lambert, Desborow, Hewſen, Holland,</hi> and others, to conſider of, and prepare, a form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to be ſetled over the three Nations,
<note place="margin">Safe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</note> in the way of a Free-State and Common-wealth, they ſend away <hi>Whalley, Goffe, Caryl,</hi> and <hi>Barker,</hi> to ſhew the ſame to General <hi>Monck,</hi> and thereupon to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate with him for avoiding the effuſion of blood: the Officers at <hi>London</hi> writing alſo to his Officers, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulating with them, touching the neceſſity of a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly union, crying out of nothing but Liberty, while the Nation groan'd under their oppreſſion; But <hi>Menck</hi> revolving with himſelf, both the greatneſs, difficulty, and hazard, of his deſign, concludes not to be raſh in
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59927:41"/>a direct quarrel, but rather by procraſtinations to weaken the force of his enemies (which he knew could not continue long without money) and ſo to gain the victory without ſtriking a blow, therefore to amuſe them, and caſt the more ſeeming gloſs upon his action he orders Col. <hi>Talbot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Monck de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires a treaty.</note> and Dr. <hi>Clargies</hi> (who were the firſt meſſengers ſent to him) to ſend <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> word that himſelf and his Officers had nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Col. <hi>Wilkes</hi> L. C. <hi>Cloberry,</hi> and Major <hi>Knight,</hi> to repair ſpeedily to <hi>London,</hi> and treat with the like number of Officers there, for a firm unity and peace, and the better to confirm it, he ſends another Letter from himſelf to the ſame purpoſe, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that his forces ſhould advance no further. But the Committee of ſafery, willing by ſtrength to hold what they had got, and not knowing what to think of the Generall, iſſue out many ſeverall Commiſſions to raiſe forces throughout all <hi>England,</hi> to anticipate him, and to ſettle Militia's to be ready in a moment,
<note place="margin">Militia ſetled.</note> as it were to reſiſt him: which he hearing, and that <hi>Lambert</hi> was coming againſt him with thirteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, be according to his before mentioned Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, forthwith ſends his three appointed meſſengers for peace, upon whoſe arrivall at <hi>Yorke,</hi> in <hi>November,</hi> and ſpeech with <hi>Lambert,</hi> he became ſo farr ſatisfied of their intentions towards an Accommodation, that thereupon he gave order his forces ſhould advance no further Northward in their march.</p>
            <p>Things being brought now into this poſture,
<note place="margin">The treary begun.</note> the Generalls three Commiſſioners arrive at <hi>London, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> the 12th. where the Treaty is immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun: which lulled the Committee of ſafety into ſuch a ſecurity, that they begin to think of ſhareing great
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59927:42"/>Offices and places of truſt and profit among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to this end, appointing <hi>Fleetwood, Desborow, Sydenham, Saloway, Cornelius Holland,</hi> Col. <hi>Clark,</hi> Col. <hi>John Blackwell,</hi> or any two of them to be Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners for the Treaſury, and to manage the affaris of the publick revenue, with power as large as could be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: (And would it not be well managed think you in the hands of ſuch bankrupts) but while theſe men mind their own wealth only, the Treaty muſt not be forgotten, which was now in hand, and on a ſudden brought to ſuch an iſſue, that it ſtartled the City, who had by Col. <hi>Alured,</hi> and Collonel <hi>Markham</hi> received Letters from <hi>Scotland</hi> of another purport, for at laſt the Commiſſioners on both ſides agreed on theſe heads en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, that is to ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the pretended Title of</hi> CHARLES STU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ART,
<note place="margin">The arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Treaty.</note> 
               <hi>or any other claiming from that family ſhould be utterly renounced.</hi> (O horrid Treaſon, firſt murder the Father, and then abjure the Son!)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Government of theſe Nations, ſhall be by a free State or Common-wealth, and not by a ſingle perſon, King, or houſe of Lords.</hi> What muſt the new ſettlement utterly aboliſh all the old fundamentall Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at one breath? Your Precipitation bodes your ruine.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:59927:42"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That a Godly and learned Miniſtery, ſhall be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and encouraged:</hi> 'Tis well the Generalls Men thought of it, for you may be aſſured it is againſt the principle of Anabaptiſts, and fifth-Monarchy Men;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Univerſities ſhall be reformed and countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, ſo, as that they may become Nurſeries of Piety, and Learning. That the Officers and Souldiers, and other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons on either ſide be indemnified for what is paſt, touching their late difference, and that all unkindneſs betwixt them be buried in perpetuall Oblivion;</hi> pray take care of that: but it may be ſuppoſed you ſhall be the furtheſt off when you think your ſelf neereſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Officers which were made priſoners in</hi> Scotland, <hi>be forthwith ſet at liberty;</hi> How will the Generall like that?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Armies be preſently diſpoſed into quarters, and that there be a committee of nineteen whereof nine to make the</hi> Quorum, <hi>who were to meet about qualifications, for ſucceeding Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the effect of part of the agreement, which was ſent away with all ſpeed to Generall <hi>Monck;</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on knowledge whereof, and by reaſon, the concluſions of the ſaid Treaty were ſo contrary to the Letters, by them formerly received, the City was ſtartled,
<note place="margin">The City ſtartle.</note> having
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59927:43"/>(as they ſuppoſed by order) been encouraged to ſtand faſt in their liberty for their Laws, Priviledges, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, and lawfull Government.</p>
            <p>But the Generall in a wiſe foreſight, and providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall care, having caſt in his mind the danger he ſtood in (for he had a wolfe by the ears) though he ſent his Commiſſioners aforeſaid, yet reſerved to himſelf the rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, ſo that nothing ſhould be of force untill it were confirmed with his own ſeal: But now the articles of the Treaty being come to his hands, he commands the return of his Commiſſioners, which they obeying, he preſently commits Col.
<note place="margin">Monck <hi>commits one of his Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Wilks</hi> to cuſtody for going beyond his Commiſſion) declareth the Treaty void, and marcheth toward the borders: which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of ſafety being advertiſed off, fall to their old tricks to delude the people, endeavouring to make them believe it was only a rumour grounded on a fained Letter pretended to be by him ſent to the City, whereas they ſeemed to be aſſured that he would acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſce in the former agreement, but truth who is <hi>filia temporis,</hi> the daughter of time, quickly appeared to undeceive the people; for in this <hi>interim</hi> his excellency (having as himſelf expreſſed it a call from God and Man, to march into <hi>England,</hi> for reſetling the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) calleth an aſſembly of the Nobles and Gentry of <hi>Scotland</hi> at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>He calls an adem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in</hi> Scotland.</note> to whom he propoſed theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they would, during his abſence, which would not be long, preſerve and ſecure the peace of that Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they would ſupply him with ſome men for his undertaking (which he engaged upon his honour ſhould be to their ſatisfaction) and that if any troubles
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59927:43"/>ſhould ariſe, they would aſſiſt him in the ſuppreſſing thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they would advance and raiſe what money they could before hand.</p>
            <p>To theſe Propoſitions the Earl of <hi>Glencarn,</hi> who was chaitman of that aſſembly, returned theſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt anſwers.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they could not engage to preſerve the peace of the Countrey in his abſence, wanting armes, and ſo in no condition to do it, but they ſhould with all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs notwithſtanding endeavour it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They they were uncapable to anſwer his deſires for the reaſons aforeſaid, neither did they think it prudent for them to engage in a war, which if it ſhould prove unſucceſsfull on their part, would be a ruine to them: or if ſucceſsfull, they did not underſtand, that it would be advantagious to them in any meaſure. But as to the third.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they were content to levy moneys, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance a years tax aforehand.</p>
            <p>Generall <hi>Monck</hi> highly ſatisfied with thoſe civil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes, endeavours to careſce and indear them by.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Giving the Lords and gentry power to arme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> by ſatisfying them privately in the deſign of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> his expedition, and accepting of their years taxes.</p>
            <p>Hereupon he reſolves now to dally no longer than his ſupplies of Men and money come in, in the mean while holding correſpondence and intelligence with his friends all over <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He keeps intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</note> from whom he a new received advertiſement, that if he could yet for a litle time keep fairly at a diſtance, his work ſhould be done e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven without any noiſe of drum or trumpet except it were in exultation and triumph. This adviſe cauſed
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59927:44"/>him to make ſome ſeeming overtures of a ſecond treaty with <hi>Lambert,</hi> yet all along inſiſting upon the re-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Parliament, before they began it.</p>
            <p>As a balk to which the Committee of ſafety de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingford <hi>in govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </note> (hoping thereby yet to lead the Nation into further errour and miſchief) that they had tranſmitted a great part of a form of government for theſe Nations to a Committee of the Officers of the Army ('tis like to be well done if it muſt be hewen out by a dint of the ſword) to be conſidered by them, (a mad crew of <hi>Gotamists</hi>) who daily meet, and are gone through a great part of it with much ſatisfaction, (to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves poſſibly to think how finely they ſhould Lord it, but to no body elſe ſurely) they are very deſirous to have ſuch a Government, as may preſerve the Liberties of the Nation (this is the old cheat) and ſecure the cauſe they have contended in (which is flat treaſon and rebellion) both againſt <hi>CHARLES STV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ART,</hi> and any other that may diſturbe the peace: hoping in time to make it appear, that their Enemies are Liers when they traduce them and render them a people that ſeek only themſelves. Then they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that they hope the faith of Gods people will hold out and not make haſt, and that good men will help them in their prayers, that God the Lord would bring forth righteouſneſs and truth, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, and bring to nought the ſecret contrivances of all his adverſaries: And ſo no doubt, he will to the ſhame and ruine of all ſuch diſſembling Hypocrites.</p>
            <p>About this time being the later end of <hi>November,</hi> the People beginning to ſmell their knavery, drew ſeveral Petitions, with an intent to deliver them, but their crazie ſtomacks being not able to bear ſuch ſtrong Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59927:44"/>belched forth a Proclamation againſt all ſuch Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions,
<note place="margin">Proclaim aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which they call undue and dangerous pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and prohibite all perſons to ſubſcribe any ſuch papers, and if offered to ſuppreſs them, or cauſe the perſon endeavouring to get ſubſcriptions to be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, upon penalty of being accounted diſturb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs to, and enemies of, the peace.</p>
            <p>But this not working its defired effect, but rather making men the more eager, ſo as they began to fear tumultuous proceedings, therefore the Mayor is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and he accordingly ſent warrants to all City Officers to charge all Maſters of families to keep in their Sons and Servants: This enraged the youth of the City to ſuch a height, that the Committee of ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fearing their own danger to ariſe from ſome diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance there, gave order <hi>December</hi> the 5th. to part of the Army,
<note place="margin">Hewſon <hi>gees into</hi> London.</note> both horſe and foot to march into the City, which they did early in the morning, where being entred, great multitudes of all ſorts of people gathered together in the Streets, the ſhops were ſhut up, and the Souldiers in all places affronted, which ſo madded them, that by command of their Col. <hi>Hewſon,</hi> they fell on the people with ſome violence, and killed two or three perſons, wherewith the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude for the preſent diſperſed, but began to bear a grudge, whoſe revenge would not be ſatisfied but with the ruine of their oppreſſours. This was the laſt help they had to rely on that they would rather reduce all to a <hi>Chaos,</hi> than quit their hold, ſnatching at every the leaſt opportunity that did but flatteringly ſeem to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them an advantage: for by this, though unwillingly, foreſeeing their Cataſtrophe at hand they are driven into more ſad thoughts of their diſſolution, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59927:45"/>of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> which <hi>Haſterig, Walton,</hi> and <hi>Morley,</hi> with the conſent of Col. <hi>Whetham,</hi> the Governour had gained: now might any man gueſs their time to be ſhort by the violent extravagancy of their actions, for <hi>nullum violentum diuturnum;</hi> the news of which arriving to them, they ſent ſome horſe and foot either to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce or block up that garriſon (here we ſee, now we ſee that great and divelliſh faction of Independency ſtrongly divided) but ſoft and fair, the game goes quite contrary, as will appear afterwards.</p>
            <p>During this dealing at <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> the Army Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers finding that nothing would ſatisfie the People, but either to re-admit the Rump Parliament or have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, they to give them hopes of a glimmering of content, Ordered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That a Parliament ſhall be called and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſit down in or before</hi> February <hi>next.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of ſafery.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Parliament to be called as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, ſhall be according to ſuch qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as are or ſhall be agreed upon, and may beſt ſecure the juſt rights, liberties, and priviledges of the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This muſt be ſolemnly proclaimed forſooth by their journey men of ſafety, together with another edict of the ſame ſtamp, commanding all honeſt and loyal ſouls out of the Cities of <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Westminster,</hi> upon pain, of impriſonment, and to be proceeded againſt as traytours, and executed: By this means, they
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59927:45"/>thought to walk in a miſt without any ſuperviſors, but alas they were much miſtaken, for though they thus cleered themſelves, as they thought, from fear of the Common Enemy (as they termed all loyaliſts) yet they could not free themſelves of their new gotten Enemies at <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> by whoſe policy they were out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witted and caſheired: yet nevertheleſs ſeven princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and unalterable ſundamentalls are agreed on, which were publiſhed to this effect, by theſe high and mighty <hi>Johns</hi> a Leyden.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That no Kingſhip ſhall be exerciſed in theſe Nations.
<note place="margin">Walling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford 7. <hi>principles of Rule</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That they will not have any ſingle perſon to exerciſe the office of chief Magiſtrate in theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That an Army may be continued and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and be conducted, ſo as it may ſecure the peace of theſe Nations, and not be disbanded, nor the conduct thereof altered but by conſent of the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatours appointed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That no impoſition may be upon the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of them that fear God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That there be no houſe of Peers.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the Legiſlative and Executive power be diſtinct, and not in the ſame hands.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That the aſſemblies of the Parliament ſhall be elected by the people of this Common-wealth, duly qualified.</p>
            <p>Here you ſee the ſcope of theſe <hi>Bedlamites,</hi> and what a fine hotch potch they would have made,
<note place="margin">Lawſon <hi>declares.</hi>
               </note> but their ſport was quickly ſpoiled by a Declaration from Vice-admirall <hi>Lawſon</hi> giving ſeverall reaſons of a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for the long Parliament to ſit again, neither
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59927:46"/>would any thing elſe ſatisfie him, though Sir <hi>Henry Vane</hi> himſelf with his Jeſuited and poyſonous breath ſought to infect him.</p>
            <p>Now alſo had <hi>Haſlerig, Morley,</hi> and others ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirred themſelves, and by their policy wrought upon the Souldiers that were ſent by the <hi>Wallingfordians</hi> againſt them that they all came over to them, and relinquiſhed their preten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed Maſters, whoſe want of money (if nothing elſe) would have made their cauſe ſeem bad enough, eſpecially ſince the rogue of all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ran directly encounter to their deſignes, their being motions almoſt in every County, ſome for the Rump wholy, others for the joyning of the ſecluded members to them, but moſt, and they the wiſeſt, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derateſt, and not leaſt conſiderable were for a full and free Parliament, but Independency being not yet ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at its full period,
<note place="margin">Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies firſt de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> begins firſt to decline by the General advance, though in part ſeemingly upheld by admitting the Rump-Parliament again into their full power, as when they were interrupted the thirteenth of <hi>October</hi> before going, who accordingly, on the four and twentyeth day of <hi>December,</hi> were owned by all the Souldiery, both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> as the ſuprem authority with much ſolemnity, the Speaker <hi>Lenthall</hi> going immediately to take care of the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> the Government whereof he committed for the time preſent to Sir <hi>Anthony Aſhly-Cooper,</hi> Mr. <hi>Weever,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Berners,</hi> and on <hi>Munday</hi> the 26th. of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> in the evening by twilight began to ſit again, and were as peremptorily imperious as before, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Lambert</hi> to <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth.</hi>
               </note> whoſe forces were all, either revolted away to General <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nck,</hi> or piece meal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired into quarters for want of pay, yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59927:46"/>all this removall of force from them, they thought not themſelves ſecure, untill he by his authority came to awe the Souldiery, and people, who were now grown tumultuous, and as ready to throw them out of the ſadle, as they had done the <hi>Wallingford</hi> faction.</p>
            <p>His excellency therefore,
<note place="margin">Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k <hi>marches to</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</note> (who could never be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſince he firſt went thither) now layes hold on this opportunity, to do his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſervice, having therefore, as is before mentioned, ſecured <hi>Scotland,</hi> he likewiſe deals with Sir <hi>Charles Coot,</hi> and others in <hi>Ireland,</hi> who ſtriking a perfect harmony with him, did ſurpriſe the moſt eminent Phanaticks in the midſt of their deſignes in <hi>Dublin</hi> Caſtle, and ſtop <hi>Ludlow,</hi> who was commander in chief in <hi>Ireland,</hi> at Sea, by this means making all <hi>Ireland</hi> ſure for the Parliament [for ſuch yet was the pretence] as it was in the 12th. of <hi>October,</hi> 1659. This wrought ſo effectually, and even to ſuch an exceſs of joy in the Parliament, that they not only approved of all Generall <hi>Monkes</hi> former actions, but ordered the hearty thanks of the houſe to be given to him for his fidelity, and faithfull ſervice, and a letter of thanks to be ſent to him, ſigned by Mr. Speaker, a proper reward ſurely, as if one word of their mouths were a ſufficient recompence for all labours, hazards, and travels.</p>
            <p>While they are thus minding themſelves and boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their own ſtrength, they receive a cooling card from ſome of the ſecluded members, who demanded to be admitted to ſit, if that Parliament were not bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, which put our muſhromes Juncto into ſuch a dump, that they were fain to paſs this following Reſolve.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:59927:47"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="resolution">
                        <head>Tueſday 27. <hi>December.</hi> 1659.</head>
                        <opener>Reſolved,
<note place="margin">Note this.</note>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>That on the fifth of</hi> January <hi>next, this houſe will take into conſideration the caſe of all abſent Members, and alſo how to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the vacant places in order to the filling up of the houſe; and that in the mean time it be referred to a Committee, to conſider of all proceedings, and all orders, and caſes touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abſent members, and make their report at the ſame time.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But this did not prove ſatisfactory, as they expected it ſhould, for the City begins to grow diſcontent, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring themſelves for a poſture of defence; In the Country the caſheired Officers, and the depreſſed No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Gentry beſtir themſelves, courting his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency all along in his march, and ecchoing in his cars perpetually a free Parliament, to whom he gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally gave no other anſwers, but that he would uſe his utmoſt intereſt, to perſwade them to reaſon and Juſtice, in the mean time wiſhing them to acquieſce in what they ſhould order; thus he marcheth with his whole Army, modelling to his own mind all Gariſons and forces in his way: This and his number of men that he brought with him, being far beyond allowance, (for they ordered only three hundred) put our Rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to a ſtand, and they could not be ſatisfied untill
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59927:47"/>they ſend the ſubtileſt couple in the houſe,
<note place="margin">Scot <hi>and</hi> Robinſon <hi>are ſent to</hi> Monck.</note> 
               <hi>Scot</hi> and <hi>Robinſon,</hi> to ſound his intention, under pretence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulating his coming to <hi>England,</hi> and complementing him, to whom he carried himſelf with ſo much gravity and reſervedneſs, that they could not catch one dropping ſyllable that might betray him.</p>
            <p>About this time the City by their Sword-bearer,
<note place="margin">The City <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him.</note> ſend to him, to whom he returnes, that he is for the Parliament as aforeſaid, yet aſſures them that, when he came to the City, he would ſatisfie their deſires and hopes conceived of him, thus owning the authority then in being, he keeps cloſe to his commiſſion, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witſtanding all the addreſſes of the Countries for a free Parliament, promiſing nothing more but that he would ſee all force removed from the Parliament, 2. The Houſe filled, and 3. That there ſhould be good proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made for future Parliaments. Thus with a ſlow and orderly march,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>He comes to St.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans.</note> attended by the prayers and wiſhes of the whole Nation, he comes at length to St. <hi>Albans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this interval of time, the Rumpers minding to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſs the whole power, both Legiſlative, and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive into their own hands, and to ſhare all places of truſt and profit among themſelves: on the fifth of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> paſs this following vote.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="resolution">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Reſolved,
<note place="margin">
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                                    <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                                 </gap>.</note>
                           </salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Touching abſent Members, that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament doth adjudge and declare, that the Members who stand diſcharged from voting or fitting in the years</hi> 1648. <hi>and</hi> 1649. <hi>do stand duly diſcharged by judgment of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59927:48"/>from ſitting as Members of this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, during this Parliament; and that writs do iſſue forth for electing of new Members in their places.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Thus did they intend to have perpetuated themſelves for their lives, and to have bequeathed their villany in ſucceſſion, to ſuch as were to be new choſen, having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready concluded,
<note place="margin">Cath of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that the Oath of renunciation of the title of CHARLES STUART (as theſe unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly mungrels were pleaſed to ſtile their Soveraign) and the whole line of the late King <hi>James</hi> ſhould be taken by every member that hereafter ſhall ſit in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, nay ſo high were they now grown, that they committed diverſe for but Petitioning for a free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>This made his Excellency haſt up to <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> where his Lady and Family were come before him by Sea; into which City he comes about the beginning of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> and takes up his lodging at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> as the Parliament had appointed him (contrary to the thoughts of many) and after two or three dayes refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (taking no notice of his reſentment of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid inſolencies) he ſolemnly attends the houſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their order,
<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and with much modeſty gives them an account of his undertakings, refuſing the chair offered him for his eaſe and honour, but leaning on the back of it, he delivered himſelf to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he deſerved not the thanks they gave him,
<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſpeech <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> having done no more than his duty, but wiſhed them rather to praiſe God for his mercy: then he humbly deſired them to ſatisfie the expectation of the Nation in the establiſhment of their
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59927:48"/>laws, liberties, properties, &amp;c. God having reſtored them, not ſo much that they ſhould ſeek their own, as the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, good. He deſired them in particular to take away the jealouſie, men had of their perpetuity, by determining their own ſeſſions, and providing for future Parliaments, wiſhing them to uſe the Nobility and Gentry civilly, intimating that it was their wiſdom rather to enlarge, than contract their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, he told them, that the fewer qualifications they put upon ſucceeding Parliaments, the better, and deſired them to be tender in impoſing new oaths (for he had heard of the eath of abrenunciation) alledging there was more reaſon to repent of thoſe already taken, than to take new ones, ſo warning them to take heed of Cavaliers, and Phanaticks, he concluded, commending</hi> Scotland <hi>to their care, and aſſuring them of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and hinting at a Free-State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This done, and he retired loaden with thanks,
<note place="margin">How the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>emp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> him.</note> he withdrawes to his place in the Councill of State, where the firſt that he finds under conſideration is the reducing of the City, (which to make a ſhort digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was now grown unruly, being ſtifly reſolved to own no power, but that of a full and Free Parliament, whereto they had been encouraged by the Country in ſeverall Declarations, but eſpecially that of <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> which in regard it gives the ſence of all in one, and was that chiefly ſtuck to by the City: I ſhall give it you at large, as Mr. <hi>Bamfield,</hi> the Recorder of <hi>Exon,</hi> ſent it to the Speaker, <hi>January</hi> the 14th.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:59927:49"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="declaration">
                        <head>The Declaration.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>We the Gentry of</hi> Devon, <hi>finding our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves without a Regular Government, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your laſt interruption, deſigned a publick meeting to conſult remedies, which we could not ſo conveniently effect till this weeke at our general quarter Seſſions, at</hi> Exon; <hi>where we found diverſe of the Inhabitants groaning under high oppreſſions, and a general defect of trade, to the utter ruine of many, and fear of the like to others, (which is ſo viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the whole Country) that it occaſioned ſuch diſorders, as were no ſmall trouble and diſturbance to us, which (by Gods bleſſing upon our endeavours) were ſoon ſuppreſt without blood: And though we find, ſince our last purpoſes, an alteration in the State of affairs, by the re-aſſembling you at the helme of Government, yet we conceive that we are but in part redreſt of our grievances, and that the chief expedient to amend the whole, will be the recalling all thoſe Members that were ſecluded in</hi> 1648. <hi>And ſate before the firſt force upon the Parliament, and alſo by
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59927:49"/>filling up vacant places, and all to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted without any Oath and engagement previous to their entrance, for which things if you pleaſe to take a ſpeedy courſe, we ſhall defend you againſt all oppoſers, and future interrupters, with our Lives and fortunes: for the accompliſhment whereof we ſhall uſe all lawfull means, which we humbly conceive may best conduce to the peace and ſafety of this Nation.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>This was ſigned by moſt of the chief gentry of the Country.</p>
            <p>Now the City, owning the purport of this Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by one of their own, and refuſing to pay taxes, had drawn the Councill of State to that violent ebulliency, of reducing it to a ſubmiſſion, which was, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the point, upon which they fell, when firſt General <hi>Monck,</hi> came firſt among them;
<note place="margin">Mo. goes into the City and demands taxes.</note> for they had rather bring the whole World into a combuſtion than their uſurped power either to equals or ſuperiours, they were ſo in love with power, that they would not have left pilling, as long as there had remained any matter ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſatisfie their ambition or covetouſneſs; wherefore they reſolve to drive on furiouſly, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore give order to the Generall to march into the City, with ſo many horſe and foot, as ſhould reduce them to an obedience, and compell them to pay the Aſſeſſment. His excellency according to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59927:50"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:59927:50"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:59927:51"/>being then their ſervant, went to the City, and at <hi>Guildhall</hi> peremptorily demandeth, by order from the Parliament and Councell of State, the payment of their taxes: this ſo ſudden demand, coming from him (from whom they hoped better things) and quite contrary to their expectation, drove the Citizens to ſuch a <hi>non-plus,</hi> that for a time they were as extaſied not knowing what to ſay, but at laſt, recollecting ſomewhat of an Engliſh temper, they return this anſwer. <hi>That in</hi> Magna Charta <hi>confirmed by the Petition of right, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed by the preſent Parliament, a day before their force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able diſſolution upon the</hi> 11 <hi>of</hi> October, <hi>they were to pay no taxes, &amp;c. but by their conſent in Parliament, which now they had not:</hi> yet to avoid giving any offence, they deſire time to conſider of it, which the Generall grants, but in the mean time writes to the houſe to know their pleaſure, to which they preſently anſwer, that 1. he ſhould impriſon Col. <hi>Bromfield,</hi> Alderman <hi>Bludworth,</hi> L. C. <hi>Jackſon,</hi> Major <hi>Cox,</hi> Col. <hi>Vincent, &amp;c.</hi> Some of which had waited upon him from the City but a little before; 2. that he ſhould remove their chains, dig up their poſts, and break their gates.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſtrange orders being brought to him,
<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his carriage in that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igent of affairs.</note> did a litle ſtartle him, knowing they were ſent as well to try his patience and obedience; as to breed an open enmity between him and the City, thereby to compell him to ſerve them perpetually, by being aſſured that they were mortall enemies; yet not willing, ſince he had gone ſo farr with ſucceſs, to looſe all now by paſſion, he with ſilence obeyes them readily, and thereby cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finds the temper of the City to be poſitively reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute for Liberty and right, ſo that being ſenſible they might be truſted, he hopes ſhortly to make them an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59927:51"/>which he had an occaſion offered to do ſoon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e than he expected,
<note place="margin">Is ungene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all'd.</note> for the Parliament had a double de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign upon him, firſt to weaken him in his intereſt and credit, by an imployment which they knew would ſo incenſe the City, and then while he is acting their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable commands, they are buſie in undermining him in his power; for when he had done their deſign as they thought, to the enraging of the Citizens, and breeding in their hearts revengefull thoughts,
<note place="margin">He joynes with the City.</note> he returnes to <hi>White-Hall</hi> upon <hi>Friday</hi> the 10th. Day of <hi>February,</hi> upon which day his Commiſſion did expire, inſtead of the renewing whereof, which he might with much juſtice have expected, as the reward of his merit, he is made a Colonel again, and only made equal in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand with ſix men more, as ſhort of him in deſert, as in honeſty, wherewith when he had acquainted the Officers of his Army, who were much unſatisfied with ſuch a reward for their late abominated imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, agreed unanimouſly among themſelves, that the Parliament intended to lay them aſide, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their former faithfull ſervice to them, and to perpetuate the Nations ſlavery, by their dateleſneſs: and therefore they reſolved to march with their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral into the City to joyn with them, and declare for a free Parliament: to this purpoſe a conference is had at the Three Tunnes near <hi>Guild-hall,</hi> where the City and Army ſtrike hands, at which time his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies Officers remonſtrate the reſent they had of the violence they were commanded to offer that famous City, which was of a ſtamp unparalleled in the moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid rage of former ages, whoſe barbarouſneſs even ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that, when they haraſſed the whole Nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, then give warning of ſeveral perſons, both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59927:52"/>and without the City, whoſe tyrannous minds they feared, abhorring in an eſpeciall manner a late pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition delivered in the houſe by one <hi>Praiſe-God Bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone,</hi> being a treaſonous libell, ſubverſive of all order and Government, dangerous to religion, both in diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and worſhip, and deſtructive to all Lawes, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and Cuſtomes, even in fundamentalls, wiſhing at laſt the Parliament to think of determining their Seſſion, and provide for future Parliaments.</p>
            <p>This being, by his Officers I ſay, preſented to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and by him in a letter communicated to the Speaker, he marcheth into <hi>London,</hi> and taketh quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Free</hi> P. <hi>promiſed</hi>
               </note> declaring for a free Parliament; and this blow was it, made Independency ſtagger, for ſo highly were both City and Country pleaſed with this Declaration, that they did hardly know in what manner to expreſs their joy, ringing their bells, making bonfires, the air reſounding nothing but the name and prayſes of <hi>Monck,</hi> and the Streets filled with gratefull hearts, who on bended knees prayed for bleſſings on the head of the hoped reſtorer, both of the Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and in this relolution he perſiſted, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the flatteries, threatnings and ſnares of the houſe, who now ſtudied nothing more than his ruine, as in him foreſeeing their own, nevertheleſs he waits for the Parliaments anſwer to his laſt letters to them, but finding they neither minded him nor them, and thought of nothing but ſetling their own intereſt, and continuing themſelves in power, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures a conference between ſome fitting members of the houſe, and ſome of the honourable Gentlemen and worthy Patriots that were excluded from it, at which himſelf being in perſon preſent, and weighing ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59927:52"/>the reaſons and arguments formed on both fides, which he heard with a deep and reſerved ſilence, after all were withdrawn, he concluded with himſelf, upon reſult from the whole, that the pretended ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement propoſed by the houſe, was of compaſs too narrow, and too weak of foundation to bear up the Nation, and repair its breaches:
<note place="margin">Secluded members admitted.</note> he reſolved therefore to withdraw all manner of force from the houſe, and to admit men of more ſober, moderate, and leſs byaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed judgments, whoſe Spirits being more apt for publick good, would eſtabliſh the Kingdom, upon termes comprehenſive of every conſiderable intereſt therein: hereupon, on the one and twentyeth day of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> meeting the ſecluded members at <hi>White-hall,</hi> and expreſſing himſelf to them in a ſpeech not delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by himſelf, but by his Secretary, wherein he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to their care,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Religion, that great <hi>primum mobile &amp; unum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarium,</hi> without which to live rather befits beaſts than men, and this was propoſed in the moſt ſober and moderate way imaginable, yet neither countenancing errour nor allowing libertiniſme.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He commended to them the State, deſiring them to be good Phyſitians to its crazed body, by applying ſuteable Phyſick, which (he ſaid) he ſuppoſed would be a full and a free Parliament, upon whoſe reſolves, as himſelf; ſo he doubted not but the whole Nation would acquieſce, he told them the houſe was open for them to enter, and prayed for their good ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>The ſecluded members being thus admitted,
<note place="margin">How they begin and wherein proceed.</note> fall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to work where they were abruptly forced to break of in <hi>December.</hi> 1648. Confirming their Vote made then by another now, that the conceſſions
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59927:53"/>of the late King were a ſufficient ground to proceed on for ſetling the peace of the Kingdom, hereby not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vindicating themſelves, but as it were at once diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anulling all that had been done as diſſonant thereto, during the whole time of their receſs.</p>
            <p>This began to infuſe a new ſpirit of life into the Kingdom, in whom at this ſpringing ſeaſon of the year, began a new to bud and peep out the bloomes of a too long froſt-nipped loyalty, ſo that one now might have ſeen what twenty years before could never ſhew, countenances, that lately were dejected through the cruell tyranny of their Aegipitian task maſters, now ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cheerfull looks, and like freſh blown roſes yield a fragant ſavour.</p>
            <p>The Parliament thus ſitting, freely vote his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy Lord Generall of all the forces in <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> by vertue of which Commiſſion he diſarmes all the Phanatick party, both in City and Country, the Parliament in the mean time providing to ſecure the Nation by two ſeaſonable Acts, the one of Aſſeſſment, and the other of the Militia; the laſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering and arming Gentlemen, and Men of worth and power, to ſtand up for their Liberties, and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and put the Country into a poſture of defence, againſt all encroaching pretenders whatſoever; and the former enabling them to raiſe moneyes (which are the ſineues of war) for maintaining of the forces, ſo raiſed to aſſert their and our rights.</p>
            <p>Thus ſetling the ancient Government of the City, and vacating the Phanatick power in the Country, they commend the eſtabliſhment of the Nation to a full and free Parliament, to be called the 25th. of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill,</hi> 1660. Iſſuing out writs to that purpoſe in the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59927:53"/>name of the keepers of the Liberty of <hi>England,</hi> by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliament, and ſetling a Councell of State of moſt diſcreet and moderate men, to whom the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the three Nations, in the intervall, and untill the meeting of the Parliament, on the aforeſaid 25th. of <hi>Aprill</hi> was committed, who with much diſcretion managed their power, to the ſatisfaction of all ſober minded men, and ſo (ſaving to the houſe of Lords their rights, notwithſtanding the Commons were in this Juncture of time, put upon neceſſity to act without them) commending the Souldiery once more to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency upon the ſixteenth day of <hi>March,</hi> in the year of our Lord 1659.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lorg</hi> P. <hi>legally ended.</hi>
               </note> (a day worthy to be remembred) they diſſolved themſelves, and ſo at laſt put a legall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to that fatall long-Parliament, which could not be diſſolved by any but by it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And thus we ſee Independency laid in the duſt, and ready to give up the ghoſt, and indeed not long after we ſhall ſee fully to expire the <hi>Prodromi,</hi> of whoſe miſerable end might be theſe and the like.</p>
            <p>The Councel of State in this intervall of power,
<note place="margin">The inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall.</note> with very great caution and warineſs, manage their affairs, turning neither to the right hand nor to the left, but keeping a direct courſe, as knowing <hi>in medio ibunt tutiſſimi,</hi> they ſet out a Proclamation againſt all diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the peace, under what pretence or name ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſparing none that in a time of ſuch hopes durſt either move a hand or tongue to work a diſturbance, taking care alſo that the order of the laſt Parliament touching elections ſhould be duly and punctually obſerved,
<note place="margin">Elections for a new Parl.</note> as conſidering that the peace or ruine of the Nation would lye in their hands.</p>
            <p>His Excellency the Lord Generall in this <hi>interreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> accepts of ſeverall invitations and treatments in the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59927:54"/>City by ſeveral of the worthy companies, yet ſtill ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an eye to the main, he keeps cloſe to his Officers (who were not yet fully reſolved) and often confers with them in a more familiar manner than ordinary, whereby he ſo wrought on them, that at laſt he brought them to declare that they would acquieſce in the reſolves of the approaching Parliament; and indeed this was a ſhrewd forerunner of the fall of Independency, as I ſaid before, whoſe only hope was builded on the averſeneſs of theſe men to lawfull power, which when they ſaw fruſtrated they might well depair; yet endeavour once more to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour a confuſion, which being obſerved by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and that a diſcontented Spirit poſſeſſed ſome of the old Officers and Grandees, according to the power given them to that purpoſe, they ſend for all ſuſpected perſons, confining them unleſs they ſubſcribed an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to demean themſelves, quietly, and peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, under the preſent Government, and acquieſce ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſively in the determination of the Parliament next enſuing, which reaſonable engagement <hi>Lambert</hi> and ſome others re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſing, were carefully confined to ſeveral priſons, by which means the peace was wonderfully preſerved: but notwitſtanding all this care, ſuch were the reſtleſs endeavours of that divelliſh faction, that (whether by the neglect or treachery of his keepers is not yet known) <hi>Lambert</hi> gets out of priſon cuningly, who being a man of looſe principles and deſperate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, ſo encouraged the Phanatick party, and ſtirred up their drooping Spirits, that they began to threaten great matters, and for perfecting their wicked deſign, begin to gather to an head near <hi>Edg-hill,</hi> which they hoped would prove to them an auſpicious Omen for the beginning of a Second war, but Heaven would no
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59927:54"/>longer wink at ſuch intollerable villanies, for the ſins of theſe <hi>Amorites</hi> were fully ripe for judgment, ſo that they were diſcovered and quickly nipped in the bud, <hi>Lambert</hi> and his accomplices being ſo eagerly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued by Col. <hi>R. Ingoldsby</hi> that they were ſuddenly forc'd to ſcatter and ſhift for themſelves by flight,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Taken and ſent to the</hi> Tower.</note> neither was that ſo ſwift or ſecure, but that <hi>Lambert</hi> was taken priſoner by the ſaid Col. <hi>Ingoldsby,</hi> and ſent priſoner up to <hi>London,</hi> at which time paſſing by <hi>Hide park,</hi> on the twenty fourth of <hi>Ayril,</hi> he ſaw all the City Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments both of horſe and foot, Trayned Band and Auxiliaries, completed, armed, and trayned, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to hazard their Lives and Fortunes againſt all ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and factious Traitors to their King and Country.</p>
            <p>The news of this firſt appearance of armed loyalty being ſpred abroad into the Countreys,
<note place="margin">The firſt loyal mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</note> did ſo animate and encourage the old oppreſſed, that caſting off their fetters and fears together, they begin to appear in their wonted guiſe, and becauſe they were by the Phanaticks traduced as men of blood and full of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, not to be ſatisfied but with the utter ruine of their adverſaries, thereupon to undeceive the vulgar, who might poſſibly have been miſled by ſuch lies, if not anſwered, did from their ſeveral and reſpective Counties, as alſo in the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> declare,
<note place="margin">The Gentry declare.</note> 
               <q>that they were far from any thoughts of revenge, it belonging to God alone (alluding to that text of Scripture, <hi>Vengeance is mine, I will repay ſaith the Lord</hi>) but as for Juſtice they would acquieſce in the judgment of the approaching Parliament.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This being done,
<note place="margin">The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins.</note> and the whole Parliament at the appointed time, beginning firſt with their duty to God (they follow that golden <hi>Pythagorean</hi> rule.)
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59927:55"/>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>)—</l>
               </q> giving him hearty thanks for that their freedome of meeting, which when they had cordially done, they fell in order to their Governour —</p>
            <p>Firſt, They fear God, then honour the King. As the ſame Pythagoras goes on;
<q>
                  <l>—<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </q> The very Heathen we ſee, by the meer light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, could dictate that which our Grand <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> of Religion would not for theſe many years, by the <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> of their new lighted notion walk after. But the Parliament were better principled, for after their devotions regularly paid to God, they in the very next place own their duty to their Prince, upon the firſt day of <hi>May</hi> (a happy day to be remembred to poſterity) voting the Government to be by King,
<note place="margin">Kingly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment voted.</note> Lords, and Commons, a conſtitution ſo incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly mixed, that it may rather be admired then envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: neither were they ſatisfied to reſt there but on the Eighth day of the ſame <hi>May,</hi> cauſed his Majeſty to be proclaimed King of <hi>England,
<note place="margin">King pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed.</note> Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> which was performed with ſo much So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity and Joy, as I preſume <hi>England,</hi> I dare ſay hardly any Kingdome in the World, ever ſaw or were ſenſible of the like, the ſhouts and acclamations of the pleaſed people rending the very skies as a token of their extraordinary Thankfulneſſe to Heaven, and at night by the multitude of their bonfires, turning the Darkneſſe into a kind of lightſome day.</p>
            <p>This hapy beginning thus owned by the general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all honeſt men, made the Parliament reſolute to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59927:55"/>cute their begun endeavours; which the more orderly to do (for order befitteth men beſt both as Subjects and Chriſtians) they immediately prepared Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners,
<note place="margin">Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners ſent to the King</note> who were perſons choyce for their integrity and wiſedome, (like thoſe heads of the children of <hi>Iſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char</hi> which were men that had underſtanding of the times to know what <hi>Iſrael</hi> ought to do) being intruſted to wait on his Majeſty, and to deſire him to come to his Parliament and People with all convenient ſpeed. Before whoſe arrival his Majeſty had withdrawn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from <hi>Bruxels,</hi> not upon any account as was by the ignorant and malicious inſinuated, but out of a deſign of ſafe guard to his own ſacred Perſon, as knowing thoſe two principles of the <hi>Romaniſts, (ſi violandum eſt jus, Regni cauſa violandum eſt;</hi> and <hi>nulla fides ſervanda eſt haereticis)</hi> might prove dangerous, if not fatal to his intereſt as affairs then ſtood. He well remembred <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt his caſe ſirnamed <hi>Caeur-du-Lion,</hi> and what his detention once coſt <hi>England,</hi> and therefore had no reaſon to caſt himſelf into the like hazard. Therefore having diſcharged all Accounts whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever at <hi>Bruxels,</hi> he as (I ſaid) removes his Court to <hi>Breda.</hi> As that firſt, he might hold the more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and quick intelligence with his friends in <hi>England,</hi> where there hardly wanted any thing to complete his Reſtoration and the Kingdomes ſatisfaction, but his Perſonal preſence; ſo in the ſecond place he there knew himſelf ſafe, being within the juriſdiction of his beloved ſiſter,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>King at</hi> Breda.</note> the Princeſſe Royal <hi>Mary</hi> Princeſſe of <hi>Orange,</hi> whoſe tender love and zeal to him in his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction deſerves to be written in braſſe, and graven with the point of a Diamond.</p>
            <p>During the time of his reſidence there to ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59927:56"/>to be a ſecond <hi>Solomon,</hi> a Prince of Peace, and not onely ſo, but the moſt pious and merciful of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who was wiſe as a Serpent, yet innocent as a Dove, by the Honourable the Lord Viſcount <hi>Mordant</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Grenvile</hi> (ſince by his Majeſties ſpecial grace created Earl of <hi>Bath</hi>) Gentleman of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Bedchamber; He ſent a moſt gracious Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with reſpective Letters to the Lords, to the Commons, to the City, and to the Army:</p>
            <p>Whetein,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty firſt offers a Pardon for all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages and miſdemeanors againſt his Father,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration layes</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy <hi>dead.</hi>
                  </note> or himſelf, to all perſons (ſuch onely excepted as ſhall be excepted by the Parliament,) promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing likewiſe ſecuritie to all, whoſe guilt might otherwiſe endanger them, ſo as they laid hold on his Majeſties Pardon within</hi> 40. <hi>dayes after the publication thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He refers the purchaſers of Kings, Queens, and Biſhops Lands to Juſtice, to the Law, and to the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He aſſures the Souldiery of their Arrears for paſt ſervices, although done againſt him, and of incouragement and pay for the future under him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Declaration was received with no ordinary joy and ſolemnity, the meſſenger Sr. <hi>Iohn Greenvil</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59927:56"/>with 500. pounds to buy him a Jewell, and upon reading thereof and a conference had with the Lords, (who had now reaſſumed their Native right by taking their places in the higher Houſe) they agree unanimouſly each in their ſeveral houſe; That a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be ſent in anſwer to his Majeſties gracious Letter and Declaration, ſuperſcribed <hi>To his moſt Excellent Majeſtie;</hi> which were ſince more immediately drawn up and ſent by Commiſſioners (before prepared as is already mentioned) ſixe from each Houſe, who were in the name of both Houſes,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To give his Majeſty moſt humble and hearty thanks for his gracious Letter and Declaration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To deſire his Majeſty to return to the exerciſe of his Regal Office, and come to his Parliament and people with all ſpeed poſſible.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, to that purpoſe to deſire him to appoint a place for the Navy to attend him: the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners that went from the houſe of Peeres were theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>The Earl of <hi>Oxford,</hi> Lord <hi>Brook,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners names that went to the King.</note>
               </item>
               <item>Earl of <hi>VVarwick,</hi> Lord <hi>Berckley,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Earl of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> Lord Viſc. <hi>Hereford.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Of the Houſe of Commons were ſelected theſe following,
<list>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Charleton,</hi> Sir <hi>George Booth,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Bruce,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Holland,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Falkland,</hi> Sir <hi>Antho. Aſhly-Cooper,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Mandevile,</hi> Sir <hi>Horatio Townſend</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Herbert,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Cholmly,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Fairefax.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hollis.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:59927:57"/>
            <p>The City of <hi>London</hi> having alſo received the like Letters and Declarations, the Lord Mayor, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen and Common-Council appoint a loyal and humble anſwer to be returned, wherein they give his Majeſty thanks for his tender care, grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to their ancient and renowned City, which was ſent by theſe worthy Gentlemen.</p>
            <list>
               <head>For the City of <hi>London.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>Alderman <hi>Adams</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Recorder <hi>VVilde</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alderman <hi>Robinſon</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alderman <hi>Bateman</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Theophilus Biddolph</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richard Ford</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alderman <hi>Vincent</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alderman <hi>Frederick</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alderman <hi>VVale</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Lewis</hi> Eſquire</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Bateman</hi> Eſq.</item>
               <item>Alderman <hi>Bludworth</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Major <hi>Chamberlin</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colonel <hi>Bromfield</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>James Bunce</hi> Bar.</item>
               <item>Alderman <hi>Langham</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alderman <hi>Reinoldſon</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alderman <hi>Brown</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Nicholas Criſpe</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alderman <hi>Tompſon</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>All theſe Letters were ſent away, but the firſt that arrived to his Majeſties hand was from his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy the Lord General <hi>Monck,</hi> who by the leave of the Houſe ſent the ſame by his brother in Law, Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Clergies</hi> who was (as being the firſt) beyond all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion welcome, and after ſome long but not tedious conferences Knighted, and at length diſmiſſed with as much kindneſſe as he was at firſt received with joy.</p>
            <p>After whom arrived ſhortly all the forenamed Commiſſioners,
<note place="margin">Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners how received by the King.</note> together with ſome of the Miniſtry, and were received by his ſacred Majeſty, his two illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious brothers of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> and his ſiſter of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:59927:57"/>
               <hi>Orange,</hi> with demonſtrations of affections on both ſides ſuch as are not capable of a deſcription by my rude pen, for they were ſuch as may be imagined onely not defined, like the joyes of a condemned ſoul now at point to dy, when ſuddenly and beyond expectation it is not onely ſnatcht out of the very jawes of death, but mounted aloft into a ſeat of Honour, how it is even overpreſſed with the overflux of ſuch a ſudden, yet joyful change, and ſtands extaſied, not knowing, or at le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt not well diſcerning the realities of thoſe violent emotions under the happineſſe whereof it at preſent labours; which ſurpaſſing joy grown over, and they diſmiſſed with abundance of ſatisfaction, with all ſpeed his Majeſty according to the earneſt requeſt of his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament prepared for <hi>England,</hi> his Royal brother, the moſt illuſtrious Duke of <hi>York,</hi> Lord high Admiral, taking order for the Navy. And in the way to the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide his Majeſty was honourably entertained by the States General at the <hi>Hague,</hi> of whom having taken his leave, and thanked them for their Treatment and Preſents, he proceeded in his journey.</p>
            <p>During this time, the Navy under the conduct of General <hi>Mountague,</hi> was come to attend and wait on his Royal pleaſure; upon notice of which, attended by the Princeſſe of <hi>Orange</hi> and her ſon, and the Queen of <hi>Bobemia,</hi> he comes aboard the <hi>Naſeby</hi> Frigot,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The King comes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board for</hi> England, <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ands at</hi> Dever.</note> by him then named the <hi>Charles,</hi> and after a repaſt there, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with high ſatisfaction, pleaſure and content on both ſides, with his Royal and Princely attendants, he lanched forth, and quickly with a proſperous and ſafe gale of wind, <hi>anuuente Coelo,</hi> came within two leagues of <hi>Dover,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Monck <hi>meets him.</hi>
               </note> (a place formerly not ſo infamous for receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Barons in their rebellious wars againſt the King,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59927:58"/>and harbouring <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> as now it was famous for its loyalty in the joyful reception of its lawful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign) when he was come thither, he ſends Poſt for the General (being reſolved not to ſet foot on <hi>Engliſh</hi> ground till he came thither) who upon the firſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that happy news, preſently took Poſt to meet him, having before taken care for Pallaces to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him, and left order for ſeveral Regiments of Horſe to attend him, for his Majeſties ſecurity; Providing with valor againſt open enemies, and with prudence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt pretended and baſely falſe friends, which being performed according to Order, His Excellency waites upon his Majeſty at <hi>Dover.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is no ſooner come thirher, but upon knowledge thereof, the King Landed, at whoſe Honored feet in the moſt humble poſture of a Loyal Subject, on his Knees Our Great General preſents himſelf, and was received and imbraced by his Majeſty in the open armes of an endeared mercy, with ſo much affection as might well manifeſt the great reſpect the King bore to his high deſerts; for to ſhew that his embrace was ſignal, and far from a meer complement, he went nearer and kiſſed him. No endearment is ever thought too great, where there is grounded Love, neither reſted he there, but like a true friend and lover indeed, takes a delight in his ſociety; for the more clear de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration whereof to all the world, he took him with his two Brothers the Dukes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter</hi> into his Coach with him to <hi>Dover</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oreſaid,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>KINGS journey to</hi> London, <hi>and the manner of it.</hi>
               </note> where after a dutiful acknowledgment from the Magiſtrates there, and ſolemn though ſhort entertainment he rid to the City of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (ſo famed for her Arch-biſhops Sea) his Majeſty being in the middle between his
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59927:58"/>two brothers; and the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> and the General riding bare before him.</p>
            <p>In this Equipage with the whole Gentry and Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>England</hi> attending, and thouſands of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ranke; he arrived as I ſaid at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> being met by the Magiſtracy in their richeſt habiliments of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and by the Miniſtry of the place, who after a grave Speech and hearty Gratulation, preſented him with a rich Bible as <hi>He was Defender of the True Faith,</hi> and afterwards with a Golden Boul full of Gold, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring it <hi>as a Tribute to him to whom Tribute was due.</hi> From <hi>Canterbury,</hi> where he reſted all <hi>Sunday,</hi> and gave thanks to God his Father and mighty Deliverer. On <hi>Munday</hi> he came to <hi>Cobham-Hall</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> a Houſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Duke of <hi>Richmond,</hi> but without any ſtay there paſſed on the ſame night to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> from whence on <hi>Tueſday, May</hi> the 29. (the day of the week which was fatal for the murther of his Royal Father, but happy to himſelf, not onely for his Birth, but alſo for giving the firſt hopes of his long wiſhed and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for return by the Vote of the Parliament on <hi>Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> the 1. of <hi>May,</hi> and his being proclaimed <hi>nemine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicente</hi> on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 8. of <hi>May.</hi>) I ſay on that day, attended by the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> the Earle of <hi>North-hampton,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Cleaveland,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Norwich,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Shrewesbury,</hi> and many others with their ſeveral reſpective Troops of the choyce Nobles and Gentry of the Land, and his Excellency with many Regiments of his beſt Horſe, the Lord <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard</hi> with the choyce Life-guard, and the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey flocking in, &amp; cutting down Palmes, and ſtrowing the wayes with all ſorts of Fragrant Flowers and deck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lanes and Paſſage, with the greateſt variety of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59927:59"/>Country Pomps, Garlands, beſet with Rings, Ribands and the like, the Air ecchoing all along and redoubling the perpetually iterated <hi>Hoſanna's;</hi> He came to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don (The Metropolis of his Kingdome,</hi> whoſe prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were no leſſe ſumptuous then joyful,) making a ſhort ſtay onely at <hi>Black-heath;</hi> (a place many yeares ſince, and more then once noted and remembred for the tumultuous aſſemblies of ſeveral Rebels, but now much more famous for the united Congregation of the whole Kingdomes Loyalty) from hence about n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, order was given for a ſpeedy march to <hi>London,</hi> in which Major General <hi>Broun</hi> did lead the Van with a compleat Troop of Gentlemen, all in cloth of Silver Doublets: Alderman <hi>Robinſon</hi> followed him with an other ſelect company, the ſeverall Lords came after with their reſpective Troops, then came the Life-Guard: After the Marſhals and Heralds, with ſome antient Lords, the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and the Lord Generall bareheaded; and then his Majeſty rid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his two brothers, the Duke of <hi>York</hi> on the right hand, and the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> on the other; after whom followed his Excellencies Life-guard, and then the Regiments of the Army all completely accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with back breaſt and Pot. In this order they came to Saint <hi>Georges</hi> fields, in a part of which towards <hi>Newington</hi> was a Tent erected, in which the Lord Mayor,
<note place="margin">King rides through the Citie.</note> and Aldermen in their moſt ſolemne Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, with their Officers, Servants, Livery-men, and Lackeyes innumerable waited, to which place when his Majeſty came, the Lord Mayor preſented him on his knees with all the <hi>Inſignia</hi> of the City, <hi>viz. Sword, Mace, Charter,</hi> &amp;c. Which he immediately returned with promiſe of Confirmation, and conferred the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59927:59"/>of Knighthood on the Lord Mayor in the place, whereafter a ſhort refreſhment, three hundred in Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet Coats and Chains repreſenting the ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies paſſing on before, the Lord Mayor bearing the Sword before the King, they proceeded in an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent order and equipage into and through the City, which was all hung with Tapiſtry, and the Streets lined on the one ſide with Livery men, on the other ſide with the Trained Bands, both taking and giving great ſatisfaction, until at laſt even tyred with the tedious pleaſure of his Welcome Journey, he came to the Gate of his Pallace of <hi>Whitehall,</hi> which ſtruck ſuch an impreſſion of greif into his ſacred heart, by the Remembrance of his Fathers horrid Murther there, as had almoſt burſt forth, if not ſtopt or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called by the Joy he received from the acclamations of the people, and the thought that he was peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly returned after ſo many years unto His own Houſe.</p>
            <p>The King being come in, went preſently to the Banqueting Houſe, where the Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment attended for him, to whom the two Speakers ſeverally made an incomparable Speech, wherein, with great eloquence, they ſet forth the many years miſery under which the Nation laboured, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated the Kingdomes Joyes at preſent, for their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped happineſſe in the future by his Majeſties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration, and ſo commended to his Princely care his three Kingdomes and people, with their Laws and priviledges, whereto the King in a Majeſtick ſtyle, made this ſhort, but full return.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:59927:60"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That he was ſo diſordered by his Journey, and the Acclamations of the people ſtill in his Ears, which yet pleaſed him as they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of Affectiou and Loyalty, that he could not expreſs himſelf ſo full as he wiſhed, yet promiſed them, that looking firſt to Heaven with a Thank-ful heart for his Reſtoration, he would have a careful Eye of eſpecial grace and favour towards his Three Kingdomes, proteſting that he would as well be a Defendor of their Laws, liberties, &amp; properties, as of their faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus received and taken ſeveral Congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Entertaiments, and diſmiſſed his Noble, Honourable, Worſhipful, and Reverend Guard of the Nobility, Gentry, Citizens, and Miniſtry, he retired to Supper, and afterwards having devoutly offered the Sacrifice of Prayer and Praiſe to the moſt high, for his ſafe return, he went to his Repoſe and Bed. The firſt Beam that darted from our Royal Sun, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſuch a ſenſe of piety into the peoples Affection, that it even made them break into an Exceſs of Joy, it was that happy Omen of a vertuous Government, the admirable Proclamation againſt debauchedneſſe, (wherein ſuch is his Majeſties zeal) he takes no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his Enemies, but our ſin which had ſo long occaſioned his exile, not ſparing therein thoſe who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be his friends, yet by their prophaneneſſe, diſſerved him. A happy Prince and happy people
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59927:60"/>ſure! where the Extremity of Juſtice endevoureth to take nothing from the Subject but a Liberty to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, which ſo highly pleaſed the people, that their Joyes rather increaſed then diminiſhed according to that of the Poet.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>— <hi>Littora cum plauſu clamor, ſuperaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Deorum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Implevere Domos, gaudent, generum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſalutant</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auxiliumque Domus ſervatorem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fatentur.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Shores ring with applauſe, the Heavens abound</l>
               <l>With grateful Clamours which therein reſound.</l>
               <l>All men ſalute him, Father, Prince, and King;</l>
               <l>That home again their baniſh'd peace doth bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Which is further alſo expreſſed by the Poet in theſe words,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>— <hi>Largis ſatiantur odoribus ignes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sertaque dependent tectis, &amp; ubique lyraeque</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tibiaque &amp; cantus animi felicia laeti</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Argumenta ſonant: reſeratis aurea valvis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Atria tota patent, pulchro<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> inſtructa paratu</hi>
               </l>
               <l>— <hi>Proceres ineunt convivia Regis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Bonfires light the Skie, Garlands adorn</l>
               <l>The Streets and Houſes: Nothing is forborn</l>
               <l>That might expreſs full joy, while to his Court</l>
               <l>The King by Nobles follow'd doth reſort,</l>
               <l>And in their Feaſts Gods wondrous Acts report.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:59927:61"/>
            <p>So reſtleſs were the Nights of our pious King, that he began to account all time ſpent in vain and amiſſe, wherein he did not do or offer ſome good to his Kingdome: to this purpoſe, on the firſt of <hi>June,</hi> (the very next day but one after his Arrival, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with his two Brothers and Sir <hi>Edward Hide,</hi> Lord Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> with many other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable perſons, went by water to the Houſe of Lords, where having ſeated himſelf in his Royal ſeat, the Black Rod was ſent to the Commons to inform them of his being there: They immediately adjour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and with their Speaker, waited his Majeſties pleaſure, who in a ſhort ſpeech acquainted them with the Occaſion and Cauſe of his preſent ſending for them, <hi>viz.</hi> To paſs thoſe Bills which he underſtood were prepared for him; the ſaid Bills being therefore read according to ancient form by the Clerk of the Crown, were paſſed by his Majeſty,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Bill conſtituting the preſent Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be a Parliament.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For authorizing the Act of Parliament for 70000. <hi>l. per menſ.</hi> for 3 moneths.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, For Continuance of <hi>Eaſter</hi> Term and all proceedings at Law, which done the Lord Chancellor <hi>Hide</hi> in a pithy Speech, told both Houſes with how much readineſſe his Majeſty had paſſed theſe Acts and how willing they ſhould at all times hereafter find him, to paſs any other that might tend to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and benefit of the people, deſiring in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties behalf, the Bill of Oblivion to be ſpeeded, that the people might ſee and know his Majeſties ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary gracious care to eaſe and free them from
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59927:61"/>their doubts and fears, and that he had not forgotten his gracious Declaration made at <hi>Breda,</hi> but that he would in all points make good the ſame.</p>
            <p>Things being brought to that happy iſſue, the King wholly intends to ſettle the Kingdome, and becauſe that in the multitude of Counſellors there is both peace and ſafety, he nominates and elects to himſelf a Privy Councel, whereof were,
<list>
                  <item>The Duke of <hi>York</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Duke of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Duke of <hi>Somerſet.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Duke of <hi>Albemarle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Marquiſs of <hi>Ormond.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Earl of <hi>Mancheſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Earl of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Earl of <hi>Northampton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Seymour.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Say.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Howard.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Atho. Aſhly Cooper.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William Morris.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Hollis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Anneſley.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>On ſeveral ſuch men he beſtowed great offices, as Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond</hi> to be Lord Steward of His Honourable Houſhold. The Earl of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> Lord Chamberlain. The Duke of <hi>Albemarle</hi> to be Maſter of the Horſe, and Knight of the Garter. Sir <hi>Will. Morris</hi> one of the Secretaries of State: which took up ſome time, in which the Parliament according to the Kings deſire proceeded in the Act of Oblivion, which at laſt, after many tedious and ſtrong debates paſſed both Houſes, and on the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> in the Twelfth year of his Majeſties Reign, had his Royal aſſent and was confirmed, wherein were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted from pardon both as to Life and Eſtate,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59927:62"/>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Liſle</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>VVilliam Say</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Hardreſſe VValler</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Valentine VVauton</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Harriſon</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward Whalley</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Hewſon</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>VVilliam Goffe</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cornelius Holland</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Chaloner</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Carew</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Jones</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Miles Corbet</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry Smith</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gregory Clement</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas VVogan</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Heveningham</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſaac Pennington</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry Martin</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Barkſtead</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gilbert Millington</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edmund Ludlow</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edmund Harvey</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Scot</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>VVilliam Cauley</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Downes</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nicholas Love</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vincent Potter</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Auguſtine Garland</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Dixwell</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>George Fleetwood</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Simon Meyne</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Michael Liveſey</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Titchburn</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Owen Row</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Lilburn</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Adrian Scroop</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Okey</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>James Temple</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Peter Temple</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Daniel Blagrave</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas VVayte</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Cooke</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Andrew Broughton</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward Dendy</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>VVilliam Hewlet</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hugh Peters</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Francis Hacker,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Daniel Axtell.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Who had fate in judgement on, ſentenced to death and did ſign the inſtrument for the horrid murther, and taking away the precious Life of our late Soveraign Lord King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of Glorious memory; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of whom have by divers means in ſundry places been taken, and others have ſurrendred themſelves
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59927:62"/>according to a Proclamation of ſummons ſet out by the King for that purpoſe, the perſons that ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred themſelves were theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Owen Row</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Auguſtine Garland</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Edmund Harvey</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Smith</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Marten</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Simon Meyne</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVilliam Heveningham</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iſaac Pennington</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Hardreſs Valler</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robert Titchborn</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>George Fleetwood</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>James Temple</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas VVayte</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peter Temple</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robert Lilburn</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gilbert Millingon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vincent Potter,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas VVogan,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>and</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn Downes,</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And therefore though they be all attainted &amp; convicted of High Treaſon by the Law of the Land at a fair and legal Trial by a ſpecial Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner</hi> directed to ſeveral of the Judges learned in the Law, and to divers other worthy and honourable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, yet they are not to ſuffer the pains of death, but their executions are to be ſuſpended until his Majeſty by the advice and aſſent of the Lords and Commons in Parliament ſhall order the execution by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to be paſſed to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The perſons that have been taken were,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Harriſon</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Adrian Scroop</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Carew</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Iones</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Francis Hacker</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gregory Clement</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Scot</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Cooke</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hugh Peters</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Daniel Axtel,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>VVilliam Heulet.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:59927:63"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Harriſon</hi> having received his Tryal, and being condemned to be hanged, drawn and quartered, accordingly on <hi>Saturday</hi> betwixt nine and ten of the clock in the morning the thirteenth of <hi>October</hi> 1660, he was drawn upon a hurdle from <hi>Newgate,</hi> to the place that is rayled in by <hi>Charing-croſs,</hi> where a Gibbet was erected, and he hanged with his face looking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Banqueting-houſe at <hi>White-hall</hi> (the fatal place pitched upon by thoſe infernal Regicides, for the ſolemn murther of our late Soveraign <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, of glorious memory) when he was half dead, the common Hangman cut him down, cut off his privy members before his eyes, then burned his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels, ſevered his head from his body, and divided his body into four quarters, which were ſent back up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame ſledge that carried it, to the priſon of <hi>Newgate,</hi> from thence his head was brought and ſet on a pole at the <hi>South</hi> end of <hi>Weſtminſter-hall,</hi> look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing toward the City of <hi>London,</hi> but his Quarters are expoſed to view, as a publick example upon ſome of the Gates of the ſame City.</p>
            <p>His pleading at his arraignment were nothing but treaſonable and ſeditious ſpeeches, rather juſtifying the crime he had committed, then any whit relenting; and ſo he continued a deſperate Schiſmatick to the Church of <hi>England</hi> to the laſt moment of his breath.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>John Carew</hi> was the next that followed, who at the time of his tryal, endeavoured onely to juſtify the late Rump and their actings, but that would not ſerve his turn, for it was proved that he did conſult and meet together with others how to put the King to death, that he ſate at the time of the ſentence, and ſigned the Warrant for execution, ſo that the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59927:63"/>Jury found him guilty of compaſſing and imagining the Kings death; for which he was alſo condemned to be hanged, drawn, and quartered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſentence on <hi>Monday</hi> the fifteenth of <hi>October,</hi> in the morning, was put in execution on the body of the ſaid <hi>Carew,</hi> his Quarters being likewiſe carried back on the Hurdle to <hi>Newgate;</hi> but ſuch was the goodneſs of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that upon the humble interceſſion of his friends, he was graciouſly pleaſed to give them his body to be buried, though his execrable treaſons had merited the contrary.</p>
            <p n="3,4">3, 4. The next in order, were Mr. <hi>John Coke</hi> the Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citor, and Mr. <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> that Carnal Prophet, and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitical Chaplain to the trayterous High Court; upon <hi>Cooke</hi>'s Trial it was proved againſt him, that he exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined witneſſes againſt the King, that he was at the drawing of the Charge, that he exhibited it in the name of the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, and the good people of <hi>England,</hi> that this Charge was of High Treaſon, that he complained of delayes, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Charge might be taken <hi>pro Confeſſo,</hi> and at laſt, that it was not ſo much he as innocent blood that demanded Juſtice, and that notwithſtanding all this, he acknowledged the King to be a gracious and wiſe King, upon which the Jury found him guilty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Then <hi>Peters</hi> was ſet to the Bar, againſt whom was proved, that he did at five ſeveral places conſult about the Kings death, at <hi>Windſor,</hi> at <hi>Ware,</hi> in <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-ſtreet,</hi> in the <hi>Painted Chamber,</hi> and in <hi>Bradſhaw</hi>'s houſe, that he compared the King to <hi>Barrabas,</hi> and preached to binde their Kings in chaines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That he had been in <hi>New England,</hi> that he came thence to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the King and foment war, that he had been in
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:59927:64"/>arms, and called the day of his Majeſties Tryal a glorious day, reſembling the judging of the world by the Saints that he prayed for it in the <hi>Painted Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> preached for it at <hi>White-hall,</hi> St. <hi>James</hi>'s Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, St. <hi>Sepulchres,</hi> and other places: upon which proofes the Jury finding him guilty alſo, of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and imagining the Kings death, the Court ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced them, <hi>viz.</hi> (<hi>Cooke</hi> and <hi>Peters</hi> both) to be led back to the place from whence they came, and from thence to be drawn upon a Hurdle to the place of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> On <hi>Tueſday</hi> following, being the ſixteenth of <hi>October,</hi> they were drawn upon two Hurles to the rayled place near <hi>Charing-croſs,</hi> and executed in the ſame manner as the former, and their Quarters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the place whence they came: ſince which, the head of <hi>Iohn Cooke</hi> is ſet on a Pole on the <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt</hi> end of <hi>Weſtminſter-hall</hi> (on the left of Mr. <hi>Harri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi>) looking towards <hi>London;</hi> And the head of Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> is placed on <hi>London</hi> Bridge, their Quarters alſo being expoſed upon the tops of ſome of the Gates of the City.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The next brought to Tryal, were <hi>Scot</hi> and <hi>Clement, Scroope,</hi> and <hi>Iones;</hi> againſt <hi>Thomas Scot</hi> was proved, that he did ſit and conſult about the Kings death, that he agreed to the ſentence, and ſigned the Warrant, whereby the King was murthered, that ſince he hath owned the buſineſs of the Kings death, by glorying in it, defending it, and ſaying he would have it engraven on his Tomb-ſtone, that all the world might know it, which being high aggravations of his crime, he was ſoon found Guilty by the Jury.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Then <hi>Gregory Clement</hi> was ſet to the Bar, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately confeſſed himſelf Guilty, <hi>modo &amp; forma,</hi> and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:59927:64"/>ſo without troubling the Jury was ſet aſide till Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Next was brought Mr. <hi>Iohn Iones</hi> againſt whom the proofs were ſhort, that he did ſit upon the King in that monſtrous Court, and that he ſigned the Sentence and horrid Inſtrument whereby the King was ordered to be put to death, upon which the Jury found him guilty.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Then <hi>Scroop</hi> was tried upon the like Indictment for compaſſing the Kings death, and againſt him was proved that he ſate in the Court, and did Sentence the King, and ſign the bloody Warrant, and after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of his Majeſty that now is, juſtified the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of that deteſtable murther, for which the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry finding him guilty, the Court gave ſentence of death againſt them as the former to ſuffer as Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and accordingly on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 17. of <hi>October,</hi> about 9. of the clock in the morning. Mr. <hi>Thomas Scot,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gregory Clement</hi> were brought on ſeveral hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles to the Gibbet erected near <hi>Charing-croſs,</hi> and were there hanged, bowelled and quartered, and about an houre after Mr. <hi>Adrian Scroop,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Iohn Jones</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one hurdle were carried to the ſame place, and ſuffered the ſame pains of death, being afterwards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and thence their quarters placed on ſeveral of the City Gates, and their heads deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly diſpoſed on the top of <hi>London</hi> Bridge and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places.</p>
            <p>Theſe being thus diſpatched, &amp; having received the reward of their Treaſon, Mr. <hi>Daniel Axtel,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Francis Hacker</hi> were brought before the Court to be tried; Againſt the firſt of whom, <hi>viz. Axtell,</hi> was in proof, that is the imagining and compaſſing the death
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:59927:65"/>of the King, that he bid his Souldiers cry out Juſtice, Juſtice, and Execution, Execution; and beat them till they did it; That he bid ſhoot the Lady that ſpoke and call'd <hi>Cromwel</hi> Traytor, ſaying, not a quarter of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England</hi> conſented to their wicked Charge; that he ſaid to Col. <hi>Huncks</hi> upon his refuſal to ſign the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for executing the King: <hi>I am aſhamed of you, the Ship is now coming into Harbour, and will you ſtrike ſayle before we come to Anchor;</hi> that he laughed at the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, as applauding them while others ſighed; that after the King was murthered, he kept Guards upon the dead body, and knew who cut off the Kings head, having ſent one <hi>Eliſha Axtell</hi> for the Executioner; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which proof the Jury found him guilty of the ſaid Treaſon whereof he ſtood indicted.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Francis Hacker</hi> was arraigned, and by diverſe witneſſes it was ſworn againſt him, that he was Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the Halbeteers, who kept the King priſoner, and would not ſuffer any acceſſe to be unto him; that he guarded him to their mock-Court, and after kept him ſure till he was murthered; that he was one of the perſons to whom the Warrant for execution was dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and that he ſigned it, that he brought the King to the fatal block and was upon the ſcaffold, being a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal agent about the Kings death; for which horrid Treaſon the Jury found him guilty: after which the Court ſentenced both him and <hi>Axtell</hi> to ſuffer death as Traytors, according to which judgement they were on <hi>Friday</hi> the 19. of <hi>October,</hi> about 9. of the clock in the morning, drawn upon one hurdle from <hi>Newgate</hi> to the common place of execution, generally called <hi>Tyburn,</hi> and there were hanged. Mr. <hi>Axtel</hi> was bowelled and quartered and ſo returned back and diſpoſed as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59927:65"/>but the body of Mr. <hi>Hacker,</hi> by his Majeſties great grace and favour, and at the humble ſuit and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of his friends was given to them entire, and by them afterwards buried.</p>
            <p>The laſt of this crew that was for preſent execution was <hi>Will. Hulet,</hi> againſt whom was proved that he was one of thoſe which came with a Frock on his body, and a Vizor on his face to perpetrate the horrid murther on the Perſon of the King, and that being ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed upon the Scaffold, he fell down before the King and asked him forgiveneſſe, being known by his voice; that himſelf ſaid, He was the man that beheaded K. <hi>Charles,</hi> &amp; for that he had one 100 l. and preferment. That <hi>Hewſon</hi> ſaid of him that he did the Kings buſineſs upon the Scaffold; That he either did cut it off, or took it up and ſaid, Behold the head of a Traytor. That being queſtioned about the ſaid words, he ſaid, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſaid it matters not; I ſay now, it was the head of a Traytor, with many other things to the like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for which moſt abhorred Treaſon, the Jury found him guilty, and he was condemned to be hang'd drawn and quarter'd at <hi>Tyburn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the deſerved Cataſtrophe that was ſet to theſe men, who without any reaſon, nay contrary to reaſon, Lawes both Divine and Humane, yea, even in defiance of Heaven, dipped their hands in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred blood of their lawful Soveraign, according to that of the Wiſeman, <hi>The eye that mocketh his Father,</hi> (Rex Pater Patriae) <hi>and deſpiſeth his Mother,</hi> (Eccleſia eſt Mater) <hi>the Ravens of the Valley ſhall pick it out;</hi> which which we ſee befallen them, their heads in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places being become a ſpectacle both to Angels and Men, and a prey to the Birds of the Aire.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:59927:66"/>
            <p>In the laſt place, it is provided by the ſaid Act of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion, that if <hi>VVilliam Lenthal, VVill. Burton. Oliver St. Iohn, Iohn Ireton</hi> Alderman, Col. <hi>Iohn Disborrow,</hi> Col. <hi>VVill. Sydenham, Iohn Blackwel</hi> of <hi>Moreclack. Chriſt. Pack</hi> Alderman, <hi>Richard Keeble, Charles Fleetwood, John Pyne, Rich. Dean,</hi> Major <hi>Richard Creed, Philip Nye</hi> Clerk, <hi>Iohn Goodwin</hi> Clerk, Sir <hi>Gilbert Pickering,</hi> Col. <hi>Thom. Liſter,</hi> and Col. <hi>Raph Cobbet,</hi> ſhall after the 1. of <hi>September</hi> 1660. accept or exerciſe any Office Eccleſiaſtical, Civil or Military, or any other publick imployment within the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>VVales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Barwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> that then ſuch perſon or perſons as do ſo accept or execute as aforeſaid, ſhall to all intents and purpoſes in Law ſtand, as if he, or they had been totally excepted by name in the Act. The like penalty is impoſed on all ſuch who did give ſentence of Death upon any perſon or perſons in any of the late illegal or Tyrannical high Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, or ſigned the Warrant for execution of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon there condemned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus by the bleſsing of God I have waded through the many intricate Meanders and Revolutions, untill at laſt I have as it were brought you by the hand to ſee that deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Faction of</hi> Indepencency <hi>(as one may ſay,) laid into its Grave; all the heads thereof being ſo annihilated by the Iuſtice of the known Law of the Land, that I hope its me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory ſhall be raked up in ſuch an Eternal forgetfulneſſe, that poſterity ſeeing no foot-ſteps thereof, ſhall conceive it to be a bare name, a mere notion, or</hi> aliquid non ens, <hi>of which in nature there can be no ſubſiſtance.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:59927:66"/>
            <head>An Appendix.</head>
            <p>HOw far the Treaſons of faction have reached, and how high they durſt ſoare is to be ſeen before, I ſhall onely now in ſhort give a hint how highly the Law of <hi>England</hi> reſents ſuch impious acts: I ſay then, the wiſdome and foreſight of the Laws of this Land in all caſes of Treaſon maketh this judgement: that the Subject that riſeth or rebelleth in forcible, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule the royal will and power of the King, intendeth to deprive the King both of Crown and Life, and this is no myſtery or quidity of the Common Law, but an infallible concluſion drawn out of reaſon and experience; for the Crown is not a ceremony or Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, but as Imperial conſiſteth of preheminence and power. This made former Traytors in all their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels againſt their Princes, not to ſtrike down-right, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God unto Lawful Kings did ever impart ſuch beams of his own glory, as Rebels never durſt look ſtraight upon them, but ever turned their pretences againſt ſome about them; this cauſed the Judges ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time to deliver their opinions for matter in Law upon two points.</p>
            <p>The firſt, that in caſe where a ſubject attempteth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to put himſelf into ſuch ſtrength as the King ſhall not be able to reſiſt him, and to force and compel the King to govern otherwiſe then according to his own royal authority and direction, it is manifeſt rebellion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, that in every Rebellion, the Law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as a conſequent, the compaſſing the death and deprivation of the King, as foregoing, that the rebel will never ſuffer that King to live or raign, which might puniſh or take revenge of his treaſon; And
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:59927:67"/>this is not onely the wiſdome of the Laws of our own Kingdome, but it is alſo the cenſure of forraign Laws, the concluſion of common reaſon, (which is the ground of Law) and the demonſtrative aſſertion of experience, which is the warranty of all reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the firſt the Civil Law, that ſaith, Treaſon is nothing elſe, but <hi>Crimen Laeſae vel dimminutae Majeſtatis,</hi> making every offence which abridgeth or hurteth the power and authority of the Prince, as an inſult or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading of the Crown, and extorting the imperial Scepter.</p>
            <p>And for common reaſon and experience, they cry, it is not poſſible that a Subject ſhould once come to that height, as to give law to his Soveraign, but what with terror of his own guilt, and what with the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the change he will never permit the King if he can chuſe to recover his authority, nay or to live Exper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence further tells us, and 'tis confirmed by all ſtories and examples; two notable ones we had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly in our own Chronicles, the firſt of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 2d. who when he kept himſelf cloſe for danger, was ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned by proclamation to come and take upon him the Government, but as ſoon as he preſented himſelf, was made priſoner, next forced to reſign, and ſhortly after; was tragically murthered in <hi>Berkly-Caſtle.</hi> The other is of K. <hi>Rich.</hi> the ſecond, before whom the Duke of <hi>Hereford</hi> (afterwards K. <hi>Hen.</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>) preſented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with three ſeemingly humble, but indeed flattering reverences, yet in the end both depoſed him and put him to death: but our own experience outvies all elſe, in the Horrid murther of our late dread Soveraign, which is related in the former parts, the puniſhment whereof is fully related in this laſt part, and therefore I ſhall no more thereof in this place.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:59927:67"/>
            <p>You may have obſerved that the practice of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicides was after they had ruined the Gentry, to advance their own kindred and allyes, though never ſo inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently unworthy, to the moſt profitable places of the Common wealth; by which means all kind of exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances were committed without controul, the Death of the King being attended with infinite oppreſſions, as in ſuch changes is uſual; which made Writers ſay, that the Death of <hi>Caeſar</hi> was no benefit to the Romans, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brought greater Calamities on them they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went befere, as may qe found in <hi>Aſpian.</hi> The ſucceſs was the like when <hi>Nero</hi> fell, for the next year that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed after his Death, felt more oppreſſion, and ſpilt more blood then was ſhed in all thoſe nine years where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he had ſo tyrannically reigned. So when the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> had expelled one Tyrant, they brought in thirty; and when the <hi>Romans</hi> expelled their King, they did not put away the Tyranny but only change the Tyrants.</p>
            <p>But ſuch and ſo tender is the hand of heaven over us, that he hath not only reſtored our Kings as at the firſt, and all our Counſellors as at the beginning; but brought us home our King ſo accompliſhed and pious, that we muſt needs confeſſe with the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe the Lord hath a delight in us, therefore hath he made him King over us.</p>
            <p>Oh then let us <hi>render</hi> without grudging <hi>unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars,</hi> acknowledge him as Gods imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Vicegerent, not preſcribing him in what manner we will be ruled, nor by what means: But in all things with obedience and humility to ſubmit to his command, like <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtata's Soldiers who would not ſacrifice at his words, <hi>ſed timendo poteſtatem, contemnebant poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> in fearing the power of God, they regarded not the power of man; yet when he led them againſt his
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59927:68"/>enemies, <hi>Subditi errant propter Dominum eternum, etiam Domino Temporali.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will conclude all with one word of Advice: Since God hath ſo bettered our condition, that our words are hardly able to expreſs our happineſſe, to avoyd the danger of a relapſe through a too careleſſe ſecurity, let circumſpection &amp; moderation take away all bitterneſſe, rather reflecting on the offences then the perſons of any offenders, ſo it may be thoſe concerned will not be ſo deſperate to proceed on further in their wicked courſes, but with ſpeed retire, and make ſome recompence to injured parties, by their future provident endevours for the Common good. And for theſe Loyal hearts who have borne the brunt of the ſtorm both at home and abroad; ſince God hath reſcued them as brands out of the fire; 'tis hoped they will be nothing the more ſecure in their vigilant care of future occurrences, having alwayes a provident eye for the timely prevention of ſuch inconveniencies, as might ſteal on them in their own, or be intended againſt them from forrain parts. That ſo the Throne of our <hi>Solomon</hi> may continue for ever, and peace be upon our <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Sed &amp; bene velle meretur veniam.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Cicero.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>☞ <hi>There is now in the Preſs ready to come forth, that ſo much deſired Book, intituled,</hi> An Exact Hiſtory of the Life and Actions of Hugh Peters: <hi>As alſo his</hi> Diary, <hi>Sold by</hi> H. Brome, <hi>and</hi> H. Marſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
